<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001522</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>960101</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>96-CH-0101</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001522</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metabolic Differences of Overweight Children and Children of Overweight Parents</brief_title>
  <official_title>Population Differences in the Insulin Sensitivity, Resting Energy Expenditure, and Body Composition of Overweight Children and Children of Overweight Parents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study focuses on the way weight is gained. Individuals who gain weight primarily in&#xD;
      their midsection (visceral weight) are at an increased risk for developing diabetes and high&#xD;
      blood pressure.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Research has shown that African Americans suffer more often from high blood pressure,&#xD;
      diabetes (non-insulin dependent), and heart disease than Caucasian Americans. These&#xD;
      conditions lead to significant numbers of deaths and diseases associated with and made worse&#xD;
      by obesity.&#xD;
&#xD;
      African American women in particular suffer from obesity and the associated conditions of&#xD;
      obesity more than any other race or gender. However, it is unknown if the conditions seen in&#xD;
      African American women are a result of the obesity or differences in their insulin&#xD;
      sensitivity, glucose disposal, or fat metabolism.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will compare body composition, total and resting energy expenditure, and glucose&#xD;
      disposal of obese African American and Caucasian children and of non-obese children of obese&#xD;
      African American and Caucasian parents, to characterize the timing and nature of factors that&#xD;
      may contribute to the prevalence of obesity and its complications.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients participating in this study will be followed for 15 years and be evaluated every 5&#xD;
      years during the study.&lt;TAB&gt;&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      African Americans have a greater prevalence than Caucasian Americans of hypertension,&#xD;
      non-insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus, and cardiovascular disease. These conditions lead to&#xD;
      substantial excess morbidity and mortality and are associated with and exacerbated by&#xD;
      obesity, the prevalence of which is strikingly elevated in African American women. It is&#xD;
      unknown if this increased prevalence of comorbid conditions is solely related to the greater&#xD;
      prevalence of severe obesity among African American women, or due to differences in insulin&#xD;
      sensitivity, glucose disposal, body composition, or fat cell metabolism. Through this&#xD;
      project, we have verified that many of the physiological differences observed between African&#xD;
      American and Caucasian adults are already present in obese children and in children at high&#xD;
      risk for developing obesity. However, the roles that differences in energy expenditure,&#xD;
      glucose metabolism, body composition, and other factors play in determining which children&#xD;
      develop obesity and its comorbid conditions in adulthood remain unclear. In this study, we&#xD;
      compare body composition, total and resting energy expenditure, and glucose disposal of obese&#xD;
      African American and Caucasian children and of non-obese children of obese African American&#xD;
      and Caucasian parents, to characterize the timing and nature of factors that may contribute&#xD;
      to the prevalence of obesity and its complications. We also relate serum levels of the&#xD;
      body-fat related circulating factors such as leptin, to these measures, and obtain samples&#xD;
      for genomic DNA isolation from participants and their parents to characterize the roles of&#xD;
      genes felt important for the development of obesity. We will follow these children for 15&#xD;
      years, studying them intensively at 5 year intervals until adulthood.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 6, 1996</start_date>
  <completion_date>April 12, 2018</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adiposity</measure>
    <time_frame>Yearly for 15 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">246</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Volunteers will qualify for inclusion under this protocol if they meet the following&#xD;
        criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Good general health. Individuals with renal, hepatic, most endocrinologic (e.g.&#xD;
             hypothyroidism, or Cushing syndrome), or pulmonary disorders (other than mild asthma&#xD;
             not requiring chronic medication) will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. For obese subjects, body mass index for age above the 85th percentile (determined by&#xD;
             NHANES I age-, sex-, and race-special data). For normal weight subjects of obese&#xD;
             parents, body mass index (determined by NHANES I age-, sex-, and race- specific data)&#xD;
             between the 5th and 85th percentile and both parents' current body mass index above 25&#xD;
             kg/m(2), or a history of a body mass index above 25 kg/m(2).&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. No significant psychiatric illness.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. At initial visit, Tanner I (prepubertal) or Tanner II (early pubertal) pubic hair and&#xD;
             breast stage of development for girls, and Tanner I or Tanner II pubic hair and testes&#xD;
             size (6ml) for boys.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Subjects must be able to undergo MRI. Volunteers with metal in their bodies that are&#xD;
             contraindications for MRI will be excluded. These include cardiac pacemakers, neural&#xD;
             pacemakers, aneurysmal clips, shrapnel, ocular foreign bodies, cochlear implants,&#xD;
             non-detachable electronic or electromechanical devices (such as infusion pumps, nerve&#xD;
             stimulators, bone growth stimulators, etc.).&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Age 6 to12 years at the start of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. For girls who have been followed to an age when they are menstruating (or are of an&#xD;
             age when pregnancy is a possibility), a negative pregnancy test.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Race of all 4 grandparents self-identified either as all Caucasian or all African&#xD;
             American.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jack A Yanovski, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yanovski SZ, Reynolds JC, Boyle AJ, Yanovski JA. Resting metabolic rate in African-American and Caucasian girls. Obes Res. 1997 Jul;5(4):321-5. doi: 10.1002/j.1550-8528.1997.tb00558.x.</citation>
    <PMID>9285838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yanovski JA, Yanovski SZ, Gold PW, Chrousos GP. Differences in the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis of black and white women. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1993 Aug;77(2):536-41. doi: 10.1210/jcem.77.2.8393890.</citation>
    <PMID>8393890</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ravussin E. Energy metabolism in obesity. Studies in the Pima Indians. Diabetes Care. 1993 Jan;16(1):232-8. doi: 10.2337/diacare.16.1.232.</citation>
    <PMID>8422781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 12, 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Insulin Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Race</keyword>
  <keyword>Body Fat</keyword>
  <keyword>Body Composition</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

