<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000502</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>21</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL028941-03</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000502</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of SC-V Versus Conventional CPR</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the benefits of a new method of cardiopulmonary resuscitation, SC-V CPR&#xD;
      (simultaneous compression and ventilation CPR) in terms of short and long-term survival and&#xD;
      lessened cerebral dysfunction.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Since the 1960's, developments in cardiopulmonary resuscitation have resulted in the savings&#xD;
      of countless numbers of lives. More recently, the emphasis has been on increasing CPR&#xD;
      capability through the development of prehospital emergency care systems and the involvement&#xD;
      of the lay public in the provision of CPR. The effectiveness of this technique in the&#xD;
      prehospital setting has been demonstrated in several community studies of patients in cardiac&#xD;
      arrest where survival rates ranged from 11-17 percent.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Additionally, for patients in ventricular fibrillation, the proportion of patients discharged&#xD;
      alive ranged from 14-30 percent in five cities where the outcome of EMS programs has been&#xD;
      examined. These successes, however, concealed many failures in which CPR could not reverse&#xD;
      death even though correctly applied within established periods between arrest and&#xD;
      resuscitation. However, considerable potential existed for improving CPR techniques and for&#xD;
      making additional inroads towards the estimated 100,000 deaths each year in the United States&#xD;
      that could be reversed through the widespread application of CPR.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A major goal of CPR is to maintain adequate peripheral perfusion (particularly the cerebral&#xD;
      and coronary circulation) during cardiac arrest while attempts are being made to restore&#xD;
      normal cardiac function. Maneuvers which increase intrathoracic pressure, such as total&#xD;
      airway occlusion during chest compression and abdominal compression by binding, have been&#xD;
      shown to increase carotid blood flow in the dog.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Sixteen periods of conventional CPR followed by SC-V CPR and return to conventional CPR were&#xD;
      studied in 11 cases of in-hospital cardiac arrest at Johns Hopkins University. The findings&#xD;
      indicated that simultaneous compression and ventilation at high airway pressures (SC-V CPR)&#xD;
      greatly increased carotid flow velocity and radial artery pressure over values achieved with&#xD;
      conventional CPR. Maximum benefit was achieved in patients in whom standard or conventional&#xD;
      cardiopulmonary resuscitation was least effective. The increases in flow index noted with&#xD;
      simultaneous compression and ventilation were up to 274 percent of control.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The success of this new method of CPR had been demonstrated during in-hospital clinical&#xD;
      trials. The benefits of this method suggested the need to test the technique in the&#xD;
      prehospital setting where the vast majority of cardiac arrests occur.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Units of the Miami and Dade County Rescue Squads utilized the technique in a mid-point&#xD;
      cross-over design. One of the three shifts at each of the study rescue stations had been&#xD;
      thoroughly instructed in the SC-V CPR protocol. A second crew was given an intensive review&#xD;
      of conventional CPR methodology. The third shift initially received the conventional CPR&#xD;
      review and continued to perform conventional CPR. After six months, the third shift was&#xD;
      trained in SC-V CPR and utilized the technique for one year. At the cross-over point, the&#xD;
      crew trained in SC-V CPR received the same intensive review of conventional CPR as did the&#xD;
      other crew. The conventional CPR crews, in turn, were trained in SC-V CPR. Total sample size&#xD;
      was 994 patients, 494 in the treatment group and 500 in the control group.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the Query/View/Report (QVR)&#xD;
      System.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1981</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1985</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Arrhythmia</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Arrest</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <condition>Ventricular Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Cerebral Anoxia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cardiopulmonary resuscitation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men, women, and children in cardiac arrest for which CPR was initiated in ten minutes or&#xD;
        less from the time of arrest.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krischer JP, Fine EG, Weisfeldt ML, Guerci AD, Nagel E, Chandra N. Comparison of prehospital conventional and simultaneous compression-ventilation cardiopulmonary resuscitation. Crit Care Med. 1989 Dec;17(12):1263-9. doi: 10.1097/00003246-198912000-00005.</citation>
    <PMID>2591221</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2000</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 27, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 25, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 25, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 26, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia, Brain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ventricular Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

