<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00006496</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>937</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL060710</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00006496</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Molecular Epidemiology of ARDS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Molecular Epidemiology of Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To examine the possible relationship between genetic factors and the acute respiratory&#xD;
      distress syndrome (ARDS).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) remains a major cause of morbidity and&#xD;
      mortality around the world. In the United States alone there are 150,000 cases per year.&#xD;
      Although there have been significant scientific advances in understanding the clinical and&#xD;
      pathophysical aspects of the syndrome, there is as yet no specific therapy for ARDS.&#xD;
      Moreover, although major risk factors for the development of ARDS include sepsis, aspiration,&#xD;
      and multiple trauma, only a minority of patients with these risk factors develop ARDS.&#xD;
      Individual differences in susceptibility to chronic disease have been a subject of active&#xD;
      molecular epidemiologic investigations for the past decade. In particular, risk factors for&#xD;
      cancer conferred by heritable polymorphisms and various metabolic functions have been&#xD;
      reported. More recently, a polymorphism of endothelial nitrate oxide synthase has been&#xD;
      associated with an increased susceptibility to coronary-artery disease, and polymorphisms in&#xD;
      GSTM1 have been associated with an increased risk of developing asbestosis. A recent study of&#xD;
      tumor necrosis factor (TNF) polymorphisms has been associated with poor outcome in ARDS.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The case-control study examined the association between specific polymorphisms in several&#xD;
      genes coding for specific inflammatory responses and for surfactant protein and their&#xD;
      potential association with increased susceptibility to ARDS. The first objective was to&#xD;
      assess the role of candidate-gene polymorphisms as risk factors for ARDS in a case-control&#xD;
      study. The second objective was to assess the relationship between genotype and phenotype for&#xD;
      candidate markers in cases and controls. The third objective was to assess the role of these&#xD;
      polymorphisms in clinical outcome (survival, recovery) using patients from both the proposed&#xD;
      case-control study and the multicenter case series and clinical trial sponsored by the NHLBI&#xD;
      ARDS network. By combining both a large case-control study and case series from the network,&#xD;
      the study had the advantages of sufficient case ascertainment, statistical power, diagnostic&#xD;
      standardization, uniform outcome criteria and study efficiency. Overall, the results of this&#xD;
      study should provide new insights into the epidemiology of ARDS and allow for possible&#xD;
      preventive strategies as well as possible modifications of therapeutic interventions for the&#xD;
      Network Phase III trials.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The investigators test the hypothesis that there is an increased risk of ARDS in patients&#xD;
      with heritable traits relating to inflammatory cytokines and surfactant. They are examining&#xD;
      risk and prognosis, and examining case and control genetics in relation to cytokine levels.&#xD;
      They also plan to do a case-series analysis from a separate study of the ARDS network. They&#xD;
      will examine TNF alpha and beta, interleukin-1 receptor antagonist, surfactant protein B and&#xD;
      interleukin-10 (IL-10).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk of ARDS</measure>
    <time_frame>From admission to ICU</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>From admission to ICU to 60 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Multi-organ Failure</measure>
    <time_frame>From admission to ICU</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4000</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Lung Diseases</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood will be collected for DNA extraction and plasma cytokine measurements&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients admitted to ICU with risk factors for ARDS&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Eligibility Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        All those with risk factors for ARDS - eg, pneumonia, trauma, sepsis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Vulnerable populations (incarcerated, pregnant, etc.) will be excluded from enrollment. The&#xD;
        following medical conditions will also exclude from study:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. immunocompromised patients&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. patients with chronic lung disease that may appear like ARDS&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. pulmonary vasculitis patients&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. patients with diffuse alveolar hemorrhage&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. patients treated with immune-modulating agents within 3 weeks of admission&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. patients unable to intubate because of DNI order or patient is placed on comfort&#xD;
             measures only&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Christiani, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Harvard University School of Public Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gong MN, Wei Z, Xu LL, Miller DP, Thompson BT, Christiani DC. Polymorphism in the surfactant protein-B gene, gender, and the risk of direct pulmonary injury and ARDS. Chest. 2004 Jan;125(1):203-11. doi: 10.1378/chest.125.1.203.</citation>
    <PMID>14718442</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gong MN, Thompson BT, Williams P, Pothier L, Boyce PD, Christiani DC. Clinical predictors of and mortality in acute respiratory distress syndrome: potential role of red cell transfusion. Crit Care Med. 2005 Jun;33(6):1191-8. doi: 10.1097/01.ccm.0000165566.82925.14.</citation>
    <PMID>15942330</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 16, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 16, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 17, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2022</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2022</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 15, 2022</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Christopher Christiani</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Newborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Lung Injury</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

