<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005612</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-12085</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MCC-IRB-5418</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-G00-1745</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005612</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination Chemotherapy Followed by Peripheral Stem Cell Transplantation in Treating Patients With Ovarian Epithelial Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>ETC</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of Intensive-Dose Etoposide, Topotecan and Carboplatin (ETC) Followed by Autologous Stem Cell Rescue in Chemosensitive Ovarian Cancer Patients With Either Minimal Residual Disease or at First Relapse</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so&#xD;
      they stop growing or die. Combining chemotherapy with autologous peripheral stem cell&#xD;
      transplantation may allow the doctor to give higher doses of chemotherapy drugs and kill more&#xD;
      tumor cells.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PURPOSE: Phase I/II trial to study the effectiveness of combination chemotherapy followed by&#xD;
      peripheral stem cell transplantation in treating patients who have ovarian epithelial cancer.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine the toxicity and potential efficacy of high dose chemotherapy (HDC)&#xD;
      comprised of etoposide, topotecan, and carboplatin (ETC) followed by autologous stem cell&#xD;
      transplantation in patients with ovarian epithelial cancer. II. Determine the maximum&#xD;
      tolerated dose of topotecan when combined with etoposide and carboplatin in these patients.&#xD;
      III. Determine the disease free survival (DFS) and overall survival (OS) in patients treated&#xD;
      with this regimen. IV. Measure the amount and subcellular location of DNA topoisomerase I and&#xD;
      II- alpha in ovarian cancer biopsies before HDC and at relapse to determine the role of&#xD;
      alterations of topoisomerases in the drug resistance of ovarian cancer. V. Correlate the&#xD;
      amount and location of both enzymes before HDC with clinical outcome (DFS and OS) and plasma&#xD;
      concentrations of topotecan and carboplatin in these patients. VI. Correlate the levels of&#xD;
      signal transducers and activators of transcription (STAT) and expression of bcl-2 family&#xD;
      proteins with response to chemotherapy and clinical outcome (DFS and OS) in these patients.&#xD;
      VII. Measure the levels of STAT and determine the expression of bcl-2 family proteins in&#xD;
      tumor biopsies before HDC and at relapse to determine the role of these cellular pathways in&#xD;
      drug response. VIII. Determine the pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic relationship of high&#xD;
      dose topotecan combined with carboplatin in these patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      OUTLINE: This is a dose escalation study of topotecan. Mobilization: After completion of&#xD;
      salvage chemotherapy and within 6 weeks of second look laparotomy, patients receive&#xD;
      cyclophosphamide IV over 2 hours and paclitaxel IV over 2 hours for 2 days. Patients then&#xD;
      receive filgrastim (G-CSF) subcutaneously daily beginning 24 hours after completion of&#xD;
      chemotherapy and continuing until autologous peripheral blood stem cells (PBSC) are harvested&#xD;
      and selected for CD34+ cells. High dose chemotherapy: After priming chemotherapy and within 6&#xD;
      weeks of second look laparotomy, patients receive carboplatin IV over 1 hour on days -8 to&#xD;
      -6; topotecan IV over 30 minutes on days -7 to -5 (beginning 12 hours after completion of&#xD;
      carboplatin infusion); and etoposide IV over 4 hours on days -5 to -3 (beginning 12 hours&#xD;
      after completion of the last topotecan infusion). Cohorts of 4-12 patients receive escalating&#xD;
      doses of topotecan until the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is determined. The MTD is defined&#xD;
      as the dose preceding that at which 6 or more of 12 patients experience dose limiting&#xD;
      toxicity. Transplantation: PBSC are reinfused on day 0. Patients are followed at 3 and 6&#xD;
      months, then annually thereafter.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: Approximately 4-30 patients will be accrued for this study within 3-4&#xD;
      years.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Low accrual&#xD;
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>August 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2004</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2004</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Progression free survival is defined as the time from date of enrollment to the time of recurrence</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>filgrastim</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carboplatin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>etoposide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>paclitaxel</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>topotecan hydrochloride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>peripheral blood stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically proven stage IIIC ovarian epithelial cancer&#xD;
        Chemosensitive to 6-8 courses of standard dose adjuvant chemotherapy (one regimen), such as&#xD;
        cisplatin or carboplatin in combination with paclitaxel, or any other standard dose regimen&#xD;
        Residual disease (no greater than 1 cm) following second look laparotomy Ineligible if no&#xD;
        microscopic disease present following induction chemotherapy OR Histologically proven newly&#xD;
        diagnosed stage IV ovarian epithelial cancer Achieved at least partial response (PR) (80%&#xD;
        or greater reduction in tumor by CT scan) following six courses of standard dose&#xD;
        chemotherapy (one regimen) OR Residual disease (no greater than 1 cm) or no disease&#xD;
        determined at the time of second look laparotomy OR Histologically proven relapsed ovarian&#xD;
        epithelial cancer Relapse following standard dose chemotherapy Chemosensitive Achieved at&#xD;
        least PR after 4-6 courses of salvage chemotherapy (total of 2 regimens) No more than a six&#xD;
        week interval between completion of standard dose chemotherapy and second look laparotomy&#xD;
&#xD;
        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 to 65 Performance status: ECOG 0 or 1 Life expectancy: Not&#xD;
        specified Hematopoietic: Not specified Hepatic: Bilirubin no greater than 2.0 mg/dL ALT or&#xD;
        AST no greater than 2.5 times normal Renal: Creatinine no greater than 2.0 mg/dL OR&#xD;
        Creatinine clearance at least 60 mL/min Cardiovascular: Ejection fraction at least 50% by&#xD;
        MUGA scan No severe cardiac dysfunction or major heart disease No angina pectoris No&#xD;
        ventricular dysrhythmias Essential hypertension allowed if controlled with medication(s)&#xD;
        Pulmonary: DLCO at least 50% predicted No symptomatic obstructive or restrictive pulmonary&#xD;
        disease Other: No active infections HIV negative No uncontrolled insulin dependent diabetes&#xD;
        mellitus No uncompensated major thyroid or adrenal dysfunction No other malignancy within&#xD;
        the past 5 years except nonmelanomatous skin cancer Not pregnant or nursing Negative&#xD;
        pregnancy test&#xD;
&#xD;
        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: Not specified Chemotherapy: See Disease&#xD;
        Characteristics No prior topotecan Endocrine therapy: Not specified Radiotherapy: Not&#xD;
        specified Surgery: See Disease Characteristics Other: No concurrent nitroglycerin&#xD;
        preparations or antiarrhythmic drugs&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen K. Fields, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2012</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 24, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 24, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 26, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stage III ovarian epithelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV ovarian epithelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent ovarian epithelial cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Ovarian Epithelial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Topotecan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

