<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001352</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>930106</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>93-I-0106</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001352</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cryptococcosis in Previously Healthy Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cryptococcosis in Previously Healthy Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This 5-year study will follow the course of disease in previously healthy patients with&#xD;
      cryptococcosis who developed the disease for no identifiable reason.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Individuals with a positive culture of Cryptococcus neoformans 18 years of age and older&#xD;
      without HIV infection or other condition predisposing to cryptococcosis (such as high-dose&#xD;
      corticosteroid therapy, sarcoidosis, or a blood cancer) may be eligible for this study.&#xD;
      Candidates who test positive for HIV infection may not participate.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants will have a physical examination, medical history, routine blood tests and&#xD;
      assessment of disease activity upon entering the study. Patients who may have active&#xD;
      cryptococcosis will also have a lumbar puncture (spinal tap) and additional blood tests.&#xD;
      Following the initial evaluation, patients receiving treatment for cryptococcosis will come&#xD;
      to the NIH Clinical Center as needed to manage their disease, typically no less than every 3&#xD;
      months. Other patients will be seen every 6 to 12 months. The visits will include a medical&#xD;
      history, physical examination, and blood and urine tests.&#xD;
&#xD;
      ...&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cryptococcus is a fungus that causes infections most commonly in immunocompromised patients,&#xD;
      such as those with AIDS and solid organ transplant recipients, particularly renal transplant&#xD;
      recipients (1-3). However, approximately one-third of cases fall outside these groups and,&#xD;
      overall, 12.9% to 17.9% have no readily identifiable immune defect (4, 5). The genetic&#xD;
      factors, which may predispose to cryptococcosis and the immune response in these patients,&#xD;
      have not been extensively studied.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This protocol is designed to examine the immune deficits that predispose to cryptococcosis as&#xD;
      well as the clinical and immune responses among previously healthy adults. The patients&#xD;
      included will have an unknown predisposing condition and cryptococcosis. Patients will&#xD;
      undergo blood, saliva, and tissue sampling. Throughout the study, patients will be provided&#xD;
      with standard medical care and will be seen as often as necessary to manage their condition.&#xD;
      Patients in whom microbiologic control of the infection has occurred but in whom inflammation&#xD;
      is causing neurologic damage may be treated with corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive&#xD;
      agents. Genetically related family members of patients will also be screened for clinical, in&#xD;
      vitro, immune, and genetic correlates of immune abnormalities. Healthy adult volunteers, as a&#xD;
      comparison group, will be enrolled as a source of blood samples for research testing.&#xD;
      Moreover, with respect to cryptococcosis, patients with isolated non-central nervous system&#xD;
      (CNS) disease (e.g., pulmonary) may serve as a subset comparator to those with (CNS)&#xD;
      involvement a major tissue tropism for Cryptococcus.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Genetic and immunologic testing will be performed on all subjects (patients, relatives, and&#xD;
      healthy volunteers) to evaluate for possible immunogenetic factors that lead to&#xD;
      susceptibility to cryptococcosis. Among the aims of this protocol are to better understand&#xD;
      the pathophysiology and genetic factors that lead to defects in host defense and to use&#xD;
      modern and evolving methods in molecular and cellular biology to elucidate the pathogenesis&#xD;
      of this particular susceptibility. A better understanding of the underlying pathophysiology&#xD;
      of immune defects and genetic susceptibility to fungal infections could allow for the&#xD;
      rational development of novel therapies for such diseases and to benefit future patients.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 1993</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurologic improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>1-2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement of neurological disability</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Cryptococcus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Genetic Relatives</arm_group_label>
    <description>Controls</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Controls</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Population</arm_group_label>
    <description>Adult patients with cryptococcosis no predisposing conditions except ICL</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Previously healthy patients with cryptococcal meningitis&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Have cryptococcosis as determined by information collected from their medical records,&#xD;
             telephone interviews or from a referring physician:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  histopathology showing cryptococci; or&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  culture of C. neoformans or C. gattii&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  a positive cryptococcal antigen in the serum and/or CSF, together with CSF cell&#xD;
                  count and chemistry consistent with cryptococcal meningitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Be over the age of 18 years old.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Have a primary physician outside of the NIH.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Agree to undergo genetic testing that will include WES and high density SNP arrays as&#xD;
             appropriate for possible WES linkage studies.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Allow samples to be stored for future research.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Pregnant patient willnot be excluded; However, research procedures greater than&#xD;
             minimal risk including bone marrow biopsy and apheresis would not be performed on&#xD;
             pregnant subjects. Otherwise, pregnant patients with cryptococcus would be treated as&#xD;
             per standard of care, minimizing teratogenic potential of drugs and ionizing radiation&#xD;
             whenever possible.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Genetic Relatives of Patients:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Genetic relatives must:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Be a genetic relative of a patient enrolled in this study&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Be over the age of 18 years old&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Agree to undergo genetic testing that may include WES and high density SNP analysis&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Allow samples to be stored for future research&#xD;
&#xD;
        Healthy Volunteers:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Healthy volunteers must:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Be between the ages of 18 and 70 years old&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Allow samples to be stored for future research&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients will be excluded for any of the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. The presence of certain types of acquired abnormalities of immunity due to:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  HIV&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Cancer chemotherapeutic agent(s)&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  An underlying malignancy could be grounds for possible exclusion of a patient if&#xD;
                  in the opinion of the investigator, the underlying disease predisposed the&#xD;
                  patient to the infection&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Monoclonal antibody therapy directed against a patient s immune system&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Any condition that in the medical opinion of the investigator may interfere with the&#xD;
             evaluation of a co-existing abnormality of immunity that is exclude patients with&#xD;
             Cushing s disease that have very high cortisol levels at the time of diagnosis of&#xD;
             their cryptococcosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Genetic Relatives of Patients:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Genetic relatives will be excluded for the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnancy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any condition that in the medical opinion of the investigator may interfere with&#xD;
             evaluation of an immune system abnormality that is the subject of study under this&#xD;
             protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Healthy Volunteers:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Healthy volunteers will be excluded for any of the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. History of HIV or viral hepatitis (B or C).&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. History of recurrent or severe infections.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. History of intravenous drug use.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. History of engaging in high risk activities for exposure to HIV;&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Receiving chemotherapeutic agent(s), immunosuppressants or have underlying malignancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Pregnancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Have history of heart, lung, kidney disease, or bleeding disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Any condition that in the medical opinion of the investigator may interfere with&#xD;
             evaluation of an immune system abnormality that is the subject of study under this&#xD;
             protocol.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter R Williamson, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Peter R Williamson, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 443-8339</phone>
    <email>williamsonpr@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1993-I-0106.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rex JH, Larsen RA, Dismukes WE, Cloud GA, Bennett JE. Catastrophic visual loss due to Cryptococcus neoformans meningitis. Medicine (Baltimore). 1993 Jul;72(4):207-24. doi: 10.1097/00005792-199307000-00001.</citation>
    <PMID>8341139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hospenthal DR, Bennett JE. Flucytosine monotherapy for cryptococcosis. Clin Infect Dis. 1998 Aug;27(2):260-4. doi: 10.1086/514669.</citation>
    <PMID>9709874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zonios DI, Falloon J, Huang CY, Chaitt D, Bennett JE. Cryptococcosis and idiopathic CD4 lymphocytopenia. Medicine (Baltimore). 2007 Mar;86(2):78-92. doi: 10.1097/md.0b013e31803b52f5.</citation>
    <PMID>17435588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 17, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cryptococcus</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cryptococcosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

