<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005457</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4901</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL039614</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005457</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Model-Free Time Curves for Longitudinal Data Analysis</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To enhance statistical methods for epidemiological studies by extending the Disturbed Highest&#xD;
      Derivative Polynomial (DHDP) to models for binary-logistic and Poisson data and by including&#xD;
      random subject effects in the Gaussian model.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      In previous work the investigator had developed the Disturbed Highest Derivative Polynomial&#xD;
      (DHDP) as a model-free time curve and had published the theoretical development for its use&#xD;
      as the overall time curve in a linear Gaussian model for longitudinal data with fixed&#xD;
      covariate effects and autocorrelated errors but without subject effects. For the logistic&#xD;
      model, the DHDP would replace the constant which appeared in the log odds in the&#xD;
      non-longitudinal case. The first-order DHDP was a straight line whose slope received random&#xD;
      disturbances over time. As such, it was capable of fitting a rich variety of arbitrarily&#xD;
      changing time curves. The second-order DHDP would generally provide a fit with smaller high&#xD;
      frequency variation. There are a number of longitudinal data analysis methods currently&#xD;
      available for Gaussian and binary-logistic data. They all have in common the requirement to&#xD;
      explicitly model the overall time curve--usually by a low order deterministic polynomial. The&#xD;
      main significance of this proposal was to represent the overall time curve by a DHDP, thereby&#xD;
      allowing the possibility for fitting arbitrarily changing time curves without explicitly&#xD;
      modeling the form of the change over time. The order of the DHDP can be selected by a&#xD;
      modification of the Akaike Information Criterion. The Poisson model should be useful in&#xD;
      fitting the periodic reported incidence of a rare disease. The relationship of the DHDP to&#xD;
      the Smoothing Polynomial Spline (SPS) was shown and methods were developed for using a SPS&#xD;
      instead of a DHDP in analysis. Robustness of the methods were examined by computer simulation&#xD;
      studies which evaluated and compared the ability of the DHDP and SPS models to estimate&#xD;
      covariate effects and time curves when the time curves were generated by processes other than&#xD;
      DHDP.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in&#xD;
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1991</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1994</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cioffi FA, Giammusso V. [Glucocorticoid therapy in head injuries]. Rass Int Clin Ter. 1969 Mar 31;49(6):370-7. No abstract available. Italian.</citation>
    <PMID>5397071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2000</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 29, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

