<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001281</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>910140</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>91-I-0140</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001281</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Studies of Blood and Reproductive Fluids in HIV-Infected and Non-HIV-Infected Persons</brief_title>
  <official_title>Studies of the Pathogenesis of HIV Infection in Human Peripheral Blood Cells and/or Body Fluids in HIV-Infected and HIV-Uninfected Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medstar Health Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the effects of HIV infection on substances produced by immune cells&#xD;
      that increase or decrease HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      HIV-infected patients and healthy normal volunteers may be eligible for this study.&#xD;
      Participants will be required to have a yearly medical evaluation, including blood tests for&#xD;
      cell counts and chemistries, a blood or urine pregnancy test for women, and other laboratory&#xD;
      tests as medically indicated or for research purposes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants will donate blood or reproductive fluids, or both. From 20 to 150 cc (4 to 30&#xD;
      teaspoonfuls) of blood will be drawn from the arm using a small needle. Participants may be&#xD;
      asked to provide blood samples on more than one occasion over the course of the study. No&#xD;
      more than 450 cc (less than 1 pint) of blood will be drawn during any 6-week period. Males&#xD;
      will be given a private room for semen donation; fluid from females will be collected with a&#xD;
      cotton swab after speculum insertion. Participants may also be asked to have a buccal swab.&#xD;
      For this procedure, the inside of the cheek is gently scraped with a blunt-ended stick or&#xD;
      brush to obtain cells (buccal mucosal cells). The tissues will be used for a variety of&#xD;
      studies on the effects of HIV infection on factors that increase or decrease HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Some of the tissues collected for this study may also be used for the following tests:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Hepatitis screening Blood may be screened for different types of viral liver infections,&#xD;
           such as hepatitis A, B, C, D, E, or G.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Genetic testing DNA from blood or cheek cells may be examined for mutations or deletions&#xD;
           that affect chemokines, cytokines and a family of enzymes called caspases. Chemokines&#xD;
           and cytokines are important mediators of the immune response. Alterations in the genes&#xD;
           for some of these substances influence HIV infection. Caspases regulate the process of&#xD;
           cell death, known as apoptosis. Caspase gene variations may determine the rate of cell&#xD;
           death in HIV-infected persons, and therefore, the rate of HIV progression. Patients with&#xD;
           abnormalities of any of these genes may be invited to join other studies of the role of&#xD;
           genetic defects in HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  HLA testing Blood may be tested for HLA type a genetic marker of the immune system.&#xD;
           These tests may be used to try to identify factors associated with the rate of&#xD;
           progression of HIV disease or related conditions. Determining HLA type is necessary to&#xD;
           be able to perform certain research studies. Some HLA types have been associated with an&#xD;
           increased risk of certain diseases like arthritis and other rheumatologic problems.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We are studying virologic and/or immunologic parameters of HIV infection and other infectious&#xD;
      or non-infectious immune deficiency diseases in order to better understand the pathogenesis&#xD;
      of HIV. Because of the lack of an adequate animal model it is generally necessary to utilize&#xD;
      human peripheral blood cells for studying aspects of either in vivo or in vitro HIV&#xD;
      infection. We wish to be able to continue to elucidate many pathogenic aspects of HIV&#xD;
      infection in relation to other infectious or non-infectious immune regulation and&#xD;
      dysregulation using human peripheral blood mononuclear cells as a model.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 9, 1993</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The purpose of this protocol is to provide a mechanism to obtain blood products and other biologic samples that will be used by NIH Intramural Investigators in studies of HIV and other infectious or immune deficiency diseases</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout</time_frame>
    <description>To provide a mechanism to obtain blood products and other biologic samples that will be used by NIH Intramural Investigators in studies of HIV and other infectious or immune deficiency diseases.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To provide the opportunity to compare genomic and proteomic properties of specimens obtained from individuals with HIV , other infectious diseases, and other immunodeficiencies with those of healthy volunteers</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout</time_frame>
    <description>To provide the opportunity to compare genomic and proteomic properties of specimens obtained from individuals with HIV, other infectious diseases, and other immunodeficiencies with those of healthy volunteers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2600</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>Immunodeficiencies</condition>
  <condition>Infectious Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV Infected Individuals</arm_group_label>
    <description>HIV infected Individuals</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV Uninfected Individuals</arm_group_label>
    <description>HIV uninfected Individuals</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Individuals with/without Immunodeficiencies</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals with/without immunodeficiencies</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Individuals with/without infectious diseases</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals with/without infectious diseases of interest</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        HIV-uninfected, HIV-infected volunteers, Volunteers with/without immunodeficiencies,&#xD;
        Volunteers with/without infectious diseases of interest&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  18 years of age or older.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Adequate venous access.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a blood pressure less than or equal to 180/100: pulse rate 50-100, unless a lower&#xD;
             pulse rate is considered normal for the volunteer.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have adequate blood counts (HIV positive volunteers: hemoglobin greater than or equal&#xD;
             to 9.0 g/dL, platelets greater than or equal to 50,000; HIV negative volunteers:&#xD;
             hemoglobin greater than or equal to 9.0 g/dL, platelets greater than or equal to&#xD;
             50,000)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Be willing and able to provide written informed consent on screening, comply with&#xD;
             study requirements and procedures, and comply with clinic policies&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willingness to allow blood samples to be used for future studies of HIV&#xD;
             infection/pathogenesis, and undergo hepatitis screening&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnant and/or breastfeeding females.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active substance abuse or history of prior substance abuse that may interfere with&#xD;
             protocol compliance or compromise patient safety.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan Moir, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Catherine A Seamon, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-3481</phone>
    <email>cseamon@cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Susan Moir, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-4559</phone>
    <email>sm221a@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY dial 711</phone_ext>
      <email>ccopr@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1991-I-0140.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jelicic K, Cimbro R, Nawaz F, Huang da W, Zheng X, Yang J, Lempicki RA, Pascuccio M, Van Ryk D, Schwing C, Hiatt J, Okwara N, Wei D, Roby G, David A, Hwang IY, Kehrl JH, Arthos J, Cicala C, Fauci AS. The HIV-1 envelope protein gp120 impairs B cell proliferation by inducing TGF-beta1 production and FcRL4 expression. Nat Immunol. 2013 Dec;14(12):1256-65. doi: 10.1038/ni.2746. Epub 2013 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24162774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Le Saout C, Hasley RB, Imamichi H, Tcheung L, Hu Z, Luckey MA, Park JH, Durum SK, Smith M, Rupert AW, Sneller MC, Lane HC, Catalfamo M. Chronic exposure to type-I IFN under lymphopenic conditions alters CD4 T cell homeostasis. PLoS Pathog. 2014 Mar 6;10(3):e1003976. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1003976. eCollection 2014 Mar.</citation>
    <PMID>24603698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Auerbach DJ, Lin Y, Miao H, Cimbro R, Difiore MJ, Gianolini ME, Furci L, Biswas P, Fauci AS, Lusso P. Identification of the platelet-derived chemokine CXCL4/PF-4 as a broad-spectrum HIV-1 inhibitor. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2012 Jun 12;109(24):9569-74. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1207314109. Epub 2012 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22645343</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 31, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lymphocytes</keyword>
  <keyword>Venipuncture</keyword>
  <keyword>Mononuclear Cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>.Identified data in BTRIS (automatic for activities in the Clinical Center).@@@@@@De-identified or identified data with approved outside collaborators under appropriate agreements.@@@@@@This study will comply with the NIH Genomic Data Sharing Policy, which applies to all NIH-funded research that generates large-scale human or non-human genomic data, as well as the use of these data for subsequent research. Large-scale data include genome-wide association studies (GWAS), single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) arrays, and genome sequence, transcriptomic, epigenomic, and gene expression data. De-identified data may be shared in an NIH-funded or approved public repositories, including the Database of Genotypes and Phenotypes (dbGAP) or in NCBI Virus Portal for viral sequencing.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Shared scientific data should be made accessible as soon as possible, and no later than the time of an associated publication, or the end of the award/support period, whichever comes first.@@@@@@Genomic data will be shared following the guidelines of the Genomic Data Sharing Policy, when applicable.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Identified data in BTRIS (automatic for activities in the Clinical Center and will be available for use following the BTRIS Policy for Data Sharing and Use).@@@@@@De-identified or identified data with approved outside collaborators under appropriate agreements.@@@@@@De-identified genomic data may be shared in an NIH-funded or approved public repositories, including the Database of Genotypes and Phenotypes (dbGAP) or in NCBI Virus Portal for viral sequencing and the use of the data within will be governed by their policies.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

