<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005655</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000121</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-C-0121</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005655</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00020163</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination Therapy of Interleukin-12 and Interleukin-2 to Treat Advanced Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Investigation of IL-12/Pulse IL-2 in Adults With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purposes of this study are fourfold. It will 1) determine what dose of interleukin-12&#xD;
      (IL-12) and interleukin-2 (IL-2) combination therapy can be given safely to patients with&#xD;
      advanced cancer; 2) evaluate the side effects of this treatment; 3) examine how the body&#xD;
      handles this drug combination; and 4) determine whether and how the therapy may cause the&#xD;
      immune system to stop or slow tumor growth.&#xD;
&#xD;
      IL-2 is an approved drug for treating melanoma and kidney cancer. IL-12 is an experimental&#xD;
      drug that has shown anti-cancer activity in animals, shrinking tumors and slowing their&#xD;
      growth. Animal studies suggest that given together, the drugs may be more effective against&#xD;
      cancer than either one singly.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients 18 years of age and older with advanced solid-tumor cancers (kidney, breast, lung,&#xD;
      sarcomas and others) that do not improve with standard treatment may qualify for this study.&#xD;
      Candidates will have a physical examination, including blood and urine tests,&#xD;
      electrocardiogram (EKG) and echocardiogram, DTH skin test (to test the function of the immune&#xD;
      system), chest X-ray and lung function tests to determine eligibility. Bone marrow biopsy and&#xD;
      imaging procedures such as CT and MRI scans may also be required. Patients over 50 years old&#xD;
      will also undergo exercise stress testing.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Treatment will consist of four courses of IL-2 and IL-12. On days one and nine of each&#xD;
      course, patients will receive three doses (one every 8 hours) of IL-2 intravenously (through&#xD;
      a vein). On days two, four, six, 10, 12 and 14, they will receive IL-12 intravenously. This&#xD;
      will be followed by a recovery period from days 15 through 35. This regimen will be repeated&#xD;
      for another three cycles; patients who show benefit without severe side effects may continue&#xD;
      for additional cycles. Treatment for the first cycle will be administered in the hospital. If&#xD;
      the drugs are well tolerated, additional therapy may be given on an outpatient basis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A biopsy (removal of a small sample of tumor tissue) will be done at the beginning of the&#xD;
      study, after completing the first treatment cycle, and possibly again when the cancer slows,&#xD;
      stops or gets worse, or if the patient leaves the study. These tumor samples will be examined&#xD;
      to evaluate the effects of treatment. Several blood samples also will be collected during the&#xD;
      course of treatment to monitor immune system effects. A device called a heparin lock may be&#xD;
      put in place to avoid multiple needle sticks.&#xD;
&#xD;
      ...&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Renal cell cancer responds to treatment with a variety of antiangiogenic and immunomodulatory&#xD;
      drugs.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the RENCA model of renal cell cancer the combination of IL-12 and pulse IL-2 cures 88-100%&#xD;
      of mice with established tumors.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The tumor regression observed in this model is due to both antiangiogenic and immunologic&#xD;
      effects.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Objective:&#xD;
&#xD;
      To define the maximum tolerated dose and dose-limiting toxicities of recombinant human IL-12&#xD;
      administered intravenously in combination with intermittent pulse recombinant human IL-2 in&#xD;
      adults with various advanced and/or refractory solid tumors.&#xD;
&#xD;
      To evaluate the pharmacokinetics of intravenous rhIL-12/pulse rhIL-2 administration in adults&#xD;
      with various advanced and/or refractory solid tumors.&#xD;
&#xD;
      To provide a preliminary assessment of the ability of rhIL-12/pulse rhIL-2 to modify&#xD;
      neovascularization and gene expression in the local tumor site, and to induce a measurable&#xD;
      antitumor effect in adults with various advanced and/or refractory solid tumors.&#xD;
&#xD;
      To evaluate the immunomodulatory activity of combined systemic administration of&#xD;
      rhIL-12/pulse rhIL-2.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Eligibility:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with advanced solid tumors for whom a proven more effective therapy does not exist.&#xD;
      Patients with renal cell cancer will be required to have received sunitinib or sorefinib or&#xD;
      refused this option.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The patient must have normal organ function and a life expectancy of at least 12 Weeks.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Normal pulmonary function (as documented by PFTs), and for patients over the age of 50,&#xD;
      normal stress thallium testing.&#xD;
&#xD;
      No prior treatment with IL-12.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Design:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Phase I dose escalation with an expansion cohort of 10 patients treated at the maximum&#xD;
      tolerated dose.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will be hospitalized for treatment. IL-2 will be given intravenously every 8 hours&#xD;
      on day 1 and this will be followed by intravenous administration of IL-12 every other day for&#xD;
      three doses on days 2, 4, and 6. After two days of rest the schedule will be repeated. Cycles&#xD;
      will be repeated every 36 days.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Tumor response will be evaluated after every treatment. Stable or responding patients will&#xD;
      continue treatment with evaluations after every cycle of treatment.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 28, 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 6, 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD and DLTof IL-12 in combination with IL-2</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">39</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Lung Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Breast Neoplasm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>rhIL-12 in combination with rhIL-2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rh IL-12</intervention_name>
    <description>rhIL-12 will be administered intravenously on days 2, 4, 6, 10, 12 and 14 of each cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rh IL-2</intervention_name>
    <description>rhIL-2 will be administered intravenously every 8 hours x 3 doses on days 1 and 9 of each cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Adult patients 18 years of age and older.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pathologically or cytologically-proven diagnosis of non-hematologic malignancy, and the&#xD;
        presence of radiographically or clinically evaluable disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with solid tumors including renal, breast, lung carcinomas, as well as sarcomas&#xD;
        for whom a proven more effective therapy does not exist. Patients with renal cell cancer&#xD;
        will have received sunitinib or sorefinib or refused this option.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must not have received myelosuppressive chemotherapy, hormonal therapy,&#xD;
        radiotherapy or immunotherapy within four weeks of entry onto this protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Estimated life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.&#xD;
&#xD;
        ECOG performance status of 0 or 1.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must be free of acute infection or other significant systemic illness.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Negative serologic testing for hepatitis B will be required to limit confounding variables&#xD;
        in the assessment of the potential hepatic toxicity of this combination.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Negative serologic testing for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) will be required given&#xD;
        the uncertain impact of rhIL-12 and/or rhIL-2 administration on viral replication, and the&#xD;
        potential alterations in immune responsiveness among patients concurrently infected with&#xD;
        HIV.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Adequate hepatic and renal function as evidence by:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Transaminases less than 2.5 times the upper limit or normal;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Total serum bilirubin less than 2.0 mg/dl;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Serum Cr less than 2.0 mg/dl or calculated creatinine clearance of greater than 60&#xD;
        ml/min/1.73M(2).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Adequate bone marrow function (without growth factor support) as evidence by:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Absolute Neutrophil count (ANC) greater than 1500 cells/mm(3);&#xD;
&#xD;
        Platelets greater than 100,000/mm(3).&#xD;
&#xD;
        For women of childbearing potential, a negative urine pregnancy test within 14 days prior&#xD;
        to initiation of study therapy is required. For patients of child-bearing potential,&#xD;
        contraceptive precautions must be maintained during study participation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Normal pulmonary function (as documented by PFTs), and for patients over the age of 50,&#xD;
        normal stress thallium testing. Normal pulmonary function testing will be defined as DLCO&#xD;
        greater than 60% of predicted and FEVI greater than 70% of predicted.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Critically-ill or medically unstable patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History or a presence of brain metastases.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of coronary artery disease, angina or myocardial infarction.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of clinically significant pleural effusion.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of malignant hyperthermia are.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent or history of autoimmune disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of congenital or acquired coagulation disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with a history of ongoing or intermittent bowel obstruction.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Women who are pregnant or lactating will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Systemic corticosteroids, radiotherapy, chemotherapy, or other investigational agents&#xD;
        within 4 weeks prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who have received any of the following agents with known immunomodulatory effects&#xD;
        within 4 weeks prior to study entry: G-CSF/GM-CSF, interferons or interleukins, growth&#xD;
        hormone, IVIG, retinoic acid.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with a history of previous therapy with rhIL-12 will be excluded from study&#xD;
        participation. For patients with renal cell carcinoma, a history of therapy with rhIL-2&#xD;
        will not exclude patients from study participation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with concurrent administration of any other investigational agent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with hematologic malignancies including leukemia or lymphoma.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of bone marrow or stem-cell transplantation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Intercurrent radiation therapy patients will be allowed on study if in the opinion of the&#xD;
        principal investigator(s) its use is not necessitated by disease progression. For patients&#xD;
        with disease progression, radiation therapy will be administered as clinically indicated&#xD;
        and the patient will be withdrawn from study participation.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas A Waldmann, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morgan DA, Ruscetti FW, Gallo R. Selective in vitro growth of T lymphocytes from normal human bone marrows. Science. 1976 Sep 10;193(4257):1007-8. doi: 10.1126/science.181845.</citation>
    <PMID>181845</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruscetti FW, Morgan DA, Gallo RC. Functional and morphologic characterization of human T cells continuously grown in vitro. J Immunol. 1977 Jul;119(1):131-8.</citation>
    <PMID>141483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubin JT. Interleukin-2: its biology and clinical application in patients with cancer. Cancer Invest. 1993;11(4):460-72. doi: 10.3109/07357909309018878. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>8324650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2, 2017</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 5, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 14, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 14, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Gene Expression</keyword>
  <keyword>Neovascularization</keyword>
  <keyword>antiangiogenic therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>immunomodulatory therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

