<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001630</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>970154</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>97-H-0154</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001630</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Autoimmune Thrombocytopenia (AITP)</brief_title>
  <official_title>High-Dose Cyclophosphamide With CD34+ Selected Autologous Hematopoietic Cell Support for Treatment of Refractory Chronic Autoimmune Thrombocytopenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Platelets are particles found along with red and white blood cells in the blood that play a&#xD;
      role in the process of blood clotting. Disorders affecting the platelets can lower the amount&#xD;
      of platelets in the blood and put patients at risk of bleeding. The condition of low&#xD;
      platelets is referred to as thrombocytopenia.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Thrombocytopenia can be associated with a variety of diseases including cancer, leukemia,&#xD;
      tuberculosis, or as a result of an autoimmune reaction. Autoimmune reactions are disorders in&#xD;
      which the normal immune system begins attacking itself. Autoimmune thrombocytopenia (AITP) is&#xD;
      a disorder of low blood platelet counts in which platelets are destroyed by antibodies&#xD;
      produced by the immune system.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Unfortunately, many patients with AITP do not respond to standard treatments for&#xD;
      thrombocytopenia. Cyclophosphamide is a drug that works to suppress the activity of the&#xD;
      immune system. Researchers believe that combining this drug with transplanted rescued blood&#xD;
      stem cells may provide effective treatment for AITP.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The purpose of this study is to explore the affordability and safety of this therapy for the&#xD;
      treatment of AITP. The effectiveness of the therapy will be measured by the number of&#xD;
      patients whose platelet levels rise greater than 100,000/m3.&#xD;
&#xD;
      If this treatment approach appears affordable, this study will form the basis for a larger&#xD;
      study to compare alternate treatment approaches.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Autoimmune Thrombocytopenia (AITP) is a disorder of low blood platelet counts in which&#xD;
      platelet destruction is caused by antiplatelet autoantibodies. A large proportion of patients&#xD;
      with chronic AITP are refractory to standard therapies including corticosteroids, immune&#xD;
      globulin and splenectomy. Cyclophosphamide is a cytotoxic immunosuppressive agent which may&#xD;
      induce durable remissions of refractory autoimmune diseases. High-dose cyclophosphamide with&#xD;
      peripheral blood stem cell (PBPC) rescue has been proposed as a potential definitive therapy&#xD;
      for AITP; however, the infusion of autoreactive lymphocytes could result in relapse. The use&#xD;
      of PBPC depleted of T-lymphocytes could circumvent this limitation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The purpose of this phase I/II study is to explore the feasibility and safety of this&#xD;
      approach, and to seek preliminary evidence of effectiveness, of using high-dose&#xD;
      cyclophosphamide (50 mg/kg/day x 4) followed by infusion of autologous PBPC enriched for&#xD;
      CD34+ cells (concomitantly depleted of CD3+ cells) for the treatment of patients with&#xD;
      refractory AITP. Safety/feasibility parameters to be examined will include the ability to&#xD;
      mobilize, harvest and purify sufficient PBPC to yield greater than 2 x 10(6) CD34+ cells/kg;&#xD;
      symptomatic acceptability and hematologic toxicities of the mobilization regimen (filgrastim&#xD;
      10 micrograms/kg/day IV); tolerability of the leukapheresis procedure, including the central&#xD;
      line placement and maintenance; depth and duration of blood cell nadirs following&#xD;
      chemotherapy; peritransplant bleeding episodes and transfusion requirements; episodes of&#xD;
      febrile neutropenia, culture-proven infections and antibiotic usage. Effectiveness will be&#xD;
      gauged by the rapidity and number of patients to achieve complete remission (platelet count&#xD;
      greater than 100,000/mm(3) and partial remission (platelet count greater than 50,000/mm(3) or&#xD;
      doubling of the platelet count with resolution of bleeding episodes). Ancillary evidence of&#xD;
      therapeutic effect will be sought by examining changes in titers of platelet surface&#xD;
      glycoprotein antibodies. In addition, alterations in T-lymphocyte subsets will be examined by&#xD;
      flow cytometry. If this treatment approach appears feasible, this study will form the basis&#xD;
      for a larger trial to compare alternate treatment approaches.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 21, 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 11, 2009</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Autoimmune Disease</condition>
  <condition>Autoimmune Hemolytic Anemia</condition>
  <condition>Thrombocytopenia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Isolex 300i</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Male or female, ages 18-65 years old.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Refractory severe chronic autoimmune thrombocytopenia, with or without autoimmune hemolytic&#xD;
        anemia (Evan's syndrome), with all the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Platelet count frequently below 20,000/mm(3) despite active&#xD;
&#xD;
             treatment for a period of greater than 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Normal or increased megakaryocytes on bone marrow&#xD;
&#xD;
             aspirate/bx.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. No plausible alternative etiology such as drug-mediated&#xD;
&#xD;
             thrombocytopenia, marrow failure syndrome or thrombocytopenia&#xD;
&#xD;
             related to viral or bacterial infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Failure of treatment with:&#xD;
&#xD;
        i. conventional-dose steroids (e.g., prednisone or dosage of 40&#xD;
&#xD;
        mg/day or equivalent, followed by dosage taper) for at least 3&#xD;
&#xD;
        months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        ii. intravenous immunoglobulin.&#xD;
&#xD;
        iii. splenectomy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        e. Episodic bleeding requiring transfusions or ecchymoses interfering&#xD;
&#xD;
        with ordinary daily activities.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        ECOG performance status greater than 1.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Cardiopulmonary disease including:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. History of coronary artery disease, angina pectoris or congestive heart failure.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. LV ejection fraction less than 40 percent by 2D echocardiogram.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Renal disease, serum creatinine greater than 2.5 mg/dL or creatinine clearance less than 30&#xD;
        mL/min.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Significant hepatic dysfunction, bilirubin greater than 2 mg/dL or transaminases greater&#xD;
        than 2 times UNL.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Uncorrected coagulopathy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Bone marrow aplasia (cellularity less than 10 percent), single or multilineage&#xD;
        hematopoietic failure, myelodysplastic syndrome, or extensive marrow fibrosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History or active diagnosis of malignancy (except treated non-melanoma skin cancer or&#xD;
        cevical carcinoma in situ).&#xD;
&#xD;
        HIV positive.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnancy or lactation, unwillingness to practice adequate birth control in the&#xD;
        peritransplant period.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Psychiatric illness or mental incapacity to understand and give informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Other medical illness or condition which, in the opinion of the Investigators, may&#xD;
        contraindicate participation in this study due to patients' risk or compromise of study&#xD;
        integrity.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Semple JW, Freedman J. Abnormal cellular immune mechanisms associated with autoimmune thrombocytopenia. Transfus Med Rev. 1995 Oct;9(4):327-38. doi: 10.1016/s0887-7963(05)80080-x. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>8541715</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karpatkin S. Autoimmune (idiopathic) thrombocytopenic purpura. Lancet. 1997 May 24;349(9064):1531-6. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(96)12118-8. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>9167472</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>George JN, el-Harake MA, Raskob GE. Chronic idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura. N Engl J Med. 1994 Nov 3;331(18):1207-11. doi: 10.1056/NEJM199411033311807. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>7935660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 21, 2011</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Immunosuppression</keyword>
  <keyword>Thrombocytopenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Autoimmune Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Evan's Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Autoimmune Hemolytic Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Episodic Bleeding</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Hemolytic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Hemolytic, Autoimmune</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombocytopenic, Idiopathic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autoimmune Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemolysis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

