<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001351</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>930086</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>93-I-0086</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001351</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation and Long-Term Follow-up of Patients With Inflammatory Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation and Long-Term Follow-Up of Patients With Acute or Chronic Inflammatory Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will investigate inflammatory diseases and disorders. Inflammation is the body s&#xD;
      immune response to many things, including infections and other acute or chronic irritants. It&#xD;
      may also be a sign of abnormal immune function. This study will allow evaluation and&#xD;
      long-term follow-up of such disorders to:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Establish and maintain a group of patients that may be eligible for other NIAID&#xD;
           protocols.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Provide clinical training and experience for NIAID fellows.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Provide a mechanism for NIAID staff to maintain their clinical skills.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Serve as a starting point for new investigations of syndromes not currently under study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients between 1 and 80 years of age with acute or chronic inflammation, including but not&#xD;
      limited to viral, fungal or bacterial infections, or abnormal immune responses may be&#xD;
      eligible for this study. Immediate family members of patients may also be enrolled for&#xD;
      preliminary examination to see if they are affected in any way that may warrant further&#xD;
      investigation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All patients and family members will have a history, physical examination and laboratory&#xD;
      tests. Depending on the results, family members may require additional tests. Patients will&#xD;
      have additional diagnostic tests indicated for their specific disease, according to accepted&#xD;
      medical standards. These may include routine blood and urine tests, X-rays or other imaging&#xD;
      studies, body fluid or tissue cultures, skin tests for allergic or immune responses, and&#xD;
      others as needed.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Treatments will include only medications approved by the Food and Drug Administration&#xD;
      according to accepted dose schedules and delivery methods.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients may be requested to donate extra blood for research studies. No more than 450 cc (30&#xD;
      tablespoons) will be drawn from adults within a 6-week period, and no more that 7 cc (1/2&#xD;
      tablespoon) from children under 18 years of age in the same time period.&#xD;
&#xD;
      ...&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Inflammatory disorders, including but not limited to those caused by viral, bacterial,&#xD;
      fungal, and parasitic infections, and those associated with aberrant immunologic responses&#xD;
      are exceedingly common acute and chronic disorders affecting humans. The pathogeneses of&#xD;
      these various disorders are being investigated under a number of NIAID clinical research&#xD;
      protocols. This protocol is an evaluation and long-term follow-up protocol of such disorders&#xD;
      for the purposes of maintaining a group of patients on which LCIM investigators draw for our&#xD;
      other various protocols. Also, this protocol may serve as a start point to studies of&#xD;
      syndromes or diseases not being addressed by specific protocols, and therefore, can be used&#xD;
      to evaluate family members of patients with inflammatory conditions when appropriate in order&#xD;
      to try to understand further the disease before embarking in a specific protocol. It is&#xD;
      anticipated that the patients will receive a degree of clinical evaluation, care and&#xD;
      monitoring more extensive that that generally available and that specimens collected from&#xD;
      them can sometimes be used for laboratory studies related to inflammatory conditions.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 1993</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>screening of patients for other protocols</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing through the study</time_frame>
    <description>screening of patients for other protocols,</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>evaluation and follow-up of interesting patients, who do not fit in our other protocols</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing through the study</time_frame>
    <description>evaluation and follow-up of interesting patients, who do not fit in our other protocols</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate family members of patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>immediate family members of patients with inflammatory conditions may be evaluated under this protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Inflammatory conditions associated with, but not limited, to acute and chronic infections or presumed infections, and congenital or acquired immunologic disorders</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        - Inflammatory conditions associated with, but not limited, to acute and chronic infections&#xD;
        or presumed infections, and congenital or acquired immunologic disorders@@@- If&#xD;
        appropriate, immediate family members of patients with inflammatory conditions may be&#xD;
        evaluated under this protocol, as a preamble to see if further investigation is warranted,&#xD;
        what would be done under a specific protocol.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITIERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Males and females ages 2 years and older.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Inflammatory conditions associated with, but not limited, to acute and chronic&#xD;
             infections or presumed infections, and congenital or acquired immunologic disorders,&#xD;
             as determined by the principal or associated investigators.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A NIAID/LCIM investigator has an interest in the patient s illness and is willing to&#xD;
             serve as attending physician to supervise the patient's medical care at the NIH.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  If appropriate, immediate family members of patients with inflammatory conditions may&#xD;
             be evaluated under this protocol to determine if they may also be affected by their&#xD;
             relative s disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willingness to participate in clinical protocols when appropriate.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects must maintain a primary physician outside NIH for non-protocol related&#xD;
             medical complaints and for emergency medical treatment required for these or other of&#xD;
             their disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willingness to have samples stored and to provide tissue samples for studying immune&#xD;
             dysregulation and for genetic analysis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ablility to provide informed consent or, for the patient cohort, has a designated&#xD;
             legally authorized representative (LAR).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  For females, not pregnant.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adriana R Marques, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1993-I-0086.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 19, 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Human</keyword>
  <keyword>Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunology</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

