<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00008892</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>010064</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>01-M-0064</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00008892</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brain Imaging in Children With AD/HD</brief_title>
  <official_title>Anatomic MRI Brain Imaging of White Matter in Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to use brain imaging technology to study the connections between&#xD;
      brain regions in children with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (AD/HD), and&#xD;
      comparing them to children without AD/HD.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will build upon previous brain imaging studies of healthy volunteers and children&#xD;
      who have AD/HD. This study will use diffusion tensor magnetic resonance imaging (DT-MRI) to&#xD;
      visualize and measure certain parts of the brains of identical twin pairs in which one twin&#xD;
      has AD/HD, combined type.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants in this study will be screened with questionnaires and interviews, psychometric&#xD;
      testing, and a physical examination. Participants' medical and educational records may be&#xD;
      reviewed. Participants will undergo an MRI scan of the brain. Prior to the MRI, participants&#xD;
      will have a training session in a simulated MRI scanner to learn how to lie still during MRI&#xD;
      scanning. Participants may be asked to return for a follow-up scan in about 2 years.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is the most common childhood psychiatric&#xD;
      disorder, present in between 3 to 10% of children in the United States (Wender et al 2001).&#xD;
      It is thought to reflect subtle anomalies in the central nervous system and thus structural&#xD;
      neuroimaging has been used extensively to delineate the neurobiology of the disorder.&#xD;
      Magnetic resonance imaging has demonstrated structural anomalies in ADHD, affecting all the&#xD;
      major lobes with particularly severe volume reductions in the cerebellum and relative&#xD;
      preservation of the caudate nucleus (for a review see Durston 2003). In structural&#xD;
      neuroimaging work, studies with monozygotic twins who are discordant for the disorder have&#xD;
      proved a particularly powerful tool, with findings of a significantly smaller caudate nucleus&#xD;
      in the affected twin compared to the unaffected, but genetically identical, twin (Castellanos&#xD;
      et al 2003). We have previously reported an overall reduction in white matter volume in all&#xD;
      four major brain lobes, with the deficit appearing to be fixed and non-progressive. However,&#xD;
      recent advances in neuroimaging of white matter make feasible an examination of white matter&#xD;
      characteristics, such as the degree of myelination and the coherence of white matter tracts.&#xD;
      The proposed project builds on our anatomic magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) studies that&#xD;
      have been performed with a 1.5-Tesla scanner in children who have&#xD;
      Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) and normal controls. We now propose to use&#xD;
      diffusion tensor magnetic resonance imaging (DT-MRI) as conventional T(1)- and T(2)-weighted&#xD;
      images at 3-Tesla to visualize and quantify white matter tracts in the brains of normal&#xD;
      monozygotic (MZ) twins, MZ twins who are concordant for ADHD, and MZ twins who are discordant&#xD;
      for ADHD. Ages will range from 6 to 21 years. Our principal focus will be on development and&#xD;
      possible abnormalities of white matter tracts linking prefrontal-striatal-thalamic circuits&#xD;
      in which we hypothesize disruption of these tracts in affected twins relative to their&#xD;
      healthy co-twins. We will also explore the usefulness of this technique in delineating white&#xD;
      matter in cerebellar circuits and characterize the normal development of white matter from&#xD;
      ages 6 to 21 by using a single healthy twin per family.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 12, 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 31, 2007</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>120</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit Disorder With Hyperactivity</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        PILOT SUBJECTS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects for pilot data collection will initially be up to 10 unscreened adult volunteers&#xD;
        who have been previously studied on the 1.5-Tesla Signa scanner. Subjects will be required&#xD;
        to provide informed consent, and to not have any medical exclusions as noted in the consent&#xD;
        form and below, particularly metallic objects and/or pregnancy. Once procedures are&#xD;
        optimized, up to 10 pediatric subjects will be studied. These pilot subjects will be&#xD;
        derived from the normal control pool of subjects who have been previously studied on the&#xD;
        1.5-Tesla Signa scanner. Informed consent and signed assent will be required, with the same&#xD;
        exclusions.&#xD;
&#xD;
        MONOZYGOTIC TWINS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects must be monozygotic twins (MZ) as confirmed by twin-similarity questionnaire and&#xD;
        by molecular cheek swab testing by polymerase chain reaction short tandem repeat multiplex&#xD;
        loci sets to find differences in the DNA types of the two co-twins. The primary test set&#xD;
        includes nine to fourteen unlinked loci with a combined matching probability for siblings p&#xD;
        less than .0001. Cases yielding a probability of twinship less than 0.99 are tested further&#xD;
        to a total of 21 loci. Subjects may also be requested to participate in an associated&#xD;
        genetic protocol (96-M-0060).&#xD;
&#xD;
        ADHD PROBANDS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Monozygotic twin.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Aged 6 - 21 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        DSM-IV diagnosis of ADHD (inattentive, hyperactive-impulsive and combined types).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age adjusted dimensional ratings (Conners Rating Scales-Revised, or Strengths and&#xD;
        Weaknesses of ADHD and Normal Behavior (SWAN)) hyperactivity/impulsivity greater than or&#xD;
        equal to 95th percentile in affected twin.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Consent and assent obtained in writing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        NORMAL PEDIATRIC VOLUNTEERS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Except for pilot subjects (up to 10 subjects), must be monozygotic twin.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Same age-range as probands.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Parent and teacher ratings within one SD of population means on ADHD/hyperactivity factors.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Consent and assent obtained in writing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        ADHD PROBANDS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of other psychiatric disorders that can produce symptoms similar to ADHD (e.g.,&#xD;
        major depression, bipolar disorder, severe anxiety disorders, pervasive developmental&#xD;
        disorders, psychotic disorders, post-traumatic stress disorder).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of neuropsychiatric conditions that may confound evaluation of ADHD (e.g.,&#xD;
        Tourette's syndrome, obsessive-compulsive disorder, or PANDAS (pediatric autoimmune&#xD;
        neuropsychiatric disorders associated with streptococcus).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of metal objects, pregnancy, or inability to provide a specimen of urine or blood&#xD;
        to rule out pregnancy in females over age 12.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of alcohol and/or other substance abuse.&#xD;
&#xD;
        NORMAL PEDIATRIC VOLUNTEERS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of any psychiatric disorders on structured psychiatric interview (DICA-IV).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of known genetic conditions.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence or history of medical conditions.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of metal objects, pregnancy, or inability to provide a specimen to rule out&#xD;
        pregnancy in females over age 12.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of alcohol and/or other substance abuse.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH), 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brandt KR, Hattery RR. MRI during pregnancy. Eur Radiol. 1997;7(6):821. doi: 10.1007/s003300050213. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>9228095</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 31, 2007</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 19, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Diffusion Tensor Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Twin Study</keyword>
  <keyword>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Normal Volunteers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

