<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001220</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>870160</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>87-CC-0160</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001220</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultrasound and Videofluoroscopy for Diagnosing Swallowing Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Ultrasound and Videofluoroscopic Imaging Techniques in Diagnosing Oropharyngeal Dysphagia in Neurologically Impaired Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will identify clinical signs and symptoms critical for diagnosing swallowing&#xD;
      disorders and will characterize swallowing problems in various patient populations, such as&#xD;
      patients with Parkinson's disease, stroke, post-polio syndrome, multiple sclerosis and other&#xD;
      conditions that cause swallowing abnormalities.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with swallowing difficulties who are enrolled in NIH neurology or speech pathology&#xD;
      protocols may be eligible for this study. Participants will undergo the following procedures:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Oral examination-A neurologist and speech pathologist examine the patient's swallowing&#xD;
           function. The patient is interviewed about difficulties with food intake, chewing and&#xD;
           swallowing during meals.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Ultrasound examination-Ultrasound creates image of areas inside the body using sound&#xD;
           waves. With the patient in a sitting position, a 3/4-inch transducer (device for&#xD;
           transmitting and receiving sound waves) is placed under the chin to visualize tongue&#xD;
           movements during swallowing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Modified barium swallow-While standing or sitting, the patient swallows 1/2 teaspoon of&#xD;
           flavored barium (a radioactive substance) six times (a total of 3 teaspoons), while the&#xD;
           tongue and pharynx (tube leading from the mouth to the esophagus) are scanned and&#xD;
           videotaped. The barium is given in three consistencies-thin, medium and thick&#xD;
           (pudding-like).&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. Electromyography-A small plastic strip with wires attached is placed under the patient's&#xD;
           chin. The patient then swallows 1/2 ounce of barium three times in a row, and the&#xD;
           movement of the chin muscles during swallowing is displayed. Patients may also be asked&#xD;
           to swallow 5/8 cup of barium twice; once with the head tilted upward and once with the&#xD;
           head untilted.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Depending on the test results, patients may be asked to return for follow-up study and&#xD;
      monitoring.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with neurological or neuromuscular conditions may be silent aspirators or at risk&#xD;
      for laryngeal penetration or aspiration because of abnormal oropharyngeal functioning and&#xD;
      thus are at risk for aspiration pneumonia and its serious effects. By providing&#xD;
      identification of the components of the abnormal swallow, and comparing swallowing across&#xD;
      tasks, we may avoid aspiration and can instruct patients on preventative or compensatory&#xD;
      swallowing techniques.&#xD;
&#xD;
      We will study the oral, pharyngeal and upper esophageal phases of swallow using both&#xD;
      ultrasonic imaging and videofluoroscopy in patients with neurologic, genetic, systemic, and&#xD;
      neuromuscular conditions. Most of the previous studies of swallowing have utilized only one&#xD;
      diagnostic imaging technique and have thus provided an incomplete swallowing assessment as&#xD;
      each procedure has unique, but limited capabilities for visualizing the anatomy and&#xD;
      physiology of the swallow.&#xD;
&#xD;
      We also plan to compare discrete and continuous swallowing in these populations. While the&#xD;
      motor physiology for discrete swallowing (i.e., single swallow) has been well studied, little&#xD;
      is known about the details of oral, laryngeal, and pharyngeal coordination during sequential&#xD;
      swallowing as a part of continuous drinking--a common event in everyday eating. A portion of&#xD;
      the protocol will study the effects of fast-paced movement sequencing on the coordination of&#xD;
      the tongue, velum, larynx, and pharynx during continuous drinking. Videofluoroscopy and&#xD;
      ultrasound may be paired or used individually to collect data from normal subjects and&#xD;
      patients with known dysphagia while they perform sequential and discrete swallowing tasks. A&#xD;
      number of timing and displacement measurements of the structures activated during these tasks&#xD;
      will be made from the digitized video images of each swallow, and analyses will be carried&#xD;
      out subsequently across tasks and subjects.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 1987</start_date>
  <completion_date>November 2005</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>750</enrollment>
  <condition>Deglutition Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Motor Neuron Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Any Clinical Center inpatients and outpatients with known or suspected dysphagia on any&#xD;
        other NIH institute protocol can be included for study as well as patients who are admitted&#xD;
        specifically for this protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Those patients at risk for oropharyngeal dysfunction will be screened initially by&#xD;
        completing a self-assessment swallowing questionnaire, and by an interview with staff&#xD;
        and/or family members. Patients who demonstrate appropriate signs and symptoms of dysphagia&#xD;
        and oral motor impairment on the screening assessment will be considered for the protocol:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Difficulty swallowing food or pills.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Changed swallowing ability.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Coughing or choking when eating.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Shortness of breath during swallowing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Food backing up into the mouth or nasal passage.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Fever or voice changes after swallowing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pain when swallowing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Unexplained loss of weight.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who are severely demented or severely compromised will be excluded if they do not&#xD;
        have sufficient cognitive ability to follow directions.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who are non-ambulatory will be excluded if they can not be braced or supported&#xD;
        within the fluoroscopy unit.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Highly agitated individuals will also be excluded if they are unable to remain confined in&#xD;
        the equipment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Infants and children under age 3 will be excluded due to radiation risk on the developing&#xD;
        visual system.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sonies BC, Parent LJ, Morrish K, Baum BJ. Durational aspects of the oral-pharyngeal phase of swallow in normal adults. Dysphagia. 1988;3(1):1-10. doi: 10.1007/BF02406274. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>3073915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Litvan I, Sastry N, Sonies BC. Characterizing swallowing abnormalities in progressive supranuclear palsy. Neurology. 1997 Jun;48(6):1654-62. doi: 10.1212/wnl.48.6.1654.</citation>
    <PMID>9191782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Donner MW. Swallowing mechanism and neuromuscular disorders. Semin Roentgenol. 1974 Oct;9(4):273-82. doi: 10.1016/0037-198x(74)90045-5. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>4421910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2005</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Swallowing Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuromotor Dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Aspiration</keyword>
  <keyword>Imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Deglutition Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Motor Neuron Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

