<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005934</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000166</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-DK-0166</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005934</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00007072</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>5-Azacytidine and Phenylbutyrate to Treat Severe Thalassemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of 5-Azacytidine and Oral Sodium Phenylbutyrate in Severe Thalassemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the safety and effectiveness of 5-azacytidine and phenylbutyrate for&#xD;
      treating thalassemia major. Patients with this disease have abnormal production of hemoglobin&#xD;
      (the oxygen-carrying protein in red blood cells), which leads to red blood cell destruction.&#xD;
      As a result, patients require frequent red cell transfusions over many years. Because of&#xD;
      these transfusions, however, excess iron is deposited in various body organs-such as the&#xD;
      heart, liver, thyroid gland and, in men, the testes-impairing their function.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Fetal hemoglobin-a type of hemoglobin that is produced during fetal and infant life-can&#xD;
      substitute for adult hemoglobin and increase the levels of red cells in the body. After&#xD;
      infancy, however, this type of hemoglobin is no longer produced in large quantities.&#xD;
      5-azacytidine can increase fetal hemoglobin levels, but this drug can damage DNA, which in&#xD;
      turn can increase the risk of cancer. This study will try to lessen the harmful effects of&#xD;
      5-azacytidine by using only one or two doses of it, followed by long-term therapy with&#xD;
      phenylbutyrate, a drug that may be as effective as 5-azacytidine with less harmful side&#xD;
      effects.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients 18 years of age and older with severe thalassemia major may be eligible for this&#xD;
      study. Before beginning treatment, candidates will have a medical history and physical&#xD;
      examination, blood tests, chest X-ray, electrocardiogram (EKG), bone marrow biopsy (removal&#xD;
      of a small sample of bone marrow from the hip for microscopic examination) and whole-body&#xD;
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). For the biopsy, the area of the hip is anesthetized and a&#xD;
      special needle is inserted to draw bone marrow from the hipbone. For the MRI scan, a strong&#xD;
      magnetic field is used to produce images that will identify sites where the body is making&#xD;
      red blood cells. During this procedure, the patient lies on a table in a narrow cylinder&#xD;
      containing a magnetic field. Earplugs are placed in the ears to muffle the loud thumping&#xD;
      sounds the machine makes when the magnetic fields are being switched.&#xD;
&#xD;
      An intravenous (IV) catheter (flexible tube inserted into a vein) is placed in a large vein&#xD;
      of the patient's neck, chest or arm for infusion of 5-azacytidine at a constant rate over 4&#xD;
      days. Patients who do not respond to this first dose of 5-azacytidine will be given the drug&#xD;
      again after about 50 days. If they do not respond to the second dose, alternate treatments&#xD;
      will have to be considered. Patients who respond to 5-azacytidine will begin taking&#xD;
      phenylbutyrate on the 14th day after 5-azacytidine was started. They will take about 10 large&#xD;
      pills 3 times a day, continuing for as long as the treatment is beneficial. All patients will&#xD;
      be hospitalized for at least 6 days starting with the beginning of 5-azacytidine therapy.&#xD;
      Those who are well enough may then be discharged and continue treatment as an outpatient.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will be monitored with blood tests daily for 2 weeks and then will be seen weekly&#xD;
      for about another 5 weeks. Bone marrow biopsies will be repeated 6 days after treatment&#xD;
      begins and again at 2 weeks and 7 weeks. MRI will be repeated 7 weeks after treatment begins.&#xD;
      After 7 weeks, patients will be seen at 3-month intervals. Bone marrow biopsies will be done&#xD;
      every 6 months for the first 3 years after treatment. Patients will have red cell&#xD;
      transfusions as needed and chelation therapy to remove excess iron.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Individuals with homozygous beta-thalassemia are either severely anemic or dependent on blood&#xD;
      transfusion to sustain life. Deficient synthesis of the beta chain leads to imbalanced chain&#xD;
      synthesis with an excess of alpha globin. This alpha globin precipitates, causing ineffective&#xD;
      erythropoiesis and shortened red cell survival. In patients with homozygous beta-thalassemia,&#xD;
      enhanced gamma globin synthesis could partially compensate for the deficient synthesis of&#xD;
      beta globin rendering chain synthesis more balanced and reducing the relative excess of alpha&#xD;
      chains. The purpose of this protocol is to test the hypothesis that induction therapy with&#xD;
      5-azacytidine, followed by maintenance treatment with oral phenylbutyrate will enhance gamma&#xD;
      globin synthesis, increase red cell production and partially or substantially correct the&#xD;
      anemia in patients with homozygous beta-thalassemia.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 2003</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>24</enrollment>
  <condition>Beta Thalassemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5-Azacytidine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Thalassemia major with progressive disease or complications of iron overload despite&#xD;
        traditional transfusion and iron chelation therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
        Thalassemia major in which standard transfusion therapy or iron chelation therapy is&#xD;
        contraindicated&#xD;
&#xD;
        ECOG performance status must be less than or equal to 2&#xD;
&#xD;
        NYHA less than or equal to class II status&#xD;
&#xD;
        Progressive disease is defined as 1) an increasing transfusion requirement or difficulty in&#xD;
        maintenance of hemoglobin levels greater than 7g/dl as a consequence of autologous or&#xD;
        allogeneic antibodies or 2) increasing extramedullary hematopoiesis causing compression&#xD;
        phenomena.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Complications of iron overload despite iron chelation therapy is defined as difficulty in&#xD;
        achieving negative iron balance when complications of iron overload exist. Complications of&#xD;
        iron overload include heart failure, or decreased cardiac ejection fraction, endocrinopathy&#xD;
        and evidence of progressive liver dysfunction.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Severe sepsis or septic shock&#xD;
&#xD;
        Current pregnancy or breast feeding&#xD;
&#xD;
        Not able to give informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
        Altered mental status or seizure disorder&#xD;
&#xD;
        AST or ALT greater than 3X upper limit of normal&#xD;
&#xD;
        Bilirubin greater than1.5X upper limit of normal, unless the abnormal bilirubin can be&#xD;
        accounted for by indirect hyperbilirubinemia due to hemolysis or Gilbert's Disease&#xD;
&#xD;
        Serum albumin less than 3g/dl&#xD;
&#xD;
        Creatinine greater than 2mg/dl and creatinine clearance less than 60ml/min&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who are moribund or patients with concurrent hepatic, renal, cardiac, metabolic,&#xD;
        or any disease of such severity that death within 7-10 days is likely&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent myelodysplastic syndrome or leukemia&#xD;
&#xD;
        NYHA class III/IV status&#xD;
&#xD;
        ECOG performance status greater than 2&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age less than 18 years&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas ED, Buckner CD, Sanders JE, Papayannopoulou T, Borgna-Pignatti C, De Stefano P, Sullivan KM, Clift RA, Storb R. Marrow transplantation for thalassaemia. Lancet. 1982 Jul 31;2(8292):227-9. doi: 10.1016/s0140-6736(82)90319-1. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>6124668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolfe L, Olivieri N, Sallan D, Colan S, Rose V, Propper R, Freedman MH, Nathan DG. Prevention of cardiac disease by subcutaneous deferoxamine in patients with thalassemia major. N Engl J Med. 1985 Jun 20;312(25):1600-3. doi: 10.1056/NEJM198506203122503.</citation>
    <PMID>4000198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Modell B, Petrou M. Management of thalassaemia major. Arch Dis Child. 1983 Dec;58(12):1026-30. doi: 10.1136/adc.58.12.1026. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>6660889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2003</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 6, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 6, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 7, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Fetal Hemoglobin</keyword>
  <keyword>5-Azacytidine</keyword>
  <keyword>Phenylbutyrate</keyword>
  <keyword>Thalassemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemoglobin</keyword>
  <keyword>Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood</keyword>
  <keyword>Thalassemia Major</keyword>
  <keyword>Beta Thalassemia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thalassemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>beta-Thalassemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Azacitidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

