<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001205</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>850127</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>85-I-0127</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001205</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Natural History of Treated Neurocysticercosis and Long-Term Outcomes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Natural History of Treated Neurocysticercosis and Long-Term Outcomes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate, treat and follow patients with cysticercosis, an&#xD;
      infection with the larval form of the pork tapeworm, T. solium. When people ingest cysts of&#xD;
      T. solium eggs, cysts develop in the muscles, brain and other organs. The cysts enlarge and&#xD;
      cause inflammation, usually in the brain. Patients may develop seizures, headache, nausea,&#xD;
      vomiting, inability to walk, poor vision due to enlargement of the brain, and increased&#xD;
      pressure in the brain. Other neurological problems may develop depending on the location of&#xD;
      the cysts. The drugs praziquantel and albendazole are used to treat cysticercosis, but it is&#xD;
      not clear if these drugs are effective in all patients, such as those with calcified cysts or&#xD;
      brain enlargement.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with suspected or confirmed cysticercosis may be eligible for this study.&#xD;
      Participants will be hospitalized for 2 to 3 weeks and will take either praziquantel or&#xD;
      albendazole by mouth for 2 weeks. They may receive a corticosteroid to lessen the side&#xD;
      effects of the drug therapy. Patients will be evaluated with medically indicated tests and&#xD;
      procedures that may include:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Blood tests.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  X-rays of the head and long bones.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Electroencephalogram - recording of the electrical activity of the brain&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Lumbar puncture (spinal tap) - examination of the cerebrospinal fluid that bathes the&#xD;
           brain and spinal cord. For this procedure, a local anesthetic is given and a needle is&#xD;
           inserted in the space between the bones (vertebrae) in the lower back. About 2&#xD;
           tablespoons of fluid is collected through the needle.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Eye examination.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) to examine the brain. MRI uses a strong magnetic field&#xD;
           and radio waves instead of X-rays to demonstrate structural and chemical changes in the&#xD;
           brain. During the scan, the patient lies on a table in a narrow cylinder (the scanner).&#xD;
           He or she can speak with a staff member via an intercom system at all times during the&#xD;
           procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Computed tomography (CT) to examine the brain. CT can be done from different angles and&#xD;
           allows the doctor to view the brain in small sections in 3-dimensions. The patient lies&#xD;
           on a table with the head positioned in the CT scanner.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Some of the tests may be repeated on the last day of therapy and at 3 and 6 months or longer&#xD;
      after therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      ...&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this protocol is to follow participants with cysticercosis during and after&#xD;
      completion of treatment, to characterize the disease course during both short- and long-term&#xD;
      follow-up, assess biomarkers associated with infection and response to treatment, improve&#xD;
      diagnostic assays, and explore host-parasite interactions. Cysticercosis is defined as an&#xD;
      infection with the larval form of Taenia solium and includes infection of the brain&#xD;
      (neurocysticercosis [NCC]) that accounts for most of the symptomatic disease and serious&#xD;
      complications. Evaluation and treatment will be provided as clinically indicated. Clinical&#xD;
      data and biospecimens will be collected during and after treatment to assess biomarkers of&#xD;
      infection and inflammation, immunologic response to treatment, and correlations between&#xD;
      biomarkers and results of clinically indicated diagnostic tests. In addition, we will collect&#xD;
      information from patient-reported outcome questionnaires completed by participants to better&#xD;
      understand the long-term effect on functional ability and determine if there is a correlation&#xD;
      between clinical deficits with biomarkers of inflammation.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 7, 1985</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterise the radiographic, biochemical, and clinical course of neurocysticercosis during and after treatment with long term follow up, with the goal of documenting a disease free state off anthelmintics for 7 years</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years-indefinite</time_frame>
    <description>To study the clinical course of cysticercosis following therapy and diminish morbidity associated with treatment of cysticercosis including neurocysticercosis or the inflammation associated with therapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Cysticercosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Male and female subjects aged 3-75 years with likely or definite neurocysticercosis (NCC) diagnosis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Male and female subjects aged 3-99 years with likely or definite neurocysticercosis (NCC)&#xD;
        diagnosis&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Patients ages 3 to 99 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Patients with proven or likely neurocysticercosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Willingness (of participant or legally authorized representative [LAR]) to sign&#xD;
                  consent and comply with study requirements.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Not applicable.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elise M O'Connell, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>JeanAnne M Ware, C.R.N.P.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-3149</phone>
    <email>warejm@niaid.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elise M O'Connell, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 761-5413</phone>
    <email>oconnellem@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1985-I-0127.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nash TE, Singh G, White AC, Rajshekhar V, Loeb JA, Proano JV, Takayanagui OM, Gonzalez AE, Butman JA, DeGiorgio C, Del Brutto OH, Delgado-Escueta A, Evans CA, Gilman RH, Martinez SM, Medina MT, Pretell EJ, Teale J, Garcia HH. Treatment of neurocysticercosis: current status and future research needs. Neurology. 2006 Oct 10;67(7):1120-7. doi: 10.1212/01.wnl.0000238514.51747.3a.</citation>
    <PMID>17030744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nash TE, Mahanty S, Garcia HH; Cysticercosis Group in Peru. Corticosteroid use in neurocysticercosis. Expert Rev Neurother. 2011 Aug;11(8):1175-83. doi: 10.1586/ern.11.86.</citation>
    <PMID>21797658</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nash TE, Garcia HH. Diagnosis and treatment of neurocysticercosis. Nat Rev Neurol. 2011 Sep 13;7(10):584-94. doi: 10.1038/nrneurol.2011.135.</citation>
    <PMID>21912406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 30, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Taenia Solium</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurocysticercosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Tapeworm</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neurocysticercosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cysticercosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Taeniasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

