<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000424</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01AR042165</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NIAMS-001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000424</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tidal Lavage in Knee Osteoarthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Tidal Lavage vs. Sham Lavage in Knee Osteoarthritis (OA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study compared the effects of tidal lavage (washing out) of the knee joint and an&#xD;
      imitation lavage procedure in people with knee osteoarthritis. In tidal lavage, the doctor&#xD;
      flushes out a knee joint with repeated injections of a mild salt solution, done under local&#xD;
      anesthesia. Study participants had to meet standard criteria for diagnosis of osteoarthritis&#xD;
      but could have low, medium, or high severity of x-ray changes indicating knee osteoarthritis.&#xD;
      We performed the lavage procedure once, and did quarterly followups for 1 year. We permitted&#xD;
      patients to use some other osteoarthritis treatments during the study, such as non-narcotic&#xD;
      pain relievers, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, and physical therapy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study was a randomized, double-blind, sham procedure-controlled evaluation of tidal&#xD;
      lavage as a treatment for knee osteoarthritis. We achieved blinding by raising a drape during&#xD;
      the study procedure and mimicking the sensory aspects of tidal lavage, but not flushing the&#xD;
      knee, in the sham lavage group. We gave all study participants subcutaneous anesthesia with&#xD;
      lidocaine and then bupivacaine and then attempted aspiration of the knee, removing up to 5 ml&#xD;
      of synovial fluid for examination and then injecting the knee with 20 ml of bupivicaine.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In people who received the sham treatment, we placed a 16-gauge catheter in the lateral&#xD;
      suprapatellar position just to the knee joint capsule and infused small volumes (less than 5&#xD;
      ml per &quot;exchange&quot; x 20) of saline into the subcutaneous tissue while manipulating the&#xD;
      anterior knee to mimic efforts to shift fluid within the knee during the &quot;aspiration&quot; phase&#xD;
      of each exchange. Patients could see the supply bag of sterile saline but could not see the&#xD;
      waste bag of this closed drainage system.&#xD;
&#xD;
      For tidal lavage patients, we made the catheter puncture in the lateral suprapatellar pouch&#xD;
      and repeatedly distended the knee with 30-50 ml of sterile saline, then aspirated this volume&#xD;
      (about 20 exchanges for a total of 1 liter of flush solution).&#xD;
&#xD;
      At the end of the procedure, we told the patients that their knee might be swollen due to&#xD;
      retained saline, and to expect this additional swelling to resolve over 24-48 hours, during&#xD;
      which time they were to minimize activity. The person who did the procedure (the principal&#xD;
      investigator) then left the room. The study nurse, who was not present for the procedure and&#xD;
      was blinded to the procedure's identity, asked the patients which treatment they thought they&#xD;
      received (tidal lavage or sham lavage). We scheduled patient followups with this study nurse&#xD;
      for 3, 6, and 12 months, and patients completed questionnaires at each visit. Questionnaires&#xD;
      were both arthritis-specific (WOMAC) and global (Quality of Well-Being).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 2001</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>180</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tidal lavage vs. sham lavage of the knee</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Knee pain attributed to osteoarthritis for at least 1 year.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Meet American College of Rheumatology clinical or clinical plus x-ray criteria for&#xD;
             knee osteoarthritis&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have at least a moderate pain rating on at least one of the five Western&#xD;
             Ontario-McMaster University Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC) scales&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Significant conditions of the spine, hips, or feet that affect the ability to walk&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Significant medical conditions that affect the ability to walk and function&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Inflammatory arthritis, such as rheumatoid arthritis or gout&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Degenerative arthritis secondary to other conditions, such as hemochromatosis,&#xD;
             Wilson's disease, or ochronosis&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current significant soft tissue rheumatism such as fibromyalgia, anserine bursitis, or&#xD;
             trochanteric bursitis&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John D. Bradley, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bradley JD, Heilman DK, Wallick JE, Olin P. Effect of blinding on response to tidal lavage (TL) and sham lavage (SL) in knee osteoarthritis (KOA). Arthritis Rheum 42(Supplement):S292,1999.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bradley JD, Heilman DK, G'Sell P: Do psychological factors &quot;predict&quot; response to tidal lavage (TL) and sham lavage (SL) in knee osteoarthritis (KOA)? Arthritis Rheum 43(Supplement):S337,2000</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bradley JD. Joint irrigation as treatment for osteoarthritis. Curr Rheumatol Rep. 2003 Feb;5(1):20-6. doi: 10.1007/s11926-003-0079-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12590881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bradley JD, Heilman DK, Katz BP, Gsell P, Wallick JE, Brandt KD. Tidal irrigation as treatment for knee osteoarthritis: a sham-controlled, randomized, double-blinded evaluation. Arthritis Rheum. 2002 Jan;46(1):100-8. doi: 10.1002/1529-0131(200201)46:13.0.co;2-v.</citation>
    <PMID>11817581</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2001</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 28, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 28, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 1, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis (OA)</keyword>
  <keyword>Knee</keyword>
  <keyword>Sham lavage</keyword>
  <keyword>Tidal lavage</keyword>
  <keyword>Lavage therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID)</keyword>
  <keyword>Placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiography</keyword>
  <keyword>Human therapy evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>WOMAC</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

