<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001922</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990009</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-N-0009</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001922</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sensory Function in Idiopathic Voice Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sensory Function in Idiopathic Voice Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is designed to improve understanding about voice disorders that are due&#xD;
      to uncontrolled muscle contractions affecting the voice box. The type of voice disorder&#xD;
      depends on which muscles of the voice box are involved. Abductor spasmodic dysphonia may lead&#xD;
      to a weak voice. Adductor spasmodic dysphonia may result in a strangled voice. Muscular&#xD;
      tension dysphonia may lead to a strained voice. Some of the major goals of the study are to;&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. understand how sensation from the voice box affects voice and speech production&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. develop better ways to diagnose sensation abnormalities affecting the voice box&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. determine if patients with voice disorders differ from persons without voice disorders&#xD;
           in the way they respond to sensory information from their voice box&#xD;
&#xD;
      Researchers believe that by understanding better how sensations of the voice box are&#xD;
      presented and how the muscles in the larynx respond to those sensations they will be able to&#xD;
      develop better treatments for patients suffering from voice disorders. ...&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Aim One: To develop and validate objective procedures for quantifying efferent&#xD;
      responses to non-invasive laryngeal mechanical and aerodynamic stimulation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study Aim Two: To develop and validate an objective test of brain stem evoked responses to&#xD;
      laryngeal stimulation using electrical stimulation of the superior laryngeal nerve.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study Aim Three: To determine whether individuals with idiopathic voice disorders have&#xD;
      abnormal conditioning of their responses to laryngeal mechanical and aerodynamic stimulation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study Aim Four: To determine whether individuals with idiopathic voice disorders have&#xD;
      abnormal brain stem responses to laryngeal stimuli.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study Aim Five: To evaluate whether sensory input plays a role in symptom generation in&#xD;
      laryngeal motor control disorders, temporary bilateral ISLN blockade will be used in&#xD;
      idiopathic voice disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study Aim Six: To evaluate whether the central pathophysiology involved in motor responses to&#xD;
      sensory stimulation are altered by botulinum toxin injection in individuals with spasmodic&#xD;
      dysphonia.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study Aim Seven: To evaluate central responses to laryngeal afferent stimulation in normal&#xD;
      volunteers and patients with idiopathic voice disorders at rest and during vocalization using&#xD;
      magnetoencephalography.&#xD;
&#xD;
      These studies will develop improved non-invasive techniques for the diagnosis of laryngeal&#xD;
      sensory disorders and will determine if abnormalities in sensory feedback modulation are&#xD;
      involved in idiopathic voice disorders. Such findings will lead to improved understanding of&#xD;
      the pathophysiology and differential diagnosis of idiopathic voice disorders and may&#xD;
      ultimately improve treatment approaches to these disorders.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 5, 1998</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 14, 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>370</enrollment>
  <condition>Phonation Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Spastic Dysphonia</condition>
  <condition>Voice Disorder</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA - Normal Volunteers:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Normal volunteers between the ages of 20 and 80 years of age will be selected after a&#xD;
             screening examination.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects will be without cardiac, pulmonary, neurological, otolaryngological,&#xD;
             psychiatric or speech and hearing problems as determined by medical history and&#xD;
             examination by an otolaryngologist.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  None of the subjects included for study will have a reduction in the range of vocal&#xD;
             fold movement during non-speech tasks such as whistling suggesting either paralysis or&#xD;
             paresis, joint abnormality or neoplasm.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA - Normal Volunteers:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any patient with a history of airway obstruction will be excluded from the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No smokers or tobacco users will be included in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects with a history of a psychiatric disorder, under the care of a psychiatrist,&#xD;
             or on medications for treatment of a psychiatric disorder will be excluded from study.&#xD;
             Examples of psychiatric disorders to be excluded are: somatoform disorders, conversion&#xD;
             disorders, currently under treatment for a major depression, or a history of&#xD;
             schizophrenia or a bipolar disorder. However, a history of a previous episode of a&#xD;
             minor reactive depression would not exclude a person from participation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Any individual with: 1) an implant or surgical clip - implanted neural stimulator,&#xD;
        implanted cardiac pacemaker or autodefibrillator, cochlear implant, ocular implant,&#xD;
        aneurysm clip, artificial heart valve, insulin pump, orthopedic pins or prosthesis: 2) a&#xD;
        foreign body - metal shavings, shrapnel, orthodontic braces, tattoos or permanent eye&#xD;
        liner; and/or, 3) any other implanted device or foreign body not listed above that is&#xD;
        possibly ferromagnetic will also be excluded from study seven because of contraindications&#xD;
        for magnetic resonance imaging.&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA - Patients with Spasmodic Dysphonia:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Symptoms present during speech and not apparent at rest.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Symptoms less evident during whisper, singing or falsetto.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Symptoms become worse with prolonged speaking, practice or anxiety.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Reflexive and emotional aspects of voice function are unaffected, such as coughing,&#xD;
             laughter or crying.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA - Patients with Spasmodic Dysphonia:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any patient with a history of airway obstruction will be excluded from the study.&#xD;
             Structural abnormalities affecting the larynx such as vocal fold nodules, polyps,&#xD;
             carcinoma, cysts, contact ulcers, or inflammation (laryngitis).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Reduction in vocal fold movement range during non-speech tasks such as whistling which&#xD;
             would suggest either paralysis or paresis, joint abnormality or neoplasm.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No smokers or tobacco users will be included in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects with a history of a psychiatric disorder, under the care of a psychiatrist,&#xD;
             or on medications for treatment of a psychiatric disorder will be excluded from study.&#xD;
             Examples of psychiatric disorders to be excluded are: somatoform disorders, conversion&#xD;
             disorders, currently under treatment for a major depression, or a history of&#xD;
             schizophrenia or a bipolar disorder. However, a history of a previous episode of a&#xD;
             minor reactive depression would not exclude a person from participation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Although patients with neurological disorders are excluded, certain focal dystonias&#xD;
             which occasionally occur simultaneously with spasmodic dysphonia, will not&#xD;
             automatically exclude a patient from participating. The determination will be made at&#xD;
             the discretion of the Laryngeal and Speech Section Team.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Although structural abnormalities of the larynx will cause a patient to be excluded,&#xD;
             those that have had previous laryngeal surgery will not automatically be disqualified&#xD;
             if they remain measurably symptomatic with their voice disorder. The determination&#xD;
             will be made at the discretion of the Laryngeal and Speech Section Team.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients whose symptoms vary during their initial interview, and/or who report periods&#xD;
             of symptom remission and are atypical of spasmodic dysphonia will not be included.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with whispering aphonia or complete aphonia will not be included.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with a constant voice quality abnormality will not be included.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with muscular tension dysphonia will be included in a separate subject group&#xD;
             and not included in spasmodic dysphonia.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Spasmodic dysphonia and muscular tension dysphonia are disorders of adult onset&#xD;
             usually first occurring after 40 years of age, therefore, we do not plan to include&#xD;
             children in this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA - Patients with Adductor SD:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Intermittent strained hoarseness and uncontrolled voice breaks or changes in pitch&#xD;
             during vowels in speech.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Symptoms most easily heard on vowels, liquids (r and l) or semivowel sounds (w and y).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Intermittent hyperadduction of the vocal folds interfering with air flow through the&#xD;
             folds during vowels in speech, stopping vocal fold vibration, and resulting in voice&#xD;
             interruptions or breaks. When the hyperadduction is less severe, voicing may become&#xD;
             strained or a rapid change in pitch may occur. In the milder forms of the disorder,&#xD;
             only intermittent irregular catches will be heard in the voice on a vowel every couple&#xD;
             of sentences. In the moderate form, the voice is constantly breaking or bursting as&#xD;
             the patient tries to force air through excessively tight vocal folds. The speech has&#xD;
             intermittent hoarseness as well. In the most severe form, individuals have a constant&#xD;
             strained hoarseness and reduced volume because very little air can be forced through&#xD;
             the vocal folds. In such individuals voice may be heard only at the end of sentences&#xD;
             as the vocal folds release at the end of speech phrases. The speech is excessively&#xD;
             slow, tight and effortful.&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA - Patients with Abductor SD:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Prolonged vocal fold opening during voiceless consonants with excessive breathiness as&#xD;
             individuals experience difficulties in closing the vocal folds to produce vowels&#xD;
             following voiceless consonants (p, t, k, s, f, h, th). Sounds such as (s, h or k) when&#xD;
             coming just before open vowels such as (ah and uh) as in home, coffee and puppy are&#xD;
             usually most affected.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A breathy voice quality, uncontrolled pitch elevations on vowel initiation, difficulty&#xD;
             coordinating breathing with speech, and complaints of excessive air loss while&#xD;
             speaking. These individuals usually have similar problems in singing but normal&#xD;
             laughter and coughing. In the milder forms only intermittent prolongations of a few&#xD;
             voiceless consonants are heard. In the more severe forms more voiceless consonants are&#xD;
             affected, speech initiation becomes more difficult and voice becomes breathy. In the&#xD;
             most severe forms of both adductor and abductor spasmodic dysphonia, individuals may&#xD;
             resort to whispering which is less affected and much less effortful.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA - Patients with Adductor SD:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any patient with a history of airway obstruction will be excluded from the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No smokers or tobacco users will be included in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with cardiac, pulmonary, neurological, otolaryngological, psychiatric or&#xD;
             speech and hearing problems as determined by medical history and examination by an&#xD;
             otolaryngologist.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Structural abnormalities affecting the larynx such as vocal fold nodules, polyps,&#xD;
             carcinoma, cysts, contact ulcers, or inflammation (laryngitis).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Reduction in vocal fold movement range during non-speech tasks such as whistling which&#xD;
             would suggest either paralysis or paresis, joint abnormality or neoplasm.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients whose symptoms vary during their initial interview, and/or who report periods&#xD;
             of symptom remission and are atypical of spasmodic dysphonia will not be included.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with whispering aphonia or complete aphonia will not be included.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with muscular tension dysphonia will be included in a separate subject group&#xD;
             and not included in spasmodic dysphonia.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA - Patients with Abductor SD:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any patient with a history of airway obstruction will be excluded from the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No smokers or tobacco users will be included in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with cardiac, pulmonary, neurological, otolaryngological, psychiatric or&#xD;
             speech and hearing problems as determined by medical history and examination by an&#xD;
             otolaryngologist.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Structural abnormalities affecting the larynx such as vocal fold nodules, polyps,&#xD;
             carcinoma, cysts, contact ulcers, or inflammation (laryngitis).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Reduction in vocal fold movement range during non-speech tasks such as whistling which&#xD;
             would suggest either paralysis or paresis, joint abnormality or neoplasm.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients whose symptoms vary during their initial interview, and/or who report periods&#xD;
             of symptom remission and are atypical of spasmodic dysphonia will not be included.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with whispering aphonia or complete aphonia will not be included.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with muscular tension dysphonia will be included in a separate subject group&#xD;
             and not included in spasmodic dysphonia.&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA - Patients with Muscular Tension Dysphonia:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Increased phonatory muscle tension in the paralaryngeal and suprahyoid muscles on&#xD;
             palpation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Constant elevation of the larynx in the neck during speech.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. A consistent hypertonic laryngeal posture for phonation, either an open posterior&#xD;
             glottic chink between the arytenoid cartilages on phonation, an anterior-posterior&#xD;
             squeeze (pinhole posture) or ventricular hyperadduction.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. A normal appearing larynx.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA - Patients with Muscular Tension Dysphonia:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Cardiac, pulmonary, neurological, otolaryngological, psychiatric or speech and hearing&#xD;
             problems as determined by medical history and examination by a physician. Any patient&#xD;
             with a history of airway obstruction will be excluded from the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Reduction in the range of vocal fold movement during non-speech tasks such as&#xD;
             whistling suggesting either paralysis or paresis, joint abnormality or neoplasm.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Intermittent symptoms during their initial interview, reports of periods of symptom&#xD;
             remission or spasmodic breaks in voicing typical or either adductor or abductor&#xD;
             spasmodic dysphonia.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. A 30 dB HL screening between 500 and 3000 Hz will be conducted if subjects report&#xD;
             difficulty following spoken instructions and a history of hearing loss or significant&#xD;
             noise exposure.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. No smokers or tobacco users will be included in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Exclude mucosal changes such as vocal nodules or polyps.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Subjects with a history of a psychiatric disorder, under the care of a psychiatrist,&#xD;
             or on medications for treatment of a psychiatric disorder will be excluded from study.&#xD;
             Examples of psychiatric disorders to be excluded are: somatoform disorders, conversion&#xD;
             disorders, currently under treatment for a major depression, or a history of&#xD;
             schizophrenia or a bipolar disorder. However, a history of a previous episode of a&#xD;
             minor reactive depression would not exclude a person from participation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        OTHER EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects will be excluded if they have a history of rheumatic fever, mitral valve prolapse&#xD;
        or cardiac arrhythmias, as determined by medical history, physical and EKG.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Individuals who might be at risk for endocarditis will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        All patients over the age of 40 years of age will have an electrocardiogram on the day of&#xD;
        the study and if there are any abnormalities they will not be allowed to participate.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnancy.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sant'Ambrogio G, Mathew OP. Laryngeal receptors and their reflex responses. Clin Chest Med. 1986 Jun;7(2):211-22.</citation>
    <PMID>3522068</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sant'Ambrogio G, Anderson JW, Sant'Ambrogio FB, Mathew OP. Response of laryngeal receptors to water solutions of different osmolality and ionic composition. Respir Med. 1991 Jan;85 Suppl A:57-60. doi: 10.1016/s0954-6111(06)80256-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2034837</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hansson L, Wollmer P, Dahlback M, Karlsson JA. Regional sensitivity of human airways to capsaicin-induced cough. Am Rev Respir Dis. 1992 May;145(5):1191-5. doi: 10.1164/ajrccm/145.5.1191.</citation>
    <PMID>1586064</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 14, 2009</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Evoked Response</keyword>
  <keyword>Spasmodic Dysphonia</keyword>
  <keyword>Aerodynamic</keyword>
  <keyword>Vibration</keyword>
  <keyword>Laryngeal</keyword>
  <keyword>Voice Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Laryngeal Brainstem Evoked Responses</keyword>
  <keyword>Long-latency Responses</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscular Tension Dysphonia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dysphonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hoarseness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Voice Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

