<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00008866</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A5069</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10905</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ACTG A5069</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>AACTG A5069</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Substudy AACTG A5070s</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00008866</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Early or Delayed Addition of Hydroxyurea to a Three-Drug Anti-HIV Drug Combination Including Didanosine, in Advanced HIV Patients Who Failed a First or Second Anti-HIV Triple-Drug Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Double-Blind, Randomized Study to Determine the Effect of Adding Delayed Versus Immediate Hydroxyurea to a Genotypic Based, ddI-Containing, Three-Drug Antiretroviral Regimen on the Recovery of Total CD4+ T-Cell Counts and Suppression of Plasma Viral Load in Advanced HIV-1 Infected Subjects Failing a First or Second Triple Combination Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out whether or not the addition of hydroxyurea to&#xD;
      didanosine (ddI) and other anti-HIV medications will result in better control of HIV&#xD;
      infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has approved ddI for treating HIV infections.&#xD;
      Hydroxyurea is approved for treating some cancers and blood disorders. It works against HIV-1&#xD;
      when combined with ddI. Researchers need to look at how well patients may respond to&#xD;
      hydroxyurea in combination with ddI and other anti-HIV drugs, and at any side effects.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Increasing frequency of treatment failures on potent antiretroviral therapy has accelerated&#xD;
      the need for new classes of agents. Hydroxyurea, an agent broadly used for its antineoplastic&#xD;
      properties, has been shown to inhibit HIV-1 in vitro and in vivo when combined with the&#xD;
      nucleoside analogue reverse transcriptase inhibitor didanosine (ddI). There is an urgent need&#xD;
      to prospectively test the safety, tolerability, and efficacy of hydroxyurea in late-stage,&#xD;
      treatment-experienced patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients undergo genotypic analysis after registration to Step 1. Genotypic antiretroviral&#xD;
      resistance test (GART) along with a patient's antiretroviral drug history will be used to&#xD;
      select an optimal antiretroviral drug regimen (non-study drugs) for each patient. Patients&#xD;
      willing to initiate the GART-based regimen are randomized at Week 5 into Step 2. They are&#xD;
      stratified, first by level of ddI resistance, then within each strata by CD4+ T cell count,&#xD;
      and then assigned to 1 of 3 treatment arms to start all study drugs (ddI and hydroxyurea) and&#xD;
      non-study antiretroviral drugs on the day of randomization. Patients in Arm A receive ddI and&#xD;
      hydroxyurea placebo; Arm B, ddI and hydroxyurea placebo that is replaced by hydroxyurea after&#xD;
      8 weeks; and Arm C, ddI and hydroxyurea. Patients receive treatment for 48 weeks. Patients&#xD;
      are checked regularly for immunologic, virologic, and metabolic parameters. Patients may&#xD;
      elect to participate in substudy A5070s, which explores the effects of study treatment on T&#xD;
      cell populations and other immunologic evaluations.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tetanus Toxoid Vaccine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydroxyurea</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Didanosine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients may be eligible for this study if they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are at least 13 years old.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have the signed consent of parent/guardian if under 18 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are HIV-positive.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have failed 1 or 2 anti-HIV drug combination therapies which had at least 3 anti-HIV&#xD;
             drugs each.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have been on stable, triple anti-HIV drug therapy for at least 16 weeks prior to study&#xD;
             entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a CD4 count under 300 cells/mm3 within 45 days prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agree not to become pregnant or make anyone else pregnant while on study drugs and for&#xD;
             60 days after stopping drugs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agree to use 2 methods of birth control while on study drugs and for 60 days after&#xD;
             stopping study drugs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a negative pregnancy test within 14 days prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients will not be eligible for this study if they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Received treatment for a serious infection or illness that was completed less than 2&#xD;
             weeks prior to study entry or, if they are still receiving treatment, he/she must have&#xD;
             been clinically stable for at least 14 days prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are pregnant or breast-feeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are using any drugs that affect the immune system, other than those specified by the&#xD;
             study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Received an immunization within 30 days prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have had pancreatitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have severe neuropathy (a condition affecting the nervous system).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Received granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF) or granulocyte-macrophage&#xD;
             colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF) within 14 days prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Abuse alcohol or drugs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have any medical condition that would make the patient unable to complete the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have used hydroxyurea within 24 weeks prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Had hepatitis within 60 days of study entry.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Asmuth</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Judith Feinberg</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Pollard</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2021</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 28, 2021</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 28, 2021</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 1, 2021</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV-1</keyword>
  <keyword>Didanosine</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy, Combination</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug Administration Schedule</keyword>
  <keyword>CD4-Positive T-Lymphocytes</keyword>
  <keyword>Hydroxyurea</keyword>
  <keyword>RNA, Viral</keyword>
  <keyword>Genotype</keyword>
  <keyword>Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-HIV Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Viral Load</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Didanosine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxyurea</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

