<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001244</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>890158</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>89-I-0158</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001244</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immune Regulation in Patients With Common Variable Immunodeficiency and Related Syndromes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Studies of Immune Regulation in Patients With Common Variable Immunodeficiency and Related Humoral Immunodeficiency Syndromes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will explore the cause of immunodeficiency in common variable immunodeficiency&#xD;
      (CVI) and other related immunodeficiency syndromes-IgA deficiency, hyper IgM syndrome,&#xD;
      thymoma and agammaglobulinemia, hypogammaglobulinemia associated with Epstein-Barr infection,&#xD;
      and others to better focus on how to correct the underlying defect.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with CVI and their family members may participate in this study. Family members must&#xD;
      be between the ages of 18 and 85, in good health and weigh at least 110 pounds.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will receive standard medical care for their illness. Procedures may include a&#xD;
      medical history and physical examination, routine blood tests, stool examination for&#xD;
      infectious agents, lung function tests, chest and sinus X-rays. Treatment may include&#xD;
      administration of immune serum globulin, antibiotics for infections, and anti-inflammatory&#xD;
      drugs, if needed. In addition, patients may undergo the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Lymphapheresis: This procedure is done to collect large numbers of white blood cells&#xD;
           (lymphocytes). Blood is collected through a needle in an arm vein, similar to donating&#xD;
           blood. The blood is separated it into its components by centrifugation (spinning), the&#xD;
           white cells are removed, and the rest of the blood (red cells, plasma and platelets) is&#xD;
           returned to the body, either through the same needle or through another needle in the&#xD;
           other arm.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Blood draw: Blood may be drawn through a needle in an arm vein (venipuncture). No more&#xD;
           than 450 milliliters (15 ounces) of blood will be collected over a 6-week period from&#xD;
           adults, and no more than 7 ml (1 1/2 teaspoons) per kilogram (2.2 pounds) of body weight&#xD;
           in children over the same time period.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Lymph node biopsies: Lymph node biopsies will be done only if required for diagnostic&#xD;
           purposes. Some of the biopsy tissue may be kept for research. Up to two lymph nodes may&#xD;
           be removed during each procedure. For the procedure, a painkiller is injected into and&#xD;
           beneath the skin in the biopsy area, and the node is removed surgically. The incision is&#xD;
           closed using dissolving sutures (stitches) that do not require removal. The biopsy takes&#xD;
           about 30 minutes. Patients will be hospitalized at least overnight for observation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Intestinal biopsies: Endoscopy and gastrointestinal biopsy will be done only if there is&#xD;
           evidence of malabsorption. Some of the biopsy tissue may be kept for research. Patients&#xD;
           are pre-medicated to allay anxiety, but are fully conscious during the procedure. A&#xD;
           flexible tube is inserted into the stomach or small intestine through the mouth. The&#xD;
           tube allows the doctor to see the intestinal mucosa and to project the image onto a TV&#xD;
           screen. At various places in the mucosal surface, small pieces of tissue are plucked out&#xD;
           using a small space at the tip of the endoscope. The procedure takes 30 to 60 minutes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Some of the blood collected may be used for genetic tests. Some blood and tissue samples may&#xD;
      be stored for future research labeled with a code, such as a number, that only the study team&#xD;
      can link to the patient.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participating family members will provide a medical history, and their pulse, blood pressure&#xD;
      and temperature will be taken. They will have 10 to 120 ml (1/3 to 4 ounces) of blood drawn&#xD;
      from a vein in the arm. Blood samples may be taken on repeated occasions as long as the&#xD;
      relative remains in the study. The blood will be used for research that may involve&#xD;
      development of diagnostic tests for CVI, evaluation of the structure and function of normal&#xD;
      blood cells for comparison with those of patients with CVI, and studies to try to determine&#xD;
      possible genetic factors involved in susceptibility to CVI.&#xD;
&#xD;
      ...&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this protocol is to carry out laboratory studies concerning the&#xD;
      immunopathogenesis of Common Variable Immunodeficiency (CVI) and related primary humoral&#xD;
      immunodeficiency diseases. Additionally, we aim to document and track the progression of&#xD;
      known complications of this primary immunodeficiency. Complications associated with CVID&#xD;
      include recurrent respiratory and gastrointestinal bacterial infections, pulmonary&#xD;
      insufficiency, nodular regenerative hyperplasia, lymphoid malignancy, and various autoimmune&#xD;
      manifestations.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with CVI and related B-Cell immunodeficiencies will be enrolled into this natural&#xD;
      history study. Protocol procedures will include baseline measurements of and changes in lab&#xD;
      studies. First- or second-degree genetically related family members (limited to mother,&#xD;
      father, siblings, grandparents, children, aunts, uncles, and first cousins of an affected&#xD;
      patient) may also be screened for clinical, in vitro, and genetic correlates of immune&#xD;
      abnormalities. Changes in the patients clinical state will be measured to determine the&#xD;
      precursors of disease complications. This may lead to developments in improving preventive&#xD;
      measures and novel treatment options for this population.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 15, 1990</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterization of immune abnormalities</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the physiologic, biochemical or genetic basis of theabnormality of immunity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of organ dysfunction/damage resulting from immune abnormality</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>To establish the extent of organ involvement (infection and/or inflammation) and organ damage or dysfunction resulting from the abnormality of immune function.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Establish pattern/pace of disease process</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 year and ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>To establish the pattern and pace of change of disease (frequency, distribution, type and extent of infections, inflammatory lesions andabnormalities of immune function).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess ability to participate in other studies</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the patient's ability to safely tolerate specific aspects of other diagnostic or therapeutic research protocols.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine eligibility for other studies</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>To determine a patient's eligibility for other studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Establish baseline of pattern/pace of disease process before participating in therapeutic trials</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>To establish a baseline assessment of the pace and extent of the disease before entering a therapeutic clinical trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>CVID</condition>
  <condition>XLA</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>General Population</arm_group_label>
    <description>MD referred or self-referred</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        General population - MD referred or self-referred&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Must have a verifiable diagnosis of common variable immune deficiency as defined by a&#xD;
             decrease both in IgG and at least one other Ig isotype to below two standard&#xD;
             deviations of normal control levels OR B-cell immunodeficiencies related to CVI&#xD;
             (defined as selective IgA deficiency, hyper IgM syndrome, thymoma and&#xD;
             agammaglobulinemia, and hypogammaglobulinemia associated with Epstein-Barr virus&#xD;
             infection), or hypogammaglobulinemia associated with other related immunodeficiencies&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Must be 2 years old or greater.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with repeated infections and suspected of having an immunodeficiency&#xD;
             syndrome.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients must have a primary medical care provider as a criterion for inclusion into&#xD;
             this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  On investigator s discretion, unaffected family members (mother, father, siblings,&#xD;
             children, grandparents, aunts, uncles, and first cousins) may be asked for the&#xD;
             provision of blood or buccal specimens for research purposes.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients who are lactating, may be eligible and will only undergo tests and&#xD;
             procedures, and/or receive medications for which data exists that proves that they are&#xD;
             minimal risk to the child.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnant women will not be newly enrolled onto this protocol, however existing&#xD;
             patients who become pregnant while on study will remain on study, as literature about&#xD;
             pregnancy in CVID patients is sparse and outside providers have minimal knowledge&#xD;
             about managing CVID during pregnancy. Pregnant women will only undergo tests and&#xD;
             procedures, and/or receive medications for which data exists that proves that they are&#xD;
             minimal risk to the fetus. Pregnant unaffected relatives will not be enrolled in this&#xD;
             study).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  All patients must be willing to have research samples stored for future studies and/or&#xD;
             other research purposes.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of other medical illnesses that would preclude individuals from undergoing routine&#xD;
        diagnostic testing or testing for immunologic features of immunodeficiency.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Warren Strober, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kimberly L Montgomery-Recht, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 827-0038</phone>
    <email>kim.montgomery-recht@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Warren Strober, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-6810</phone>
    <email>wstrober@niaid.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1989-I-0158.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jaffe JS, Eisenstein E, Sneller MC, Strober W. T-cell abnormalities in common variable immunodeficiency. Pediatr Res. 1993 Jan;33(1 Suppl):S24-7; discussion S27-8. doi: 10.1203/00006450-199305001-00128.</citation>
    <PMID>7679486</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mannon PJ, Fuss IJ, Dill S, Friend J, Groden C, Hornung R, Yang Z, Yi C, Quezado M, Brown M, Strober W. Excess IL-12 but not IL-23 accompanies the inflammatory bowel disease associated with common variable immunodeficiency. Gastroenterology. 2006 Sep;131(3):748-56. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2006.06.022.</citation>
    <PMID>16952544</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cunningham-Rundles C. Autoimmune manifestations in common variable immunodeficiency. J Clin Immunol. 2008 May;28 Suppl 1(Suppl 1):S42-5. doi: 10.1007/s10875-008-9182-7. Epub 2008 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>18322785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 15, 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Agammaglobulinemia</keyword>
  <keyword>CVID</keyword>
  <keyword>XLA</keyword>
  <keyword>Humoral Immunodeficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Common Variable Immunodeficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

