<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005213</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1092</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL038256</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005213</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lithium Countertransport and Blood Pressure In CARDIA and TOMHS</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To conduct ancillary studies of sodium-stimulated lithium counter-transport in the Chicago&#xD;
      components of the Coronary Heart Disease Risk Development in Young Adults (CARDIA) cohort and&#xD;
      in the Treatment of Mild Hypertension Study (TOMHS) cohort.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      CARDIA was a longitudinal study of the influence of lifestyle on coronary heart disease risk&#xD;
      factors during the young adult and post-young-adult years, the time period during which risk&#xD;
      for cardiovascular disease was thought to undergo crucial evolution. Four centers&#xD;
      participated in this study. The Chicago CARDIA population consisted of 1,100 Black and white&#xD;
      men and women age 18 to 30 at baseline, of diverse socioeconomic backgrounds.&#xD;
&#xD;
      TOMHS was a two phase double-blind randomized controlled clinical trial to determine whether&#xD;
      pharmacologic therapy in conjunction with nutritional-hygienic intervention for persons with&#xD;
      mild hypertension results in greater reduction of cardiovascular morbidity than&#xD;
      nutritional-hygienic treatment alone. Four clinical centers were involved in Phase I.&#xD;
      Participants were randomized into one of six treatment groups. Each group received&#xD;
      nutritional-hygienic treatment plus one of the following: placebo, diuretic, alpha blocker,&#xD;
      beta blocker, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor, calcium channel blocker. Randomization&#xD;
      was stratified to assure balance within each treatment group with regard to participants'&#xD;
      drug treatment status prior to randomization. The primary endpoint was cardiovascular&#xD;
      morbidity.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Abnormalities in cellular sodium metabolism have long been thought to play a role in the&#xD;
      pathogenesis of hypertension. Techniques for measuring membrane electrolyte transport rates&#xD;
      have been refined, providing an opportunity to characterize sodium metabolism in cells from&#xD;
      hypertensives. The early clinical studies examined erythrocytes and leukocytes because of&#xD;
      their easy accessibility and the possibility that they would reflect vascular tissue&#xD;
      metabolism, and documented differences in sodium fluxes between hypertensives and&#xD;
      normotensives. Subsequent studies have supported the early findings that abnormalities in&#xD;
      membrane cation transport were associated with essential hypertension.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The findings up to 1988 indicated that one or more transport systems might be altered in&#xD;
      essential hypertension but each system was not affected similarly, nor did all hypertensives&#xD;
      show the same changes in each of the transport systems studied. The most consistent findings&#xD;
      have been observed for sodium-stimulated lithium countertransport (LCT). Clinical and&#xD;
      population-based studies have revealed that mean LCT is significantly elevated among&#xD;
      hypertensives. In contrast, increased, decreased, and normal mean values have been reported&#xD;
      for sodium cotransport, and increased or normal mean values for adenosine triphosphate&#xD;
      (ATP)-dependent sodium-potassium pump activity.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The relationship between LCT and blood pressure has been examined in several studies. The&#xD;
      largest of these was an epidemiological survey involving 3,800 men and women age 5 to over 75&#xD;
      in Gubbio, Italy. LCT was significantly and positively associated with both systolic and&#xD;
      diastolic blood pressure in this population after controlling for age, sex, and weight, but,&#xD;
      after controlling also for other factors known to be related to blood pressure such as serum&#xD;
      uric acid and glucose, the relationship was inconsistently significant in this&#xD;
      cross-sectional study. In other cross-sectional research, LCT was found to account for three&#xD;
      percent of the variation in blood pressure in a study of healthy blood donors after&#xD;
      adjustment for weight and age. Other cross-sectional population-based studies involving&#xD;
      smaller numbers have shown a significant relationship between LCT and diastolic blood&#xD;
      pressure in adolescents and in white adults, but not among Black adults; also between LCT and&#xD;
      systolic blood pressure, but not diastolic blood pressure, in Black children and white&#xD;
      adolescents.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Much of the data available in 1988 had been derived from small numbers in cross-sectional&#xD;
      studies, chiefly clinical, only a few population-based. Large samples were needed to provide&#xD;
      adequate power to detect relationships among LCT and demographic, dietary, and other factors.&#xD;
      Prospective data were needed to assess whether LCT was an independent risk factor for future&#xD;
      development of high blood pressure in people normotensive at baseline, whether LCT could be&#xD;
      modified, and whether this change was associated with changes in blood pressure.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the cross-sectional CARDIA investigation, studies were conducted on the relationships&#xD;
      among lithium countertransport, blood pressure, and factors related to blood pressure such as&#xD;
      age, sex, race, weight, body mass index, pulse, dietary factors, alcohol intake, serum&#xD;
      glucose, triglycerides, cholesterol, high density lipoprotein cholesterol, uric acid, and&#xD;
      ionized and total calcium. Prospective data were also collected from TOMHS to examine whether&#xD;
      lithium countertransport was modified in mild hypertension by diet or by a combination of&#xD;
      diet and antihypertensive drugs. Lithium countertransport was assayed in erythrocytes at the&#xD;
      second examination in CARDIA and at baseline, 12 months, and 24 months in TOMHS.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in&#xD;
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 1988</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 1990</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2000</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 15, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 15, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 16, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

