<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001971</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>910214</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>91-DK-0214</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001971</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Patients With Liver Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Patients With Liver Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study aims to evaluate, investigate, and follow-up patients suffering from acute&#xD;
      and chronic liver disease. The study will focus on understanding diseases affecting the&#xD;
      liver.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients participating in the study will first undergo a routine check-up as an outpatient.&#xD;
      They will be asked to provide blood and urine samples for laboratory testing and will undergo&#xD;
      an ultrasound of the liver. Ultrasound examinations use sound waves to determine the size and&#xD;
      texture of the liver. After the initial visit subjects will be requested to follow-up once a&#xD;
      year at the outpatient department for a similar check-up.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Additional tests may be requested throughout the study to provide information for other&#xD;
      research studies and individual consent will be requested. These tests may include liver&#xD;
      biopsies, skin biopsies, and / or specialized blood, plasma, and lymphocyte examinations.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subjects that qualify for medications presently being studied may be offered the opportunity&#xD;
      to benefit from experimental therapy....&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Description:&#xD;
&#xD;
      This is a clinical research protocol to allow for collection of samples and data obtained&#xD;
      during clinical evaluation and long-term follow up of patients who have an acute or chronic&#xD;
      liver disease. The protocol is designed to create a repository to study the natural history&#xD;
      and pathogenesis of various liver diseases such as acute and chronic hepatitis B, C, D and E,&#xD;
      primary biliary cirrhosis, primary sclerosing cholangitis, Wilson's disease, hemochromatosis,&#xD;
      nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH), noncirrhotic portal hypertension, hepatocellular&#xD;
      carcinoma, and cryptogenic or poorly defined forms of chronic liver disease. Samples&#xD;
      collected during the course of clinical care for patients with liver disease include blood,&#xD;
      saliva, urine, stool, and residual tissue obtained during clinically-indicated liver biopsies&#xD;
      not otherwise needed for clinical care. Additionally, subjects with liver disease will be&#xD;
      asked to provide a blood sample for genetic analysis. Healthy volunteers will be recruited&#xD;
      and asked to provide a blood sample to serve as controls for the genetic analyses. Research&#xD;
      will be conducted to investigate genetic factors that may contribute to liver diseases&#xD;
&#xD;
      Objectives: Primary Objective&#xD;
&#xD;
      To collect data and samples during clinical evaluation, treatment and follow-up of&#xD;
      participants for future use in studies of liver diseases&#xD;
&#xD;
      Secondary Objective&#xD;
&#xD;
      To determine if genetic factors may contribute to the susceptibility, progression, outcome,&#xD;
      or treatment success of different liver diseases.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 27, 1992</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Predisposition and outcomes related to liver disease susceptibility, progression, and treatment response</measure>
    <time_frame>Annual visits</time_frame>
    <description>Predisposition and outcomes related to liver disease susceptibility, progression, and treatment response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8050</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis D</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis B</condition>
  <condition>Liver Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy individuals</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy individuals who have recovered from liver diseases or who are healthy volunteers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Liver disease patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This is a general clinical research protocol to allow for evaluation, investigation and&#xD;
        long-term follow up of patients who have an acute or chronic liver disease. The protocol is&#xD;
        designed to study the natural history and pathogenesis of various liver diseases such as&#xD;
        acute and chronic hepatitis B, C, D and E, primary biliary cirrhosis, primary sclerosing&#xD;
        cholangitis, Wilson's disease, hemochromatosis, nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH),&#xD;
        noncirrhotic portal hypertension, hepatocellular carcinoma, and cryptogenic or poorly&#xD;
        defined forms of chronic liver disease.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Affected Subjects&#xD;
&#xD;
        In order to be eligible to participate in this study, an affected participant must meet all&#xD;
        of the following criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. &gt;=2 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Meets one of the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Suspected or evidence of acute or chronic liver disease on evaluation by a&#xD;
                  referring licensed independent practitioner (LIP), OR&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. At risk for acute or chronic liver disease&#xD;
&#xD;
        Healthy Volunteers&#xD;
&#xD;
        In order to be eligible to participate in this study, a healthy volunteer must meet all of&#xD;
        the following criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. &gt;= 18 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. In good general health as evidenced by medical history&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Affected Participants&#xD;
&#xD;
        An affected participant who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from&#xD;
        participation in this study:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. History of significant medical illnesses that might interfere with prolonged follow up&#xD;
        evaluation&#xD;
&#xD;
        Healthy Volunteers&#xD;
&#xD;
        A healthy volunteer who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from&#xD;
        participation in this study:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Any chronic medical condition, including (but not limited to) heart, kidney, or lung&#xD;
             diseases&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Taking any regular medications or supplements (with the exception of regular&#xD;
             multivitamins and/or oral contraceptives)&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Average alcohol consumption &gt; 1 drink/day in past 6 months, per self-report&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. History of liver disease (with the exception of neonatal jaundice)&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. History of severe illness, infection or major surgery in the past year&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. History of cancer (with the exception of basal cell carcinoma resected &gt; 1 year prior&#xD;
             to enrollment)&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. BMI &lt; 18 or BMI &gt;25&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Hemoglobin &lt; 11 (women) or hemoglobin &lt; 12 (men)&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. ALT &gt;35 (men) or ALT &gt;25 (women)&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Alkaline Phosphatase &gt;= 150&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Bilirubin &gt;2 g/dL&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. HIV positive, Anti-HCV positive, HBsAg positive or Anti-HBc positive&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Pregnancy&#xD;
&#xD;
         14. Inability to provide informed consent&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>T. Jake Liang, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patricia E Alcivar</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-6121</phone>
    <email>patricia.alcivar@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>T. Jake Liang, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-1721</phone>
    <email>jakel@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1991-DK-0214.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 31, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 19, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hepatitis B</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis C</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis D</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Hepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

