<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000915</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HIVNET D01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000915</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An HIV Vaccine Preparedness Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>HIV Vaccine Preparedness Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to estimate the rate at which a certain population becomes&#xD;
      infected with HIV. The individuals examined in this study are people who are expected to take&#xD;
      part in future studies of HIV vaccines and nonvaccine HIV prevention studies. This study also&#xD;
      examines the chances of becoming HIV-positive based on certain risk factors under conditions&#xD;
      that are similar to the conditions that would exist in HIV vaccine and non-HIV prevention&#xD;
      studies.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Before studying the effectiveness of a potential HIV vaccine, it is important to learn about&#xD;
      the range of HIV risk behaviors in the potential participants of these studies. The&#xD;
      probability of HIV infection associated with these risk behaviors should also be examined.&#xD;
      This study is designed to increase the ability of HIVNET to put into place HIV prevention&#xD;
      trials, to increase the diversity of trial participants, and to target populations at highest&#xD;
      risk for HIV infection.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Vaccine preparedness studies are necessary in order to prepare for launching preventive HIV&#xD;
      vaccine efficacy trials. It is important to gather information on the risk of HIV infection&#xD;
      among recruited populations, the extent and stability of HIV risk behaviors in these&#xD;
      populations, and the risk of HIV infection associated with risk behaviors. This vaccine&#xD;
      preparedness study is designed to expand the capacity of the HIVNET to implement HIV&#xD;
      prevention trials, increase the diversity of its participant population, and further target&#xD;
      populations at highest risk of HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants complete a total of 6 scheduled study visits: 2 at baseline, 2 at follow-up 6&#xD;
      months later, and 2 at follow-up 12 months after enrollment. Participant risk behaviors and&#xD;
      knowledge of and attitudes toward HIV vaccine and other HIV prevention trials are assessed at&#xD;
      each time point. HIV infection status is tested by standard HIV ELISA and Western blot at&#xD;
      follow-up, as well as at participant request throughout the study. Participants are&#xD;
      instructed to recognize and report suspected primary HIV infection based on symptoms or&#xD;
      high-risk exposures. HIV pre-test, risk reduction, and post-test counseling is provided in&#xD;
      accordance with CDC standards of practice. Participants who become infected with HIV during&#xD;
      the study are counseled and referred for medical and psychosocial services.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>4892</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vaccine preparedness</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participants meet the following criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  HIV-seronegative.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Available for 6 months of the study. (Note:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participants who plan to move from one study location to another are eligible.)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willing and able to provide information for locator purposes.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Report one or more of the following risk behaviors:&#xD;
&#xD;
        For men:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Intravenous or intramuscular injection of any drug on an average of 3 or more days per&#xD;
             week during the last 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Anal intercourse (receptive or insertive) with one or more other men in the last year.&#xD;
&#xD;
        For women:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Intravenous or intramuscular injection of any drug on an average of 3 or more days per&#xD;
             week during the last 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Having a current male sex partner who is infected with HIV.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Having a current male sex partner who has injected drugs in the last 5 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Having 5 or more male sex partners in the last year.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diagnosis of syphilis, chlamydia, gonorrhea, first episode herpes, pelvic inflammatory&#xD;
             disease, and/or trichomoniasis in the last year.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Exchange of sex for money or drugs in the last year.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of crack cocaine in the last 12 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        See General Inclusion Criteria for required risk behaviors.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Volunteers must be:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  HIV-positive through HIVNET testing or HIV-seronegative by EIA.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Presently in a sexual relationship of at least 6 months duration with the intention to&#xD;
             remain with this partner for the duration of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willing to identify and recruit this sexual partner to which he/she has disclosed or&#xD;
             will disclose HIV serostatus.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willing to receive counseling and HIV testing (HIV-seronegative partners only).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willing to agree to be interviewed with their partner and individually.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willing to continue engaging in sex with their partner.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willing to participate in a couples-based condom promotion intervention.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willing and able to attend each scheduled intervention/follow-up study visit.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Co-existing Condition:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Persons with the following symptoms or conditions are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  An obvious psychological or psychiatric disorder that would preclude provision of&#xD;
             informed consent or otherwise contraindicate study participation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any condition which in the opinion of the principal investigator would interfere with&#xD;
             achieving the study objectives.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Men at risk through anal intercourse only are excluded if they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Currently have a single HIV-seronegative partner with whom they have been in a&#xD;
             mutually monogamous relationship for at least 2 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Men and women at risk through injection only are excluded if they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have been participating in any methadone drug treatment program for at least the last&#xD;
             6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Currently obtain over 50 percent of needles/syringes for injection of drugs from a&#xD;
             needle exchange program.&#xD;
&#xD;
        NOTE:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Meeting the following extremely high injection risk criteria overrides the exclusion&#xD;
             criteria for injection risk as outlined above:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Using a needle or syringe after one or more known HIV-positive persons 2 or more times&#xD;
             in the past 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Using a needle or syringe after persons of unknown HIV status in the past 3 months&#xD;
             provided the following two conditions are true:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  (1) report using a needle or syringe after someone else 2 or more different times in&#xD;
             the past 3 months and (2) report using a needle or syringe after 3 or more different&#xD;
             persons in the past 3 months. (This second criterion could be met in 3 episodes of&#xD;
             injection with a single injection partner, if the participant used a needle or syringe&#xD;
             after a different person each time. Alternatively, the criterion could be met in a&#xD;
             single episode of injection, if the participant used a needle or syringe after 3 or&#xD;
             more persons had used a single set of works.)&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Enrollment in an HIV vaccine trial, unless approval is obtained from the Data&#xD;
             Management Committee Project Officer.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Risk Behavior:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  See General Exclusion Criteria for excluded risk behaviors.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dave Metzger</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>George Seage</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles County / Health Research Assoc / Drew Med Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90059</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ of Illinois Hosp at Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Univ</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bronx Lebanon Hosp Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10456</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York Blood Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10456</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York Univ Med Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ of Pennsylvania / HIVNET</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miriam Hosp</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02906</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woody GE, VanEtten-Lee ML, McKirnan D, Donnell D, Metzger D, Seage G 3rd, Gross M; HIVNET VPS 001 Protocol Team. Substance use among men who have sex with men: comparison with a national household survey. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2001 May 1;27(1):86-90. doi: 10.1097/00126334-200105010-00015.</citation>
    <PMID>11404525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 1999</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>AIDS Vaccines</keyword>
  <keyword>Incidence</keyword>
  <keyword>Knowledge, Attitudes, Practice</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk-Taking</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

