<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001582</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>970143</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>97-C-0143</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001582</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00899067</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigation of the Human Immune Response in Normal Subjects and Patients With Disorders of the Immune System and Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Collection of Blood, Bone Marrow and Tissue Samples for the Investigation of the Human Immune Response, Lymphoma Biology and HTLV-1 Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This protocol is being submitted to consolidate, update, and expand two previously approved&#xD;
      protocols (77-C-0066 and 82-C-0044) into a single protocol. The purpose of this study is to&#xD;
      examine the factors involved in the regulation of the immune system of healthy individuals&#xD;
      and to define the abnormalities in this regulation that underlies the immunological disorders&#xD;
      of patients with a variety of immunodeficiency and malignant disorders. The studies will&#xD;
      include the ex vivo phenotypic and functional analysis of the network of cells involved in&#xD;
      humoral and cellular immune responses, and in vivo testing for the capacity to make&#xD;
      delayed-type hypersensitivity and humoral responses following immunization with a variety of&#xD;
      antigens. Individuals to be studied will include patients with a variety of malignancies and&#xD;
      patients with primary and secondary immunodeficiency disorders. Selected family members or&#xD;
      family members known to be genetic carriers of certain immunodeficiency diseases as well as&#xD;
      normal, unrelated individuals will also be studied. A small number of procedures will be used&#xD;
      including analysis of blood obtained by phlebotomy, apheresis, skin testing and recall&#xD;
      antigens and immunization to assess humoral immunity.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  The evaluation of the cells of the immune system and HTLV-1 infection has been a central&#xD;
           focus of the Metabolism Branch for the past 30 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Blood obtained by apheresis or blood drawing, skin biopsies and other tissues will be&#xD;
           evaluated for abnormalities related to immunity, HTLV-1 infection and the immune system.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Advances in the characterization of acquired genetic changes in tumor samples has&#xD;
&#xD;
      led to insights for the development of targeted therapy of malignancy&#xD;
&#xD;
      Objectives:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  To characterize the molecular biology and immunological features as well as the clinical&#xD;
           course of individuals with suspected or known disorders of the immune system or cancer&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  To define the nature of the immunological, genetic and epigenetic abnormalities in the&#xD;
           cells of patients with immunodeficiency diseases associated with infections and/or a&#xD;
           high incidence of malignancy and in patients with cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  To obtain whole blood, plasma and leukocytes, as well as skin, lymph node and bone&#xD;
           marrow biopsies on patients with immunodeficiency or cancer to investigate the immune&#xD;
           system.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Eligibility:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Subjects with cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Subjects with immunodeficiency.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Subjects with HTLV-1 infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Design:&#xD;
&#xD;
      -This is a natural history study that permits tissue acquisition for analysis of the immune&#xD;
      system and HTLV-1 infection.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 7, 1997</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Create Biobank</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>No statistical endpoints are identified for this study; the purpose of the study is to acquire information regarding various immunodeficiency syndromes, HTLV-1 infection and malignancies. The data collected will not be combined for a summary report of the entire study; however, reports for specific disease entities may be published.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>ATL</condition>
  <condition>Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Suspected or known disorder of the immune system or cancer; or, known or potential carrier of autoimmune disorder or immunodeficiency disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Primary clinical patients/population with a suspected or known disorder of the immune&#xD;
        system or cancer per the eligibility criteria.@@@&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participants must meet at least one of these criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Have suspected or known disorder of the immune system or cancer&#xD;
&#xD;
        Be a known or potential carrier of autoimmune disorder or immunodeficiency disease.&#xD;
        Specific disorders may include but are not limited to:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  X-linked (severe combined immunodeficiency)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Autosomal recessive SCID&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  X-linked CD40 ligand deficiency&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Common variable immunodeficiency&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ataxia-telangiectasia&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Wiskott Aldrich syndrome&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  DiGeorge syndrome&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Infection with HTLV-1&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age greater than or equal to 18 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participant must be able to understand and sign informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participants who will undergo apheresis must have hematocrit greater than 28%, and platelet&#xD;
        count greater than 50,000.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects for whom apheresis is desired but whose counts are lower than those above must be&#xD;
        evaluated and approved by a Department of Transfusion Medicine consult physician.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Weight greater than 25 kg is necessary for apheresis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Overall Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnant women will not be eligible for any aspect of this protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria for Apheresis Alone:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Any diagnosed medical condition which may be worsened by the apheresis procedure.&#xD;
        Specifically the participant should not have any of the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Congestive Heart Failure&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. History of angina&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Severe hypotension (at the discretion of the participant's physician, the apheresis&#xD;
             staff and the attending physician from the Department of Transfusion Medicine (DTM)&#xD;
             per DTM Standard Operating Policies.)&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Poorly controlled hypertension (average baseline blood pressure greater than 160/90)&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. History of a coagulation protein disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pediatric patients (less than 18 years) will not undergo apheresis.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin C Conlon, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>NCI Medical Oncology Referral Office</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 760-6050</phone>
    <email>ncimo_referrals@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kevin C Conlon, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 760-6087</phone>
    <email>conlonkc@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1997-C-0143.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 23, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Autoimmune Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune System Evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>Human Response Investigation</keyword>
  <keyword>Tissue Acquisition</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>.All IPD recorded in the medical record will be shared with intramural investigators upon request. @@@@@@In addition, all large scale genomic sequencing data will be shared with subscribers to dbGaP. @@@@@@All collected IPD will be shared with collaborators under the terms of collaborative agreements.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Clinical data will be available during the study and indefinitely. @@@@@@Genomic data will be available once genomic data are uploaded per protocol GDS plan for as long as database is active.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Genomic data will be available once genomic data are uploaded per protocol GDS plan for as long as database is active.@@@@@@Genomic data will be made available via dbGaP through requests to the data custodians.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

