<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000683</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AVEG 002</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10537</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000683</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I Multicenter, Randomized, Double-Blind Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Immunogenicity of Recombinant Vaccinia Virus Expressing the Envelope Glycoproteins of Human Immunodeficiency Virus</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Multicenter, Randomized, Double-Blind Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Immunogenicity of Recombinant Vaccinia Virus Expressing the Envelope Glycoproteins of Human Immunodeficiency Virus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluation of the safety and immunogenicity (immunological reactivity) of HIVAC-1e vaccine.&#xD;
      An additional goal is to determine which dose level of vaccine might be most effective.&#xD;
      Specific questions to be addressed in this part of the study include: Are there adverse&#xD;
      reactions to gp160 vaccine when given to vaccinees previously immunized with a&#xD;
      vaccinia-recombinant? Does gp160 vaccination of prior HIVAC-1e vaccine result in stimulation&#xD;
      of neutralizing antibody and other humoral immune responses? Does vaccination with gp160&#xD;
      enhance the development of cell-mediated immune responses in HIVAC-1e vaccinees? Is the&#xD;
      magnitude of immune response to gp160 booster immunization greater following priming with&#xD;
      GP160 recombinant vaccinia (HIVAC-1e) vaccination than priming with three doses of purified&#xD;
      recombinant gp160? AMENDED: An 80 mcg dose of gp160 has been chosen for the booster because&#xD;
      this dose has been shown to be safe and immunogenic in previous trials and allows comparison&#xD;
      of the late boost in this protocol with the late boost in the protocol in which patients were&#xD;
      primed with three doses of gp160. Original design: HIVAC-1e vaccine is a preparation of the&#xD;
      envelope protein of HIV (the virus that causes AIDS). The protein is produced by genetic&#xD;
      modification in vaccinia virus. The purpose of a vaccine is to produce an artificially&#xD;
      increased immunity to a particular disease, in this case, AIDS. Since there is no known cure&#xD;
      for AIDS, the control of this disease necessitates the development of effective prevention&#xD;
      such as vaccines.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      AMENDED: An 80 mcg dose of gp160 has been chosen for the booster because this dose has been&#xD;
      shown to be safe and immunogenic in previous trials and allows comparison of the late boost&#xD;
      in this protocol with the late boost in the protocol in which patients were primed with three&#xD;
      doses of gp160. Original design: HIVAC-1e vaccine is a preparation of the envelope protein of&#xD;
      HIV (the virus that causes AIDS). The protein is produced by genetic modification in vaccinia&#xD;
      virus. The purpose of a vaccine is to produce an artificially increased immunity to a&#xD;
      particular disease, in this case, AIDS. Since there is no known cure for AIDS, the control of&#xD;
      this disease necessitates the development of effective prevention such as vaccines.&#xD;
&#xD;
      AMENDED: Participants in the amended study will be given one injection in the deltoid muscle&#xD;
      of gp160 vaccine. The injection of gp160 will be given 2 months after the first take with the&#xD;
      HIVAC-1e vaccine. After each inoculation, volunteers will be observed for one hour. For four&#xD;
      days after each inoculation, each participant will be interviewed daily to monitor side&#xD;
      effects and asked to record their temperature and symptoms twice daily. It is anticipated&#xD;
      that a cohort of approximately 20 HIVAC-1e recipients from the participating AIDS Vaccine&#xD;
      Evaluation Units will agree to receive the booster immunizations of gp160, and that this&#xD;
      number of patients will be adequate to determine the booster effect of gp160. Original&#xD;
      design: Study patients receive two immunizations, one at the beginning of the study and a&#xD;
      second one eight weeks later. These immunizations are administered by scarification on the&#xD;
      arm, the same way that smallpox vaccines were given for several years. The patients are&#xD;
      divided into two groups. The control group receives a derivative of the smallpox vaccine that&#xD;
      is used to produce HIVAC-1e vaccine. The treatment group actually receives HIVAC-1e. Whether&#xD;
      a patient receives the parent virus or the vaccine is determined randomly by computer, and&#xD;
      neither the patient nor the physician knows who actually receives the vaccine. The group&#xD;
      receiving the parent virus and the group receiving HIVAC-1e are then divided into three&#xD;
      subgroups receiving different doses of HIVAC-1e, in order to test the effectiveness of&#xD;
      different doses of HIVAC-1e. Following the first inoculation and the booster inoculation&#xD;
      eight weeks later, patients have the vaccination site covered with a special waterproof&#xD;
      bandage until the vaccination site has healed. Participants are counseled on how to avoid&#xD;
      contact spread of the vaccine virus including hand washing, management of the bandage, and&#xD;
      separation from persons at high risk for the complications of the virus infection. Patients&#xD;
      are closely followed for the first four weeks following immunization and then followed for a&#xD;
      minimum of one year. Women are included only if willing to provide continuing information on&#xD;
      sexual practices and menstrual patterns, and furnish urine samples, as appropriate, for&#xD;
      pregnancy testing on the day of/before vaccination and every other week throughout the 56th&#xD;
      day after receipt of vaccine. At the Johns Hopkins site, patients are compensated depending&#xD;
      on how far they have to travel as long as they commit to every-other-day visits for the first&#xD;
      30 days. This is to change the bandage and check on healing. Interested patients should call&#xD;
      collect for additional information about travel pay.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1993</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>54</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HIVAC-1e</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gp160 Vaccine (MicroGeneSys)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must demonstrate the following clinical and laboratory findings:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Normal history and physical examination.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Normal chest X-ray (optional).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Normal urinalysis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Negative ELISA.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Negative Western blot test.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Negative HIV culture.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No evidence of smallpox vaccination.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Note:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  As an operational definition, an individual can be considered &quot;vaccinia naive&quot; only if&#xD;
             no scar is observable and the patient claims and/or has evidence of not being&#xD;
             vaccinated. If the patient does not know his/her history, it should be presumed that&#xD;
             he/she was vaccinated.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients will be excluded from the study for the following reasons:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Appearance of or serologic or clinical evidence of HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Appearance of or serologic or clinical evidence of clinically active viral infections,&#xD;
             including mononucleosis, Epstein-Barr virus, cytomegalovirus which may affect HIV&#xD;
             immunocompetence.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Syphilis, gonorrhea, or any other sexually transmitted diseases including chlamydia or&#xD;
             pelvic inflammatory disease in the last 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of immunodeficiency or chronic illness.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Evidence of depression.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of positive PPD (tuberculosis exposure).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Positive syphilis serology.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Positive for circulating Hepatitis B antigen.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Eczema, active or within the past year.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Household contact with someone who is pregnant.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Household contact with children less than 12 months old.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Household contact with anyone with eczema.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Household contact with anyone with immunodeficiencies.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Vaccinia immunity.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Note:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current PPD test is required only if Merieux skin reaction to the tuberculin antigen&#xD;
             is positive.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  If the patient does not know his/her vaccine history, it should be presumed that&#xD;
             he/she was vaccinated.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Treatment:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded within 1 year of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Treatment for psychiatric problems.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded within 6 months of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Blood transfusions or cryoprecipitates.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients may not have any of the following diseases or symptoms:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Appearance of or serologic or clinical evidence of HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Appearance of or serologic or clinical evidence of clinically active viral infections,&#xD;
             including mononucleosis, Epstein-Barr virus, cytomegalovirus which may affect HIV&#xD;
             immunocompetence.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Syphilis, gonorrhea, or any other sexually transmitted diseases including chlamydia or&#xD;
             pelvic inflammatory disease in the last 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of immunodeficiency or chronic illness.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Evidence of depression.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Eczema, active or within the past year.&#xD;
&#xD;
        High risk behavior for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection, including:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any history of intravenous drug use.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Syphilis, gonorrhea, or any other sexually transmitted diseases including chlamydia or&#xD;
             pelvic inflammatory disease in the last 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  More than 2 sexual partners or sexual contact with a high-risk partner in the last 6&#xD;
             months.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Koff W</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ. of Rochester AVEG</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>McElrath MJ, Corey L, Berger D, Hoffman MC, Klucking S, Dragavon J, Peterson E, Greenberg PD. Immune responses elicited by recombinant vaccinia-human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) envelope and HIV envelope protein: analysis of the durability of responses and effect of repeated boosting. J Infect Dis. 1994 Jan;169(1):41-7. doi: 10.1093/infdis/169.1.41.</citation>
    <PMID>8277196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Montefiori DC, Graham BS, Zhou JY, Zhou JT, Ahearn JM. Binding of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 to the C3b/C4b receptor CR1 (CD35) and red blood cells in the presence of envelope-specific antibodies and complement. National Institutes of Health AIDS Vaccine Clinical Trials Networks. J Infect Dis. 1994 Aug;170(2):429-32. doi: 10.1093/infdis/170.2.429.</citation>
    <PMID>8035031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Montefiori DC, Graham BS, Zhou J, Zhou J, Bucco RA, Schwartz DH, Cavacini LA, Posner MR. V3-specific neutralizing antibodies in sera from HIV-1 gp160-immunized volunteers block virus fusion and act synergistically with human monoclonal antibody to the conformation-dependent CD4 binding site of gp120. NIH-NIAID AIDS Vaccine Clinical Trials Network. J Clin Invest. 1993 Aug;92(2):840-7. doi: 10.1172/JCI116658.</citation>
    <PMID>8349820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graham BS. Clinical trials of AIDS vaccines in seronegative volunteers: vectors and combinations. AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses. 1992 Aug;8(8):1327-8. doi: 10.1089/aid.1992.8.1327. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>1466951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Montefiori DC, Graham BS, Kliks S, Wright PF. Serum antibodies to HIV-1 in recombinant vaccinia virus recipients boosted with purified recombinant gp160. NIAID AIDS Vaccine Clinical Trials Network. J Clin Immunol. 1992 Nov;12(6):429-39. doi: 10.1007/BF00918855.</citation>
    <PMID>1287035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cooney EL, Collier AC, Greenberg PD, Coombs RW, Zarling J, Arditti DE, Hoffman MC, Hu SL, Corey L. Safety of and immunological response to a recombinant vaccinia virus vaccine expressing HIV envelope glycoprotein. Lancet. 1991 Mar 9;337(8741):567-72. doi: 10.1016/0140-6736(91)91636-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1671940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graham BS, Matthews TJ, Belshe RB, Clements ML, Dolin R, Wright PF, Gorse GJ, Schwartz DH, Keefer MC, Bolognesi DP, et al. Augmentation of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 neutralizing antibody by priming with gp160 recombinant vaccinia and boosting with rgp160 in vaccinia-naive adults. The NIAID AIDS Vaccine Clinical Trials Network. J Infect Dis. 1993 Mar;167(3):533-7. doi: 10.1093/infdis/167.3.533.</citation>
    <PMID>8095059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graham BS, Rowland JM, Modliszewski A, Montefiori DC. Antifusion activity in sera from persons infected with human immunodeficiency virus type 1. J Clin Microbiol. 1990 Dec;28(12):2608-11. doi: 10.1128/jcm.28.12.2608-2611.1990.</citation>
    <PMID>2279989</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hammond SA, Bollinger RC, Stanhope PE, Quinn TC, Schwartz D, Clements ML, Siliciano RF. Comparative clonal analysis of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1)-specific CD4+ and CD8+ cytolytic T lymphocytes isolated from seronegative humans immunized with candidate HIV-1 vaccines. J Exp Med. 1992 Dec 1;176(6):1531-42. doi: 10.1084/jem.176.6.1531.</citation>
    <PMID>1460417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perales MA, Schwartz DH, Fabry JA, Lieberman J. A vaccinia-gp160-based vaccine but not a gp160 protein vaccine elicits anti-gp160 cytotoxic T lymphocytes in some HIV-1 seronegative vaccinees. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr Hum Retrovirol. 1995 Sep 1;10(1):27-35.</citation>
    <PMID>7648281</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2021</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 26, 2021</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 26, 2021</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 2, 2021</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vaccines, Synthetic</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccinia Virus</keyword>
  <keyword>Viral Envelope Proteins</keyword>
  <keyword>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS Vaccines</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Seronegativity</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Preventive Vaccine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vaccinia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

