<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001641</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>970089</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>97-HG-0089</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001641</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Heritable Connective Tissue Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical and Molecular Manifestations of Heritable Connective Tissue Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purposes of this study are to identify the genes responsible for inherited connective&#xD;
      tissue disorders and learn about the range of medical problems they cause. It will&#xD;
      investigate whether specific gene changes cause specific medical problems and will establish&#xD;
      diagnostic criteria (signs and symptoms) for the individual syndromes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Children and adults with a known or suspected inherited connective tissue disorder (Marfan,&#xD;
      Ehlers-Danlos or Stickler syndrome, or other closely related disorders) and their family&#xD;
      members may be eligible for this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients enrolled in the study will have a medical history, physical examination and blood&#xD;
      tests, as well as other procedures that may include:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Echocardiogram (ultrasound of the heart)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  X-rays and other imaging studies, such as magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or&#xD;
           computerized tomography (CT) scans&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Lung function studies&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Urine tests&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Skin biopsy (removal of a small piece of tissue, under local anesthetic, for microscopic&#xD;
           examination)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Examination by various specialists (e.g., in ophthalmology, gastroenterology,&#xD;
           rehabilitation medicine) as needed&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Questionnaires regarding chronic pain and fatigue, quality of life, and the impact of&#xD;
           the connective tissue disorder on the patient and family.&#xD;
&#xD;
      (Patients who wish to enroll but cannot travel to NIH may have a more limited participation,&#xD;
      including review of medical records, telephone interview regarding personal and family&#xD;
      history, and collection of a specimen (blood, skin biopsy, or other) for genetic testing.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will be notified of genetic testing results that show a change responsible for their&#xD;
      connective tissue disorder. If they wish, the information will also be sent to their local&#xD;
      health care provider, along with recommendations for additional tests or treatment options.&#xD;
      No treatment is offered as part of this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participating family members who do not themselves have a connective tissue disorder will&#xD;
      provide a small blood sample for gene testing and be interviewed by telephone about their&#xD;
      personal and family health history. Those whose blood test results show a gene change&#xD;
      associated with a connective tissue disorder will be invited to NIH for a discussion of the&#xD;
      findings or referred to a genetic center in their area.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We will investigate the clinical manifestations and molecular genetic defects of heritable&#xD;
      connective tissue disorders, concentrating on the Marfan, Stickler, and Ehlers-Danlos&#xD;
      syndromes. Although each of these conditions has been known for many years, the full spectrum&#xD;
      of the associated phenotypes continues to be expanded and the genetic etiology of these&#xD;
      conditions has not been completely elucidated. In addition, many patients have features&#xD;
      overlapping two or more of the described syndromes, precluding unequivocal diagnosis. The&#xD;
      goals of this study are to further define and characterize the full phenotype and natural&#xD;
      history of these disorders, and to perform genetic linkage, gene identification, mutation&#xD;
      detection, and genotype/phenotype correlations in affected individuals and families.&#xD;
      Individuals suspected to have Marfan, Stickler or Ehlers-Danlos syndrome or a closely related&#xD;
      disorder, as well as interested family members, will be enrolled. Participants will undergo&#xD;
      genetic analyses and periodic clinical assessment. The expected outcomes will be improved&#xD;
      clinical descriptions of the conditions and gene and mutation identification with analysis of&#xD;
      genotype/phenotype correlations.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 2002</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>900</enrollment>
  <condition>Connective Tissue Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dissecting Aneurysm</condition>
  <condition>Ehlers Danlos Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Marfan Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Nail Patella Syndrome</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Individuals and their family members will be offered enrollment if they have a suspected or&#xD;
        established diagnosis of Marfan, Stickler, Ehlers-Danlos, or a closely related syndrome.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Personal or family history of one or more of the following features in a pattern suggestive&#xD;
        of a heritable connective tissue disorder:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Marfanoid body habitus;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Aortic dilatation and/or dissection;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Ectopia lentis, detached retina, vitreous degeneration and/or early onset high myopia;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Posterior cleft palate; joint laxity and/or dislocation;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Premature osteoarthritis;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Skin fragility, striae, easy bruisability and/or hyperextensibility;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pectus excavatum or carinatum;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Scoliosis, spondylolisthesis, and/or dural ectasia;&#xD;
&#xD;
        High frequency sensorineural hearing loss.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Inability to provide informed consent.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beighton P, de Paepe A, Danks D, Finidori G, Gedde-Dahl T, Goodman R, Hall JG, Hollister DW, Horton W, McKusick VA, et al. International Nosology of Heritable Disorders of Connective Tissue, Berlin, 1986. Am J Med Genet. 1988 Mar;29(3):581-94. doi: 10.1002/ajmg.1320290316. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>3287925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cutting GR, Kazazian HH Jr, Antonarakis SE, Killen PD, Yamada Y, Francomano CA. Macrorestriction mapping of COL4A1 and COL4A2 collagen genes on human chromosome 13q34. Genomics. 1988 Oct;3(3):256-63. doi: 10.1016/0888-7543(88)90086-9.</citation>
    <PMID>3224982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dietz HC, Pyeritz RE, Hall BD, Cadle RG, Hamosh A, Schwartz J, Meyers DA, Francomano CA. The Marfan syndrome locus: confirmation of assignment to chromosome 15 and identification of tightly linked markers at 15q15-q21.3. Genomics. 1991 Feb;9(2):355-61. doi: 10.1016/0888-7543(91)90264-f.</citation>
    <PMID>2004786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2002</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Fibrillin</keyword>
  <keyword>Collagen</keyword>
  <keyword>Marfan Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Stickler Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Aortic Dissection</keyword>
  <keyword>Ehlers-Danlos</keyword>
  <keyword>Connective Tissue Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Nail-Patella Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Marfan Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arachnodactyly</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nail-Patella Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aneurysm, Dissecting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Connective Tissue Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

