<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00004575</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000077</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-H-0077</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00004575</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Miconazole on Blood Flow</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of Miconazole as an Inhibitor of Endothelium-Derived Hyperpolarizing Factor</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will investigate the effect of the drug miconazole on blood vessel dilation.&#xD;
      Miconazole stops production of EDHF, a substance that causes arteries to dilate. EDHF is&#xD;
      produced by the cells that line blood vessels.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Normal volunteers between the ages of 21 to 60 may participate in this study. Candidates will&#xD;
      be screened for eligibility with a medical history, physical examination, electrocardiogram&#xD;
      and routine laboratory tests. Those enrolled will be injected with miconazole to study its&#xD;
      effects on blood vessels.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study participants will take three aspirin tablets. After administration of a local&#xD;
      anesthetic, small tubes will be inserted through a needle into the artery and vein of the&#xD;
      forearm. These will be used to measure blood pressure and to draw blood samples during the&#xD;
      study. Forearm blood flow will be measured using pressure cuffs placed on the wrist and upper&#xD;
      arm, and a strain gauge (a rubber band device) placed around the forearm. When the cuffs are&#xD;
      inflated, blood will flow into the arm, stretching the strain gauge, and the flow measurement&#xD;
      will be recorded.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Small doses of four drugs-bradykinin, sodium nitroprusside, miconazole, and LNMMA-will be&#xD;
      given through the arterial catheter. Bradykinin stimulates the release of EDHF and can lower&#xD;
      blood pressure. Sodium nitroprusside causes blood vessels to dilate and is used to treat high&#xD;
      blood pressure and heart failure. Miconazole is commonly prescribed to treat various&#xD;
      infections, including vaginal yeast infections, jock itch and athlete's foot. In much higher&#xD;
      doses, it is used to treat fungal infections that have spread to the lungs, brain, kidneys,&#xD;
      or bladder. LNMMA inhibits production of nitric oxide, another substance produced by the&#xD;
      lining cells of blood vessels.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Blood flow will be measured throughout the study, which will last approximately 3 hours.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The vascular endothelium synthesizes at least three potent vasodilator substances: nitric&#xD;
      oxide (NO), prostacyclin and an endothelium-derived hyperpolarizing factor (EDHF). EDHF&#xD;
      release is stimulated by receptor-dependent agonists such as acetylcholine and bradykinin&#xD;
      (BK), and leads to hyperpolarization of the underlying smooth muscle cells presumably by&#xD;
      opening Ca(2+)-activated K(+) channels. Indirect pharmacologic evidence suggests that EDHF is&#xD;
      a cytochrome P450-derived arachidonic acid metabolite, presumably an epoxide.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Numerous inhibitors of EDHF have been defined in animal tissues. Of these, miconazole has&#xD;
      proven to be safe when administered to humans as a topical and parenteral antifungal agent.&#xD;
      At levels that are attained with routine clinical use, it has a rapid onset of action with&#xD;
      high specificity of inhibition of EDHF in animal models. This study is designed to&#xD;
      investigate the safety and efficacy of intra-arterial miconazole in inhibiting BK-mediated&#xD;
      forearm vasodilation in normal volunteers.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 2001</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>15</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Miconazole, L-NMMA, Bradykinin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Healthy male or female volunteers (age 21-60 years).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No presence of intercurrent illness.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No current smoking (within previous 5 years).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No hypertension (greater than 140/90).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No diabetes.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No hypercholesterolemia (total cholesterol greater than 240 mg/dl).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No pregnancy or menopause.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No renal failure (creatinine greater than 1.4 mg/dl).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No allergies to miconazole, parabens, castor oil or aspirin.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No bleeding disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No consumption of any medications during the last one week, including vitamins and&#xD;
        unconventional medications.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feletou M, Vanhoutte PM. Endothelium-derived hyperpolarizing factor. Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol. 1996 Dec;23(12):1082-90. doi: 10.1111/j.1440-1681.1996.tb01174.x.</citation>
    <PMID>8977164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Furchgott RF, Vanhoutte PM. Endothelium-derived relaxing and contracting factors. FASEB J. 1989 Jul;3(9):2007-18.</citation>
    <PMID>2545495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keef KD, Bowen SM. Effect of ACh on electrical and mechanical activity in guinea pig coronary arteries. Am J Physiol. 1989 Oct;257(4 Pt 2):H1096-103. doi: 10.1152/ajpheart.1989.257.4.H1096.</citation>
    <PMID>2801972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2001</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Endothelium</keyword>
  <keyword>Vasodilation</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular Biology</keyword>
  <keyword>Venous Occlusion Plethysmography</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Miconazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bradykinin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kininogens</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

