<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005215</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1094</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL038763</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005215</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lipoprotein Subfractions and Coronary Heart Disease During 25 Year Follow-up</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the relationship of fatal and nonfatal coronary heart disease to lipoprotein&#xD;
      fractions and other risk factors in a prospective epidemiologic study conducted between 1954&#xD;
      and 1957.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Prospective epidemiologic studies of cholesterol, blood pressure, and cigarette use have&#xD;
      provided much of the evidence linking these established risk factors to coronary heart&#xD;
      disease, for example the Framingham Study, the Western Electric Study, and the Chicago&#xD;
      Peoples Gas Company Study. Concurrent to these well known studies, was an effort by Dr. John&#xD;
      Gofman to measure lipoprotein subfraction concentrations in 2,880 male and female employees&#xD;
      of the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, and to establish prospectively the&#xD;
      associations of HDL2, HDL3, LDL, IDL, smaller VLDL and larger VLDL to coronary heart disease.&#xD;
      After 10 years of follow-up, Dr. Gofman presented his findings at the Lyman Duff Memorial&#xD;
      Lecture on October 13, 1965. The findings were subsequently published in Circulation in 1966.&#xD;
      He reported an increased risk of coronary heart disease in association with high serum mass&#xD;
      concentrations of LDL, IDL, and smaller VLDL and low concentrations of HDL2 and HDL3. This&#xD;
      pioneering effort by Dr. Gofman preceded the recognition of the importance of lipoprotein&#xD;
      subfractions by nearly a decade, so that more detailed statistical analyses and further&#xD;
      follow-up of the cohort were deferred indefinitely. Most importantly, in 1952 Gofman used&#xD;
      essentially the same methodology to measure lipoprotein subfractions that was in practice in&#xD;
      1988 at the Donner Laboratory for numerous in-house and collaborative studies including the&#xD;
      study of atherosclerotic progression in the Stanford Coronary Risk Intervention Project, the&#xD;
      effects of exercise and weight loss on lipoproteins in the Stanford Exercise Training Study&#xD;
      and Weight Control Projects, and metabolism and genetic transmission as part of the Donner&#xD;
      Laboratory NIH program project entitled Lipoprotein Subclasses: Structure, Origin and&#xD;
      Metabolism.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Serum lipoprotein subfraction concentrations were measured in 1,961 men and 423 women who&#xD;
      were employed or who applied for employment at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory between&#xD;
      1954 and 1957. Computer files were created by Dr. Gofman at Donner Laboratory for&#xD;
      epidemiologic studies of lipoprotein fractions. The files included name, age, gender and the&#xD;
      following medical information: cholesterol, lipoprotein subfraction concentrations, blood&#xD;
      pressure, weight, smoking history, hemoglobin, red and white blood cell counts, and blood&#xD;
      proteins. Dr. Gofman provided those computer files for this study. The vital status and the&#xD;
      history of coronary disease in the cohort were determined through state and national&#xD;
      mortality surveillance systems, public records, medical and hospital records, autopsy&#xD;
      reports, and telephone interviews with cohort members. All medical documents were examined by&#xD;
      a physician and endpoints assigned according to international diagnostic criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The data were used to extend Dr. Gofman's initial study from 10 to 30 years of follow-up.&#xD;
      Survival analysis was used to assess the independent contributions of specific lipoprotein&#xD;
      subclasses to coronary disease while controlling for other risk factors. Other issues&#xD;
      examined were whether HDL2 and HDL3 showed different relationships to coronary disease,&#xD;
      whether the relationships of lipoprotein subfractions to coronary disease were independent of&#xD;
      other established risk factors, and whether measurements of lipoprotein subfraction&#xD;
      concentrations offered significant improvement over total cholesterol in predicting coronary&#xD;
      disease risk.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in&#xD;
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 1988</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 1992</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>May 2000</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 29, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

