<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000697</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG 092</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11067</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000697</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Foscarnet in the Treatment of Cytomegalovirus (CMV) of the Eyes in Patients With AIDS Who Cannot Use Ganciclovir</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Randomized Controlled Trial of Immediate Versus Delayed Foscarnet Therapy in AIDS Patients With Non-Immediately Sight-Threatening CMV Retinitis Who Cannot Be Treated With Ganciclovir Due to Myelosuppression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To study the safety and effectiveness of foscarnet in the treatment of AIDS patients who have&#xD;
      active infection with cytomegalovirus (CMV) that is causing inflammation of the retina&#xD;
      (retinitis). In addition, these patients cannot be treated with ganciclovir (DHPG) because of&#xD;
      its toxic effect on the body's blood-forming cells or because white blood cell or platelet&#xD;
      counts were too low.&#xD;
&#xD;
      CMV is a common virus, which can cause blindness and death in AIDS patients. Previous studies&#xD;
      demonstrate that foscarnet has been effective in both AIDS and non-AIDS patients with CMV&#xD;
      infection. Although treatment with ganciclovir (DHPG) is also effective, a significant&#xD;
      toxicity leading to dose-limiting neutropenia (low white blood cell count) in one third of&#xD;
      treated patients has been associated with the drug. Based on the serious nature of CMV&#xD;
      retinitis and the lack of alternative drug therapies for DHPG-sensitive patients, the present&#xD;
      study will evaluate the safety and efficacy of intravenous (IV) foscarnet in AIDS patients&#xD;
      with CMV retinitis.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CMV is a common virus, which can cause blindness and death in AIDS patients. Previous studies&#xD;
      demonstrate that foscarnet has been effective in both AIDS and non-AIDS patients with CMV&#xD;
      infection. Although treatment with ganciclovir (DHPG) is also effective, a significant&#xD;
      toxicity leading to dose-limiting neutropenia (low white blood cell count) in one third of&#xD;
      treated patients has been associated with the drug. Based on the serious nature of CMV&#xD;
      retinitis and the lack of alternative drug therapies for DHPG-sensitive patients, the present&#xD;
      study will evaluate the safety and efficacy of intravenous (IV) foscarnet in AIDS patients&#xD;
      with CMV retinitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Following routine evaluation studies, patients are randomized to receive foscarnet right away&#xD;
      or to delay treatment, as their retinitis has been determined not to be immediately&#xD;
      sight-threatening. Patients are hospitalized for the first 3 days and may remain hospitalized&#xD;
      for as many as 14 days. Foscarnet is given by vein (IV) in what is called induction therapy,&#xD;
      and if the patient's retinitis stabilizes after 2 weeks of treatment, treatment with&#xD;
      foscarnet is continued in maintenance therapy for another 8 weeks. During maintenance&#xD;
      therapy, patients receive salt solution IV to help prevent any toxic side effect of foscarnet&#xD;
      on the kidneys. Patients have regular checkups to monitor their retinitis as well as their&#xD;
      general health. Patients taking zidovudine (AZT) prior to entering the study may continue&#xD;
      their treatment if they are selected for the delayed treatment group; if they are selected&#xD;
      for the immediate treatment group, they begin or resume AZT therapy when they enter the 2nd&#xD;
      week of maintenance therapy. Patients are followed as outpatients for at least 10 weeks, with&#xD;
      clinic check-ups and lab tests once every week; eye exams are done once a week for the first&#xD;
      2 weeks and then every other week. If clinically indicated, a continued maintenance regimen&#xD;
      may be administered after the 10th week; the total duration of therapy plus maintenance is&#xD;
      not to exceed 24 weeks. Note: Patients scheduled for the delayed foscarnet treatment are&#xD;
      immediately given foscarnet at the first sign that their retinitis is getting worse.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Cytomegalovirus Retinitis</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Foscarnet sodium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed if hematologically stable on that regimen for at least 30 days prior to study&#xD;
        entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Oral antibiotics.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chemotherapy for Kaposi's sarcoma.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acyclovir for outbreaks of herpes simplex or shingles.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Zidovudine (AZT), either initiated or continued, by patients randomized to both&#xD;
             treatment arms. AZT given concurrently with foscarnet may be administered at a dose of&#xD;
             100 or 200 mg every 4 hours (q4h) at the investigator's discretion. Patients&#xD;
             randomized to the delayed treatment arm may initiate or continue AZT administration at&#xD;
             a dose of 100 or 200 mg q4h at the investigator's discretion. AZT may not be&#xD;
             administered during the first 3 weeks of foscarnet therapy. Patients randomized to&#xD;
             immediate therapy may begin or resume AZT when they enter the 2nd week of maintenance&#xD;
             therapy (week 4 of the 10-week study period), if their hemoglobin is = or &gt; 8 g/dl and&#xD;
             absolute neutrophil count is = or &gt; 1000 cells/mm3 at that time. Caution should be&#xD;
             used in the concurrent use of foscarnet and ciprofloxacin, as such use has appeared to&#xD;
             exacerbate renal failure in one patient.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must have active AIDS-related cytomegalovirus (CMV) retinitis as identified by its&#xD;
        characteristic ophthalmoscopic appearance and verified by fundus photography. Patients must&#xD;
        also demonstrate one of the following clinical and/or laboratory findings:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Treatment with ganciclovir (DHPG) resulting in dose-limiting toxicity (absolute&#xD;
             neutrophil count (= polymorphonuclear leukocytes plus bands) &lt; 500 cells/mm3 or&#xD;
             platelets &lt; 25000 platelets/mm3) occurring on = or &gt; two documented occasions at least&#xD;
             7 days apart while receiving up to a maximum induction regimen of 10 mg/kg/day or a&#xD;
             maintenance regimen of up to 5 mg/kg/day. Neutropenia should not be the result of&#xD;
             zidovudine (AZT) treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ineligibility for DHPG therapy because of baseline neutropenia (absolute neutrophil&#xD;
             count &lt; 500 cells/mm3) or thrombocytopenia (platelets &lt; 25000 platelets/mm3)&#xD;
             documented on = or &gt; 2 occasions at least 7 days apart. Baseline myelosuppression&#xD;
             should not be the result of ongoing therapy with either prescription drugs, including&#xD;
             AZT, or over-the-counter medications.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Zidovudine (AZT), according to protocol stipulations.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Prophylaxis therapy for Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia (PCP).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chemotherapy for Kaposi's sarcoma.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Co-existing Condition:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with any of the following diseases or symptoms are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  An immediately sight-threatening lesion in a salvageable eye (i.e., patients who have&#xD;
             a cytomegalovirus (CMV) lesion that is within 1500 microns of the optic disc or fovea&#xD;
             in an eye with correction vision of 20/100 or better).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Corneal, lens or vitreous opacification which precludes examination of the fundi of&#xD;
             either eye.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any clinically significant pulmonary or neurologic impairment (i.e., patients who are&#xD;
             intubated or comatose), although patients with a history of a seizure disorder or a&#xD;
             central nervous system (CNS) mass lesion may be enrolled.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Systemic acyclovir as preventive therapy for herpes infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any nephrotoxic agent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Specifically excluded are aminoglycosides, amphotericin B, and parenteral pentamidine.&#xD;
             A patient who requires such therapy must be temporarily discontinued from study&#xD;
             therapy; if nephrotoxic therapy is given for &gt; 7 days, the patient will be permanently&#xD;
             withdrawn from study therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other anti-cytomegalovirus (CMV) therapy, specifically ganciclovir, CMV hyperimmune&#xD;
             serum/globulin, interferons, and immunomodulators.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients will be excluded from the study if they are unwilling or unable to suspend&#xD;
        zidovudine (AZT) treatment during the first 3 weeks of the study period (1) if randomized&#xD;
        to the immediate treatment arm, or (2) when crossed-over from the delayed treatment arm to&#xD;
        foscarnet therapy because of retinitis progression.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Foscarnet for cytomegalovirus (CMV) retinitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Excluded within 7 days of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Immunomodulators.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Investigational agents other than ganciclovir.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MA Jacobson</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>CS Crumpacker</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polis MA. Foscarnet and ganciclovir in the treatment of cytomegalovirus retinitis. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr (1988). 1992;5 Suppl 1:S3-10.</citation>
    <PMID>1318365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2021</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 27, 2021</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 27, 2021</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 4, 2021</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Retinitis</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS-Related Opportunistic Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Marrow</keyword>
  <keyword>Ganciclovir</keyword>
  <keyword>Foscarnet</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytomegalovirus Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiviral Agents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytomegalovirus Retinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Foscarnet</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Phosphonoacetic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

