<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001754</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>980119</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>98-HG-0119</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001754</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Skeletal Disorders and Short Stature</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical and Molecular Manifestations of Human Skeletal Dysplasias and Short Stature</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will determine the genes responsible for skeletal dysplasias (disorders of the&#xD;
      skeleton) and short stature and define the range and type of medical problems they cause over&#xD;
      time. It will investigate whether specific gene changes cause specific medical problems in&#xD;
      these disorders and identify the signs and symptoms upon which their diagnoses must be based.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Individuals with short stature or with a skeletal dysplasia known or suspected to be caused&#xD;
      by a gene mutation (change) may be eligible for this study. Family members may also&#xD;
      participate. Skeletal dysplasias under study include: achondroplasia, hypochondroplasia,&#xD;
      achondrogenesis type II, hypochondrogenesis, Kniest dysplasia, spondyloepiphyseal dysplasias,&#xD;
      Stickler syndrome; Shmid and Jansen metaphyseal dysplasias; pyknodysotosis, proximal&#xD;
      symphalangism, brachydactyly types B C and E, Ellis van Creveld and related disorders,&#xD;
      metatrophic chondrodysplasias, cartilage-hair hypoplasia and disorders with a skeletal&#xD;
      abnormality that have not yet been defined but might be the result of a genetic defect.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will talk with two genetics specialists who will explain the study and its possible&#xD;
      implications for the patient and family and answer questions. The patient's medical records&#xD;
      will be reviewed, a personal and family history will be taken, and a physical examination&#xD;
      will be done. Various other procedures that may be done include drawing up to 6 tablespoons&#xD;
      of blood, some of which will be used for DNA (genetic) studies, X-rays, echocardiography&#xD;
      (ultrasound of the heart), magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), eye examination, hearing test,&#xD;
      sleep study, sperm analysis and skin biopsy (surgical removal of a small piece of skin done&#xD;
      under local anesthetic). There may be additional evaluations by specialists in rheumatology,&#xD;
      rehabilitation medicine and orthopedics. When the tests and examinations are completed (after&#xD;
      2 to 3 days), a doctor will discuss the results with the patient. Patients whose DNA studies&#xD;
      show that a gene change is responsible for their disorder will meet with a genetics nurse or&#xD;
      counselor to review the results, express their feelings and ask any questions they may have.&#xD;
      Patients may be asked to return to NIH every 6 months to 2 years for continued follow-up.&#xD;
      Medical management will be provided primarily by the patient's own physician.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participating family members will be interviewed by telephone about their personal and family&#xD;
      health history and will have a blood sample drawn for DNA testing. If a gene change is found&#xD;
      that is responsible for the bone disorder or growth problem in the family, arrangements will&#xD;
      be made for the family member to discuss the implications of the findings with a genetics&#xD;
      specialist.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We will investigate the clinical manifestations and molecular genetic defects of human&#xD;
      skeletal dysplasias and generalized short stature. Families with skeletal dysplasias or short&#xD;
      stature of known or suspected genetic basis will be enrolled. Affected individuals or&#xD;
      individuals suspected of having a skeletal dysplasia will undergo periodic clinical&#xD;
      assessment and genetic analyses for the purpose of: 1) definition and characterization of&#xD;
      phenotype, 2) determination of the natural history of the disorder, and 3) genotype/phenotype&#xD;
      correlation. Genetic linkage studies may be performed for disorders in which the genetic&#xD;
      bases is not yet known.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date>May 2001</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>600</enrollment>
  <condition>Developmental Bone Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dwarfism</condition>
  <condition>Skeletal Dysplasias</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients with known or suspected skeletal dysplasias or short stature and their family&#xD;
        members of any age will be recruited worldwide from diverse medical communities including&#xD;
        genetics, orthopedics, ophthalmology, and pediatrics.&#xD;
&#xD;
        DISEASE CATEGORY I:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Individuals and family members with a suspected or an established diagnosis of any FGFR3&#xD;
        disorder, type II collagen disorder, Schmid metaphyseal dysplasia, pyknodysostosis,&#xD;
        proximal symphalangism, or brachydactyly type C.&#xD;
&#xD;
        DISEASE CATEGORY II:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Individuals and family members with a suspected or an established diagnosis of a skeletal&#xD;
        dysplasia in which the disease gene is not yet known, including: Ellis van Crevald,&#xD;
        brachydactyly types B and E, and cartilage-hair hypoplasia.&#xD;
&#xD;
        DISEASE CATEGORY III:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Individuals and family members who have previously uncharacterized systemic manifestations&#xD;
        suggestive of a skeletal dysplasias, with clinical findings of: disproportionate or&#xD;
        proportionate short stature; and/or cleft palate; and/or detached retina; and/or history of&#xD;
        loose joints or frequent joint dislocation; and/or history of, or family history of,&#xD;
        premature arthritis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Short Stature Category I: Individuals with generalized short stature and their family&#xD;
        members. This includes adults with abnormal stature as statistically defined from&#xD;
        standardized growth charts.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must be able to give informed consent, older children (greater than or equal to 7 years&#xD;
        old) who do not give assent, or persons who are wards of the state will be excluded from&#xD;
        the study.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bellus GA, Hefferon TW, Ortiz de Luna RI, Hecht JT, Horton WA, Machado M, Kaitila I, McIntosh I, Francomano CA. Achondroplasia is defined by recurrent G380R mutations of FGFR3. Am J Hum Genet. 1995 Feb;56(2):368-73.</citation>
    <PMID>7847369</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bellus GA, McIntosh I, Smith EA, Aylsworth AS, Kaitila I, Horton WA, Greenhaw GA, Hecht JT, Francomano CA. A recurrent mutation in the tyrosine kinase domain of fibroblast growth factor receptor 3 causes hypochondroplasia. Nat Genet. 1995 Jul;10(3):357-9. doi: 10.1038/ng0795-357.</citation>
    <PMID>7670477</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bogaert R, Tiller GE, Weis MA, Gruber HE, Rimoin DL, Cohn DH, Eyre DR. An amino acid substitution (Gly853--&gt;Glu) in the collagen alpha 1(II) chain produces hypochondrogenesis. J Biol Chem. 1992 Nov 5;267(31):22522-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1429602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2000</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Dwarfism</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene Mapping</keyword>
  <keyword>Linkage</keyword>
  <keyword>Mutation Analysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Skeletal Biology</keyword>
  <keyword>Brachydactyly Types C &amp; E</keyword>
  <keyword>Cartilage-Hair Hypoplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Ellis Van Crevald</keyword>
  <keyword>FgFR-3</keyword>
  <keyword>Proximal Symphalangism</keyword>
  <keyword>Pyknodysotosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Schmid Metaphyseal</keyword>
  <keyword>Short Stature</keyword>
  <keyword>Skeletal Dysplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Type II Collagen Disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dwarfism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteochondrodysplasias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases, Developmental</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

