<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001261</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>900139</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>90-N-0139</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001261</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intravenousimmunoglobulin (IVIg) for the Treatment of Inflammatory Myopathies</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Efficacy of High-Dose Intravenous Immunoglobulin in Patients With Inflammatory Myopathies: A Three Month Randomized Trial With Option for Cross-Over</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Inflammatory myopathies are a group of muscle diseases characterized by muscle weakness, high&#xD;
      levels of muscle enzymes in the blood, and inflammation of the tissue surrounding muscle&#xD;
      fibers (endomysium).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The diseases making up the inflammatory myopathies are grouped into three subsets:&#xD;
&#xD;
      I) Polymyositis (PM)&#xD;
&#xD;
      II) Dermatomyositis (DM)&#xD;
&#xD;
      III) Inclusion Body Myositis (IBM)&#xD;
&#xD;
      Inflammatory myopathies are thought to be autoimmune processes and are treated with steroids&#xD;
      and immunosuppressive drugs. However, many patients who initially respond to these treatments&#xD;
      develop resistance to the therapy or experience side effects causing the treatments to be&#xD;
      stopped.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Researchers believe that intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIg) may provide patients with PM, DM,&#xD;
      and IBM a safer and more effective alternative to standard therapies for the diseases. IVIg&#xD;
      is a drug that has been used successfully to treat other immune-related diseases of the&#xD;
      nervous system.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study will take 60 patients and divide them into two groups. Group one will receive 2&#xD;
      injections of IVIg once a month for three months. Group two will receive 2 injections of&#xD;
      placebo &quot;inactive injection of sterile water&quot; once a month for three months. Following the&#xD;
      three months of treatment, group one will begin taking the placebo and group two will begin&#xD;
      taking IVIg for an additional 3 months. The drug will be considered effective if patients&#xD;
      receiving it experience a significant improvement (&gt;15%) in muscle strength.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The inflammatory myopathies are a group of acquired muscle diseases characterized by subacute&#xD;
      onset of progressive proximal muscle weakness, elevated serum muscle enzymes and endomysial&#xD;
      inflammation. They comprise 3 clinically distinct subsets: polymyositis (PM), dermatomyositis&#xD;
      (DM) and Inclusion Body Myositis (IBM). Because immune-mediated mechanisms are primarily&#xD;
      responsible for the clinical manifestations of these conditions, the treatment of choice is&#xD;
      with corticosteroids or immunotherapy drugs. Although most of the patients initially respond&#xD;
      to these drugs, a number of them become resistant or develop unacceptable side effects that&#xD;
      necessitate their discontinuation. The need for a more effective and safe immunotherapy in&#xD;
      patients with PM, DM or IBM prompted the present study using high dose intravenous&#xD;
      immunoglobulin (IVIg). IVIg is an immunomodulating agent which has been shown to be effective&#xD;
      and safe in the treatment of a number of patients with immune-related neuromuscular diseases.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This is a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled study involving 30 patients, who will&#xD;
      receive IVIg or placebo for 3 months and then will cross-over to the alternate therapy for&#xD;
      another period of 3 monthly infusions. The monthly dose of IVIg is 2 GM/Kg divided into two&#xD;
      daily doses. The drug will be considered effective if patients experience an increase of more&#xD;
      than 15% in their baseline muscle strength. Muscle strength will be assessed with a series of&#xD;
      objective dynamometric measurements performed before and at the end of each monthly infusion.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 1990</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>120</enrollment>
  <condition>Dermatomyositis</condition>
  <condition>Inclusion Body Myositis</condition>
  <condition>Polymyositis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gamma Globulin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Selected patients should have PM, IBM or DM.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Specifically they should have a) proximal muscle weakness; b) no evidence of clinical,&#xD;
        histological or family history of another neuromuscular illness; c) elevation of muscle&#xD;
        enzymes during the course of the disease; d) typical skin rash in case of DM; and e)&#xD;
        diagnostic muscle biopsy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Suitable candidates for IVIg should be patients with active, bonefide disease who:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. have been treated with steroids but had: a) no response or incomplete response (as&#xD;
             defined by continued muscle weakness) to high-dose therapy or b) a good response to&#xD;
             steroids but inability to taper the dose without a flare of disease activity or c)&#xD;
             unacceptable steroid side effects such as gastrointestinal hemorrhages, osteonecrosis,&#xD;
             hyperglycemia, extreme weight gain etc., and&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. have been treated with one immunosuppressive drug (such as azathioprine, Methotrexate,&#xD;
             Cyclophosphamide, Cyclosporine) but without benefit or with unacceptable side effects.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnant or nursing women (confirmed by a screening pregnancy test).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Critically ill patients such as those requiring intravenous pressors for maintenance of&#xD;
        cardiac output due to severe cardiomyopathy, patients with respiratory insufficiency and&#xD;
        patients with severe muscle weakness requiring help for basic self care.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Children below age 18.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with severe renal or hepatic disease, severe COPD or coronary artery disease or&#xD;
        other systemic medical problems often seen when PM or DM is associated with severe cases of&#xD;
        lupus, rheumatoid arthritis or scleroderma.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with known allergic reaction to IVIg.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Serum IgA less than 11mg/dl.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dalakas MC. Polymyositis, dermatomyositis and inclusion-body myositis. N Engl J Med. 1991 Nov 21;325(21):1487-98. doi: 10.1056/NEJM199111213252107. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>1658649</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dalakas M. Treatment of polymyositis and dermatomyositis. Curr Opin Rheumatol. 1989 Dec;1(4):443-9. doi: 10.1097/00002281-198901040-00005. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>2702045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roifman CM, Schaffer FM, Wachsmuth SE, Murphy G, Gelfand EW. Reversal of chronic polymyositis following intravenous immune serum globulin therapy. JAMA. 1987 Jul 24-31;258(4):513-5. doi: 10.1001/jama.1987.03400040111034. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>3599350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2002</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Polymyositis/Dermatomyositis</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle Immunopathology</keyword>
  <keyword>Intravenous High-Dose Immunoglobulin</keyword>
  <keyword>Inclusion Body Myositis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatomyositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polymyositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myositis, Inclusion Body</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>gamma-Globulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins, Intravenous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rho(D) Immune Globulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

