<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001399</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>940033</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>94-H-0033</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001399</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gene Therapy for the Treatment of Fanconi's Anemia Type C</brief_title>
  <official_title>Retroviral Mediated Gene Transfer of the Fanconi Anemia Complementation Group C Gene to Hematopoietic Progenitors of Group C Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fanconi's Anemia is an inherited disorder that can produce bone marrow failure. In addition,&#xD;
      some patients with Fanconi's anemia have physical defects usually involving the skeleton and&#xD;
      kidneys. The major problem for most patients is aplastic anemia, the blood counts for red&#xD;
      blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets are low because the bone marrow fails to&#xD;
      produce these cells. Some patients with Fanconi's anemia can develop leukemia or cancers of&#xD;
      other organs.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Many laboratory studies have suggested that Fanconi's anemia is caused by an inherited defect&#xD;
      in the ability of cells to repair DNA. Recently, the gene for one of the four types of&#xD;
      Fanconi's anemia, type C, has been identified. It is known that this gene is defective in&#xD;
      patients with Fanconi's anemia type C.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Researchers have conducted laboratory studies that suggest Fanconi's anemia type C may be&#xD;
      treatable with gene therapy. Gene therapy works by placing a normal gene into the cells of&#xD;
      patients with abnormal genes responsible for Fanconi's anemia type C. After the normal gene&#xD;
      is in place, new normal cells can develop and grow. Drugs can be given to these patients kill&#xD;
      the remaining abnormal cells. The new cells containing normal genes and will not be harmed by&#xD;
      these drugs.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The purpose of this study is to test whether researchers can safely place the normal&#xD;
      Fanconi's anemia type C gene into cells of patients with the disease. The gene will be placed&#xD;
      into special cells in the bone marrow called stem cells. These stem cells are responsible for&#xD;
      producing new red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fanconi anemia (FA) is a rare genetic disorder characterized by progressive pancytopenia,&#xD;
      congenital abnormalities, and predisposition to malignancy. Therapy is currently limited to&#xD;
      allogeneic marrow transplantation; patients lacking a suitable donor usually die from aplasia&#xD;
      or acute leukemia. Recently, mutation in a novel gene named FACC (Fanconi anemia&#xD;
      C-complementing) has been identified as causing one type of FA. FACC mutations, which&#xD;
      introduce splicing errors or stop codons, have been identified in 15% of FA patients. We have&#xD;
      recently been successful in functional complementation of four FA cell lines using retroviral&#xD;
      vectors to transfer a copy of the normal FACC gene. We also analyzed the ability of four&#xD;
      viral vectors to functionally correct hematopoietic progenitor cells from a patient bearing a&#xD;
      splice donor mutation. As for the lymphoid cell lines, these CD34 enriched cells were&#xD;
      extremely sensitive to MMC. After injection of these progenitor cells with viral vectors&#xD;
      bearing normal FACC, the progenitors gave rise to increased numbers of colonies both in the&#xD;
      absence and presence of up to 5 nM MMC, whereas control cells were completely destroyed by 1&#xD;
      nM MMC. In summary, we have demonstrated that: (1) retroviral vectors can be engineered to&#xD;
      transfer a normal FACC gene to FA(C) lymphoid cell lines and primary hematopoietic cells; (2)&#xD;
      introduction of a normal FACC gene into CD34+ progenitors markedly enhances their growth in&#xD;
      the absence and presence of MMC.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study is designed to determine whether hematopoietic progenitors transduced with the&#xD;
      normal FACC gene can be re-infused safely into FA(C) patients. CD34+ cells obtained from&#xD;
      G-CSF mobilized peripheral blood will be transduced ex vivo over a 72 hour period in the&#xD;
      presence of IL-3, IL-6, and stem cell factor with the FACC retroviral vector. These&#xD;
      transduced cells will be re-infused into FA(C) patients. Patients will be monitored for&#xD;
      toxicities as well as evidence of successful gene transfer and expression. The procedure will&#xD;
      be repeated up to a total of 4 times with each treatment 2-4 months apart. Theoretically,&#xD;
      these rescued stem cells should have a selective growth advantage within the hypoplastic FA&#xD;
      marrow environment in vivo.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 3, 1993</start_date>
  <completion_date>February 11, 2009</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>9</enrollment>
  <condition>Fanconi's Anemia</condition>
  <condition>Pancytopenia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transduced CD34+ Cells</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must meet the following criteria within 30 days prior to study entry (Day 0)&#xD;
        unless otherwise noted.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Males or females, age greater than or equal to 5 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Diagnosis of Fanconi anemia, complementation group C, as confirmed by 1) Diepoxybutane or&#xD;
        mitomycin C testing and 2) DNA analysis indicating FACC mutations.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Adequate baseline organ function as assessed by the following laboratory values within 30&#xD;
        days prior to study entry (day -30 to 0).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Adequate renal function with estimated creatinine clearance greater than 50 ml/min. (This&#xD;
        will be determined by serum creatinine and 24-hour urine creatinine ordered concurrently).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Adequate liver function with SGOT, SGPT and alkaline phosphatase less than or equal to 5&#xD;
        times the ULN (if transaminases greater than the upper limit of normal (ULN), patients&#xD;
        should have a hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAG) test prior to study entry. Patients may&#xD;
        not enter the study if HBsAG is positive).&#xD;
&#xD;
        PT and PTT not more than 1.5 times the ULN.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Serum Amylase less than or equal to 1.5 times the ULN.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Bilirubin less than or equal to 3.0 mg/dL.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Triglyceride less than 400 mg/dl.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Ability to give informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Normal cardiac function by history and exam.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Resting transcutaneous oxygen saturation greater than 90 percent on room air.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Karnofsky Performance Status greater than or equal to 40.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Although there are no blood count criteria for inclusion in this study, preference will be&#xD;
        given to patients with significant marrow failure as reflected by anemia, neutropenia,&#xD;
        and/or thrombocytopenia. Furthermore, we intend to first enroll adults and older children,&#xD;
        to the extent possible, before enrolling younger children.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who meet any one of the following criteria will be excluded from study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients presenting with acute leukemia or bone marrow aspirate revealing greater than 10&#xD;
        percent blasts.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnant or lactating females (all patients must practice adequate birth control and&#xD;
        females of child-bearing potential must have a negative serum beta-HCG pregnancy test&#xD;
        (within Day -7 to Day 0).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Acute infection: any acute viral, bacterial, or fungal infection which requires specific&#xD;
        therapy. Acute therapy must have been completed within 14 days prior to study treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Hepatitis-B surface antigen positive patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        HIV-infected patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Acute medical problems such as ischemic heart or lung disease that may be considered an&#xD;
        unacceptable anesthetic or operative risk.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with any underlying conditions which would contraindicate therapy with study&#xD;
        treatment (or allergies to reagents used in this study).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients less than 25 kg in weight .&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who elect bone marrow transplantation.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whitney MA, Saito H, Jakobs PM, Gibson RA, Moses RE, Grompe M. A common mutation in the FACC gene causes Fanconi anaemia in Ashkenazi Jews. Nat Genet. 1993 Jun;4(2):202-5. doi: 10.1038/ng0693-202.</citation>
    <PMID>8348157</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strathdee CA, Gavish H, Shannon WR, Buchwald M. Cloning of cDNAs for Fanconi's anaemia by functional complementation. Nature. 1992 Apr 30;356(6372):763-7. doi: 10.1038/356763a0. Erratum In: Nature. 1992 Jul 30;358(6385):434.</citation>
    <PMID>1574115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strathdee CA, Duncan AM, Buchwald M. Evidence for at least four Fanconi anaemia genes including FACC on chromosome 9. Nat Genet. 1992 Jun;1(3):196-8. doi: 10.1038/ng0692-196.</citation>
    <PMID>1303234</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 11, 2009</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Gene Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem Cell Rescue</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Marrow Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Fanconi Anemia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fanconi Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fanconi Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancytopenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

