<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001306</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>920223</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>92-CH-0223</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001306</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Steroid Therapy in Autoimmune Premature Ovarian Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Autoimmune Premature Ovarian Failure: A Controlled Trial of Alternate-Day Prednisone Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      No therapy for infertile patients with premature ovarian failure has been proven effective.&#xD;
      Some anecdotal reports have suggested that high dose, long term prednisone (steroid) therapy&#xD;
      may be useful in treating autoimmune ovarian failure. However, prednisone, when used in&#xD;
      high-doses for long periods of time has substantial side effects, including aseptic necrosis&#xD;
      of bone where portions of bone die without the presence of infection and are surrounded by&#xD;
      healthy tissue. Aseptic necrosis of bone often requires major surgical treatment. Even with&#xD;
      this known level of risk, patients with premature ovarian failure are being treated based on&#xD;
      this anecdotal evidence.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will test the hypothesis that a lower risk therapy (alternate-day, lower dose,&#xD;
      shorter-term prednisone) will cause a remission of autoimmune ovarian failure. There is no&#xD;
      reliable blood test to identify patients who have premature ovarian failure. Therefore, all&#xD;
      patients must undergo a laparoscopic ovarian biopsy to confirm the presence of an auto immune&#xD;
      reaction in the ovaries (autoimmune oophoritis). Laparoscopy is a surgical procedure that&#xD;
      allows doctors to explore the abdomen using a camera-like device called a laparoscope. The&#xD;
      procedure has been used clinically by some reproductive endocrinologists to identify patients&#xD;
      with premature ovarian failure who have an autoimmune mechanism for the disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The treatment will be deemed successful based on the return of ovulation as determined by&#xD;
      weekly serum progesterone levels.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Autoimmune oophoritis is a distinct clinical entity and a known cause of premature ovarian&#xD;
      failure. It is characterized by the presence of circulating adrenal antibodies. No therapy&#xD;
      for infertile patients with premature ovarian failure due to autoimmune oophoritis has been&#xD;
      proven effective by prospective controlled study. Anecdotal reports have suggested that&#xD;
      high-dose, long-term prednisone therapy may be useful in treating autoimmune ovarian failure.&#xD;
      However, prednisone, when used in high-dose for a long-term has substantial side effects,&#xD;
      including aseptic necrosis of bone requiring major surgical intervention. Despite this risk,&#xD;
      patients with premature ovarian failure are being treated based on this anecdotal evidence.&#xD;
      We are aware of two patients with premature ovarian failure who developed aseptic necrosis of&#xD;
      bone on high-dose, long-term prednisone therapy administered elsewhere.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This protocol will test the hypothesis that a lower risk therapy (alternate-day, lower dose,&#xD;
      shorter-term prednisone) will induce remission of ovarian failure caused by autoimmune&#xD;
      oophoritis. The protocol will use a double-masked, placebo-controlled design. Patients with&#xD;
      premature ovarian failure who have serologic evidence of steroidogenic cell autoimmunity will&#xD;
      be candidates. Successful outcome will be defined as a return of ovulation as determined by&#xD;
      weekly serum progesterone levels. The hypothesis that short-term, alternate-day prednisone&#xD;
      therapy restores ovulation will be tested with an equality of proportions test comparing the&#xD;
      proportion of patients who ovulate during placebo with the proportion of patients who ovulate&#xD;
      during prednisone therapy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 10, 1992</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 12, 2011</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Actual">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Autoimmune Disease</condition>
  <condition>Infertility</condition>
  <condition>Premature Ovarian Failure</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION/EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Women 18 to 39 years of age with premature ovarian failure who meet the following&#xD;
        requirements will be candidates for the study:&#xD;
&#xD;
        At least a four month history of amenorrhea not due to pregnancy,&#xD;
&#xD;
        Clearly elevated gonadotropins with a serum FSH greater than or equal to 40 IU/L on two&#xD;
        separate occasions at least one month apart,&#xD;
&#xD;
        Positive adrenal or ovarian antibodies demonstrated by indirect immuno-fluorescence using&#xD;
        monkey tissue as substrate or other laboratory evidence of steroidogenic cell autoimmunity&#xD;
        such as the presence of antibodies against 21-hydroxylase,&#xD;
&#xD;
        No evidence for genetic, metabolic, toxic, or iatrogenic cause of the ovarian failure,&#xD;
&#xD;
        No medical contraindication to glycocorticoid therapy,&#xD;
&#xD;
        No glycocorticoid therapy taken in the past year (patients on appropriate replacement&#xD;
        therapy for Addison's disease are not excluded),&#xD;
&#xD;
        No medical contraindication to pregnancy.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>39 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maity R, Caspi RR, Nair S, Rizzo LV, Nelson LM. Murine postthymectomy autoimmune oophoritis develops in association with a persistent neonatal-like Th2 response. Clin Immunol Immunopathol. 1997 Jun;83(3):230-6. doi: 10.1006/clin.1997.4338.</citation>
    <PMID>9175911</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anasti JN, Flack MR, Froehlich J, Nelson LM. The use of human recombinant gonadotropin receptors to search for immunoglobulin G-mediated premature ovarian failure. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1995 Mar;80(3):824-8. doi: 10.1210/jcem.80.3.7883837.</citation>
    <PMID>7883837</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim TJ, Anasti JN, Flack MR, Kimzey LM, Defensor RA, Nelson LM. Routine endocrine screening for patients with karyotypically normal spontaneous premature ovarian failure. Obstet Gynecol. 1997 May;89(5 Pt 1):777-9. doi: 10.1016/s0029-7844(97)00077-x.</citation>
    <PMID>9166320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 12, 2011</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Autoimmune</keyword>
  <keyword>Follicle</keyword>
  <keyword>Menopause</keyword>
  <keyword>Biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Glucocorticoids</keyword>
  <keyword>Premature Ovarian Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Amenorrhea</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovarian Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>POF</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Primary Ovarian Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Menopause, Premature</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autoimmune Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

