<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001957</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000016</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-DC-0016</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001957</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testing a Possible Cause of Reduced Ability of Children to Process Speech in Noise</brief_title>
  <official_title>TEOAE Suppression in Children With Auditory Processing Difficulty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders (NIDCD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to increase our understanding of the difficulty people have recognizing the&#xD;
      spoken word, especially in noisy situations.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subjects must be between 12 and 18 years old with no history of voice disorder, autism,&#xD;
      stuttering, aphasia, multiple sclerosis, traumatic brain injury, severe language disorders,&#xD;
      and psychiatric disorders. Group A subjects must show reduced speech-in-noise scores and&#xD;
      Group B subjects must demonstrate speech-in-noise scores within normal limits.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The child will perform a series of hearing tasks that will take from 1.5 to 2 hours, with a&#xD;
      break halfway through. A routine hearing test will be given. The child will sit in a&#xD;
      sound-treated room wearing earphones and will depress a button in response to sound or to&#xD;
      repeat words. The words may be in quiet or mixed with noise. In a test called &quot;immitance,&quot;&#xD;
      air pressure change and tones will be sent through a miniature probe in the ear for about 1&#xD;
      minute. TEOAE (transient-evoked otoacoustic emission) testing will test the inner ear with&#xD;
      clicking sounds. At times, noise will be presented through a probe in the opposite ear.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The child will listen to a series of recordings of speech in quiet and in noise and will be&#xD;
      asked to repeat what is heard. These recordings will include monosyllabic words with some&#xD;
      part of the sounds cut out; words presented with several voices speaking together; two words&#xD;
      presented at the same time, one to each ear (child must repeat both words); and two sentences&#xD;
      presented at the same time, one to each ear (child must repeat sentence presented to chosen&#xD;
      ear).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The only risk in this study is tiredness from listening.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Five to ten percent of school-age children in the United States are identified as having&#xD;
      learning disability and 10 to 20% have attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD). Many&#xD;
      of these children have difficulty with tasks that challenge the auditory system. It is&#xD;
      estimated that 3 to 7 percent of children have difficulty with auditory processing as a major&#xD;
      factor interfering with education (Chermak and Musiek, 1997). Pinpointing physiological&#xD;
      causes of auditory processing difficulty has been elusive. Intervention is hampered by the&#xD;
      lack of knowledge of possible physical causes and therefore intervention addresses systems&#xD;
      rather than causes of auditory processing difficulty. Indeed, whether the problem has a&#xD;
      peripheral or central origin is unclear. Identification of physiological differences in&#xD;
      children with auditory processing disorders may lead to electrophysiologic identification of&#xD;
      potential auditory processing disorders. Thus the possibility of early intervention might&#xD;
      reduce the educational impact of this problem.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The aim of this study is to investigate the relationship of the efferent auditory neural&#xD;
      system to the ability to process speech in noise. The study measures suppression of&#xD;
      otoacoustic emissions in a population of adolescents with auditory processing difficulty as&#xD;
      demonstrated by reduced ability to process speech in noise (Group A). These subjects will be&#xD;
      compared to an age and sex matched group of adolescents with speech-in-noise test scores&#xD;
      within normal limits (Group B). The study population will include 100 children between the&#xD;
      ages of 12 and 18 years. All subjects must demonstrate normal puretone thresholds, speech&#xD;
      recognition scores in quiet and middle ear function measured by acoustic immittance tests.&#xD;
      Furthermore, the subjects' otoacoustic emissions must have reproducibility percentages within&#xD;
      normal limits in the 2000, 3000, 4000 and 5000 Hz frequency bands. Subjects will complete an&#xD;
      auditory speech recognition test battery (Scan-A and NU6 in multi-talker noise) and&#xD;
      otoacoustic emission suppression tests. The auditory recognition tests each measure the&#xD;
      subjects' ability to recognize speech in the presence of various types of noise and/or&#xD;
      filtering. A group design will be used. Outcome parameters are the amount of suppression in&#xD;
      dB for a group of subjects with normal speech understanding in noise and a group with reduced&#xD;
      speech scores in noise and the relationship between speech measures and the degree of&#xD;
      suppression.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>November 2003</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>100</enrollment>
  <condition>Central Auditory Disease</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects selected will be between the ages of 12 and 18 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        All subjects must score within normal limits on measures of threshold sensitivity, speech&#xD;
        recognition in quiet, middle ear function and TEOAEs to be included in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Group A subjects must be identified as having learning or attention problems in school and&#xD;
        show show reduced scores on speech-in-noise tasks.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Group B subjects must demonstrate speech-in-noise scores within normal limits.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Groups will be matched for sex, age and handedness.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects will be excluded for history of voice disorders, autism, stuttering, aphasia,&#xD;
        multiple sclerosis, traumatic brain injury, severe language disorders and psychiatric&#xD;
        disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Children who are being treated for hyperactivity disorder will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Children who are taking medication prescribed for hyperactivity, anxiety or depression may&#xD;
        be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Children younger than 12 will be excluded.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders (NIDCD)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berlin CI, Hood LJ, Wen H, Szabo P, Cecola RP, Rigby P, Jackson DF. Contralateral suppression of non-linear click-evoked otoacoustic emissions. Hear Res. 1993 Dec;71(1-2):1-11. doi: 10.1016/0378-5955(93)90015-s.</citation>
    <PMID>8113128</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collet L. Use of otoacoustic emissions to explore the medial olivocochlear system in humans. Br J Audiol. 1993 Apr;27(2):155-9. doi: 10.3109/03005369309077907.</citation>
    <PMID>8220283</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collet L, Kemp DT, Veuillet E, Duclaux R, Moulin A, Morgon A. Effect of contralateral auditory stimuli on active cochlear micro-mechanical properties in human subjects. Hear Res. 1990 Jan;43(2-3):251-61. doi: 10.1016/0378-5955(90)90232-e.</citation>
    <PMID>2312416</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2003</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 19, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Ostoacoustic Emission</keyword>
  <keyword>Central Auditory Processing</keyword>
  <keyword>CAPD</keyword>
  <keyword>Medial Olivocochlear Bundle</keyword>
  <keyword>Speech Impediment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Auditory Diseases, Central</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

