<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005290</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL040587</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005290</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epidemiology of Interstitial Lung Disease</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of New Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of New Mexico</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To establish a population-based registry of interstitial lung disease in Bernalillo County,&#xD;
      New Mexico.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Although many investigations have been conducted to characterize the pathogenesis of&#xD;
      interstitial lung diseases, few examined the epidemiology of these disorders in a general&#xD;
      population. The establishment of the registry represented the first step in a sequence of&#xD;
      investigations designed to characterize the epidemiology of the interstitial lung diseases.&#xD;
      The registry initially served a descriptive purpose; the incidence of the interstitial lung&#xD;
      diseases was measured in a defined population. Subsequently the registry served as a&#xD;
      mechanism for ascertaining cases for a case-control study. Finally, the registry provided&#xD;
      population-based data for clinical purposes on presentation, physiology, and natural history&#xD;
      of the interstitial lung diseases.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The resources of the New Mexico Tumor Registry were adapted to identify new cases of&#xD;
      interstitial lung disease in Bernalillo County. Other sources of information for identifying&#xD;
      new cases included pulmonary physicians, primary care physicians, death certificates, and&#xD;
      autopsies. After a case of interstitial lung disease had been identified from the various&#xD;
      sources of information, data collection included an interviewer-administered symptoms&#xD;
      questionnaire, abstracted medical record data, phlebotomy for measurement of serum&#xD;
      precipitins, and evaluation of available chest x-rays and biopsy materials. Follow-up was&#xD;
      used to determine the natural history of the disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study was renewed in 1993 to complete the work conducted from 1988 through 1992.&#xD;
      Case-ascertainment, data collection, and follow-up of incident cases of ILD identified during&#xD;
      the period 10/1/88-9/30/92 were completed. The incidence of ILDs was described. The clinical&#xD;
      characteristics of patients with ILDs were described. The prognosis of the most common ILDs&#xD;
      were described.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 1988</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 1997</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Lung Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Lung Diseases, Interstitial</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mapel DW, Samet JM, Coultas DB. Corticosteroids and the treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Past, present, and future. Chest. 1996 Oct;110(4):1058-67. doi: 10.1378/chest.110.4.1058. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>8874268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coultas DB, Hughes MP. Accuracy of mortality data for interstitial lung diseases in New Mexico, USA. Thorax. 1996 Jul;51(7):717-20. doi: 10.1136/thx.51.7.717.</citation>
    <PMID>8882079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coultas DB, Zumwalt RE, Black WC, Sobonya RE. The epidemiology of interstitial lung diseases. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1994 Oct;150(4):967-72. doi: 10.1164/ajrccm.150.4.7921471.</citation>
    <PMID>7921471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mulloy KB, Coultas DB, Samet JM. Use of chest radiographs in epidemiological investigations of pneumoconioses. Br J Ind Med. 1993 Mar;50(3):273-5. doi: 10.1136/oem.50.3.273.</citation>
    <PMID>8457495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mapel DW, Hunt WC, Utton R, Baumgartner KB, Samet JM, Coultas DB. Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: survival in population based and hospital based cohorts. Thorax. 1998 Jun;53(6):469-76. doi: 10.1136/thx.53.6.469.</citation>
    <PMID>9713446</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 14, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 14, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Interstitial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

