<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001956</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000055</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-D-0055</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001956</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Influence of Genetics in Pain Sensitivity</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to learn more about the role of genetics in pain sensitivity.&#xD;
      Pain perception varies widely among individuals, and information gained from this trial may&#xD;
      lead to better methods of preventing and controlling pain. The study consists of two parts,&#xD;
      described below. All enrollees will participate in part 1; patients needing oral surgery for&#xD;
      removal of third molars may also participate in part 2.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Normal volunteers, oral surgery patients, and family members of both groups may be eligible&#xD;
      for this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Part 1 -Sensitivity testing for hot and cold. Participants will rate their pain response to&#xD;
      hot and cold stimuli on a scale from &quot;no pain&quot; to the &quot;worst pain imaginable.&quot; Heat&#xD;
      sensitivity is measured using a small probe placed on the skin for a few seconds. The hottest&#xD;
      temperature tested may cause pain for a few seconds but will not produce a burn. Response to&#xD;
      cold is measured by placing the hand in cold water for up to 3 minutes and occasionally&#xD;
      flexing the fist. Participants will rate their pain level every 15 seconds. In addition to&#xD;
      the testing, a blood sample will be drawn to examine for genes related to pain.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Part 2 - Oral surgery. Patients will have their third molar removed under a local anesthetic&#xD;
      (lidocaine) injected in the mouth and a sedative (Versed) given through a vein in the arm. A&#xD;
      small tissue biopsy will be taken from the tissue over one of the third molars. Patients will&#xD;
      stay in the clinic for up to 7 hours after surgery while the anesthetic wears off and will&#xD;
      rate any pain they may have according to the rating scale used in Part 1 of the study. Pain&#xD;
      medication (ketorolac, or Toradol) will be given when needed, and patients will complete pain&#xD;
      questionnaires for 3 hours after the drug is given to rate its effectiveness. Patients will&#xD;
      receive additional pain relievers, if needed. A second biopsy on the side opposite the first&#xD;
      will be taken under local anesthetic to measure changes in chemical signals produced in&#xD;
      response to the surgery.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Variability in pain sensitivity is a well known phenomena. Clinicians involved in the care of&#xD;
      post-surgical patients are very familiar with this variation in sensitivity. The variability&#xD;
      also extends to experimental pain stimuli (e.g., a thermal pulse to the forearm) and can be&#xD;
      demonstrated with normal volunteers. In our clinic, variation in the intensity and onset of&#xD;
      acute pain in the oral surgery model, in subjects matched for similar levels of tissue injury&#xD;
      ranges from little or no post-operative pain to reports of severe pain unrelieved by standard&#xD;
      analgesics. While a variety of factors may account for the variability such as race or gender&#xD;
      (Gordon 1998), preclinical data indicate that genetic factors profoundly influence pain&#xD;
      sensitivity. Thus, the proposed study seeks to investigate genetic contributions to acute&#xD;
      experimental and clinical post-operative pain. We have recently shown a strong correspondence&#xD;
      between pain reports using thermal heat stimuli and post-operative pain reports. This&#xD;
      observation has given us an important quantitative screening tool for genetic analysis of a&#xD;
      moderate-sized cohort of subjects that has direct clinical relevance. Normal subjects and&#xD;
      their siblings and/or parents will undergo two somatosensory tests to determine pain&#xD;
      phenotype and will provide a blood sample which will be analyzed for genetic polymorphisms&#xD;
      contributing to sensitivity to pain. Some of these subjects will also be candidates for the&#xD;
      oral surgery protocol and similar pain ratings will be obtained from them post-operatively.&#xD;
      The initial study will examine known polymorphisms for candidate genes that code for pain&#xD;
      sensing and pain suppressing molecules.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>February 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>800</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Hyperalgesia</condition>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood draw</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral surgery</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tissue biopsy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients in need of oral surgery for removal of impacted third molar will be recruited from&#xD;
        the local community and by physician or dental referrals.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Use of prescription and nonprescription analgesics, antihistamines, and antidepressants. No&#xD;
        history of psychiatric or neurological disorders or a positive score on the Beck Depression&#xD;
        Inventory, those females who are pregnant or nursing.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Dental And Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brennum J, Kjeldsen M, Jensen K, Jensen TS. Measurements of human pressure-pain thresholds on fingers and toes. Pain. 1989 Aug;38(2):211-7. doi: 10.1016/0304-3959(89)90240-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2780075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Casey KL, Minoshima S, Berger KL, Koeppe RA, Morrow TJ, Frey KA. Positron emission tomographic analysis of cerebral structures activated specifically by repetitive noxious heat stimuli. J Neurophysiol. 1994 Feb;71(2):802-7. doi: 10.1152/jn.1994.71.2.802.</citation>
    <PMID>8176441</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen ACN, Dworkin SF, Haug J, Gehrig J. Human pain responsivity in a tonic pain model: psychological determinants. Pain. 1989 May;37(2):143-160. doi: 10.1016/0304-3959(89)90126-7. Erratum In: Pain 1989 Nov;39(2):248.</citation>
    <PMID>2664663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2005</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 19, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 30, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Genetic Markers</keyword>
  <keyword>Thermal Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperalgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Cold Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Peripheral Nerve</keyword>
  <keyword>Allodynia</keyword>
  <keyword>Spinal Cord</keyword>
  <keyword>Personality Traits</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain Ratings</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperalgesia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

