<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001142</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000010</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-CH-0010</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001142</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metabolism and Body Shape of Healthy Children and Children With Chronic Infections</brief_title>
  <official_title>Metabolism and Body Composition of Healthy Children and Children With Chronic Infections</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Some HIV-infected adults develop lipodystrophy that includes significant changes in body&#xD;
      shape, with fat losses in the face, arms and legs, and fat gain in the trunk. This&#xD;
      lipodystrophy is often accompanied by other disorders of metabolism, such as increased levels&#xD;
      of fat and insulin in the blood.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The majority of these cases have been seen when patients are taking medications called&#xD;
      protease inhibitors. These are anti-retroviral medications designed to treat patients with&#xD;
      HIV. It is unclear if lipodystrophy is a result of having HIV or the medication used to treat&#xD;
      HIV. It has been suggested, but not proven, that lipodystrophy is a direct side effect of&#xD;
      protease inhibitors. In addition, it is unknown if HIV-infected children develop significant&#xD;
      lipodystrophy after taking protease inhibitors.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will investigate the prevalence of metabolic disorders and changes in body fat&#xD;
      distribution in children taking protease inhibitor anti-retroviral medications. The results&#xD;
      will be compared to three other groups; (1) children suffering from other non-HIV chronic&#xD;
      infections, (2) HIV-infected children not taking protease inhibitors, and (3) healthy&#xD;
      children.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study will look at HIV-infected children who have already started taking protease&#xD;
      inhibitors. It will evaluate these children for disorders in metabolism as well as body fat&#xD;
      changes. In addition, the study will follow HIV-infected children who will begin taking&#xD;
      protease inhibitors. The study will follow these children for 18 months to detect the&#xD;
      development of disorders in metabolism and / or body fat changes.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Some HIV-infected adults develop a lipodystrophy that includes significant changes in body&#xD;
      shape, with fat loss in the face, arms and legs, and fat gain in the trunk. This&#xD;
      lipodystrophy is often accompanied by hypertriglyceridemia, hypercholesterolemia, and&#xD;
      hyperinsulinemia. So far, almost all cases of lipodystrophy have occurred in patients treated&#xD;
      with protease inhibitor-containing antiretroviral therapies. Whether this lipodystrophy is a&#xD;
      result of the use of protease inhibitors or other therapies employed for HIV infection, or is&#xD;
      one of the many manifestations of HIV infection, and is unmasked by the longevity achieved by&#xD;
      those treated with protease inhibitors remains uncertain. It has been suggested, although not&#xD;
      proven, that this condition may be an adverse effect of protease inhibitor treatment. It is&#xD;
      also unknown whether HIV-infected children develop significant lipodystrophy when exposed to&#xD;
      protease inhibitors. We propose to investigate whether initiation of protease&#xD;
      inhibitor-containing antiretroviral regimens in children with HIV infection affects the&#xD;
      prevalence of dyslipidemia, insulin resistance, and alterations of body fat distribution, and&#xD;
      to study the pathophysiology of these changes. The incidence of such abnormalities will be&#xD;
      compared to children with non-HIV-related chronic infections, to HIV-infected children who&#xD;
      are treated with protease inhibitor sparing regimen, and to healthy controls.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study has both cross-sectional and longitudinal components. Children with HIV infection,&#xD;
      who are to begin taking protease inhibitors and who are already taking protease inhibitors as&#xD;
      part of their treatment for HIV infection, will be recruited for a single cross-sectional&#xD;
      evaluation that will include studies of lipid and glucose metabolism and body composition. In&#xD;
      the longitudinal component, those children with HIV infection, who were studied before they&#xD;
      began taking protease inhibitors, will be followed prospectively for 18 months to delineate&#xD;
      further the relationships between treatment and the development of lipodystrophy and&#xD;
      abnormalities in lipid and glucose metabolism. If the cross-sectional study does not show&#xD;
      that the prevalence of lipodystrophy and its associated metabolic alterations increases as a&#xD;
      function of exposure to protease inhibitors, we will terminate the prospective study. Changes&#xD;
      in triglyceride levels, insulin levels, and regional body fat will be evaluated as primary&#xD;
      outcome measures. As part of the evaluations performed during the cross-sectional and&#xD;
      longitudinal studies, we will investigate the pathophysiology of dyslipidemia in HIV-infected&#xD;
      children by assessing lipoproteins and their subclasses, apolipoproteins, and both&#xD;
      lipoprotein lipase levels and activity.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2000</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>185</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Hyperlipidemia</condition>
  <condition>Lipodystrophy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        FOR PROTEASE INHIBITOR-NAIVE HIV-INFECTED CHILDREN AND HIV-INFECTED CHILDREN ON PROTEASE&#xD;
        INHIBITOR-CONTAINING ANTIRETROVIRAL REGIMENS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Evidence of HIV infection based on Center for Disease Control and Prevention criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Enrollment on protocol 98-C-0041 or other HIV treatment protocol for children.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No other chronic disease unrelated to infection that may cause changes in body composition&#xD;
        or in lipid or glucose homeostasis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No previous use of a protease inhibitor-containing antiretroviral regimen (PROTEASE&#xD;
        INHIBITOR-NAIVE HIV-INFECTED CHILDREN ONLY).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Data available concerning the start date of protease inhibitor treatment (HIV-INFECTED&#xD;
        CHILDREN ON PROTEASE INHIBITOR-CONTAINING ANTIRETROVIRAL REGIMENS ONLY).&#xD;
&#xD;
        HEALTHY PEDIATRIC VOLUNTEERS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Good general health. No significant hematologic, renal, hepatic, endocrinologic, or&#xD;
        pulmonary disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No evidence of HIV infection by standard HIV antibody testing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Body mass index for age below 85th percentile.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Not currently using prescription medications on a continuing basis; the use of&#xD;
        over-the-counter medications will be reviewed on a case-by-case basis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Stable clinical condition during evaluation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        CHILDREN WITH CONDITIONS CAUSING CHRONIC INFECTIONS OTHER THAN HIV:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Evidence of chronic, non-HIV-related infection such as chronic granulomatous disease,&#xD;
        hyperimmunoglobin E syndrome, etc.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Evidence of non-growth hormone-deficient growth failure, defined as a 12-month height&#xD;
        velocity at or below the fifth percentile for age using standard reference norms and by&#xD;
        clinically-indicated testing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No evidence of HIV infection by standard HIV antibody testing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No current (last 2 months) use of sex steroid supplementation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Enrollment in an ongoing NIH protocol for treatment of their disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age between 4 and 18 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No other chronic disease unrelated to infection that may cause either changes in body&#xD;
        composition or lipid or glucose homeostasis such as Type I diabetes mellitus,&#xD;
        lipodystrophic diabetes, Cushing's syndrome etc.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No pregnancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No inability to undergo MRI because of metal objects within their bodies that are&#xD;
        contraindications for MRI. These include cardiac pacemakers, neural pacemakers, aneurysmal&#xD;
        clips, schrapnel, ocular foreign bodies, cochlear implants, non-detachable electronic or&#xD;
        electromechanical devices.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No allergic reaction to heparin.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carr A, Samaras K, Burton S, Law M, Freund J, Chisholm DJ, Cooper DA. A syndrome of peripheral lipodystrophy, hyperlipidaemia and insulin resistance in patients receiving HIV protease inhibitors. AIDS. 1998 May 7;12(7):F51-8. doi: 10.1097/00002030-199807000-00003.</citation>
    <PMID>9619798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lo JC, Mulligan K, Tai VW, Algren H, Schambelan M. &quot;Buffalo hump&quot; in men with HIV-1 infection. Lancet. 1998 Mar 21;351(9106):867-70. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(97)11443-X.</citation>
    <PMID>9525364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller KD, Jones E, Yanovski JA, Shankar R, Feuerstein I, Falloon J. Visceral abdominal-fat accumulation associated with use of indinavir. Lancet. 1998 Mar 21;351(9106):871-5. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(97)11518-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9525365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2000</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Body Fat</keyword>
  <keyword>DXA</keyword>
  <keyword>HAART</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperlipidemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipodystrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Protease Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Side-Effects</keyword>
  <keyword>Visceral Fat</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lipodystrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperlipidemias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperlipoproteinemias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

