<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005761</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000135</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-EI-0135</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005761</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blood Factors and Diabetic Retinopathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of Association of Serum Factors With Diabetic Retinopathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will determine whether certain factors in the blood are associated with the&#xD;
      severity of diabetic retinopathy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients age 10 years and older with diabetes mellitus and diabetic retinopathy may be&#xD;
      eligible for this study. Those enrolled will represent a range of diabetic retinopathy from&#xD;
      minimal to severe. Participants will undergo the following procedures:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  medical history&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  thorough eye examination&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  photographs of the eye&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  blood tests to measure blood lipids (cholesterol and triglycerides) and serum creatinine&#xD;
           (for kidney function)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  blood tests to measure levels of blood factors (cell adhesion molecules, chemokines and&#xD;
           vascular endothelial growth factor) that may be related to the progression of diabetic&#xD;
           retinopathy&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  blood pressure measurement&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  urinalysis&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study may lead to a better understanding of how diabetic retinopathy develops and&#xD;
      progresses.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants with a range of severity of diabetic retinopathy and healthy volunteers will be&#xD;
      evaluated once for serum levels of cell adhesion molecules, chemokines and vascular&#xD;
      endothelial growth factor. This study may lead to a better understanding of the pathogenesis&#xD;
      of diabetic retinopathy and the identifying of possible targets for treatment. All study&#xD;
      participants will undergo an ocular exam and ophthalmic photography. Blood is drawn for the&#xD;
      analysis of these serum factors.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 23, 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 7, 2010</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Actual">173</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Retinopathy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  VOLUNTEER INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Volunteers will be able to enroll if they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have the ability to understand and sign an informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are able and willing to give a blood sample.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are healthy as determined by study Investigator.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have no chronic diseases.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Do not exhibit any clinical indications of diabetes.&#xD;
&#xD;
        PARTICIPANT INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participants will be able to enroll if they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have the ability to understand and sign an informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are able and willing to give a blood sample.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a clinical diagnosis of diabetes based on any one of the following criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Documented history of plasma glucose value greater than or equal to 210 mg/dl on&#xD;
                  three different occasions.&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Fasting blood sugar greater than or equal to 150 mg/dl on three different&#xD;
                  occasions.&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Documented history of ketoacidosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
               4. Insulin dependency.&#xD;
&#xD;
               5. Documented history of abnormal glucose tolerance test.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Neither volunteers nor participants will be eligible if they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are under the age of 10.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have severe systemic disease(s) that compromise our ability to obtain an adequate&#xD;
             examination.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have any of the following ocular characteristics or conditions in both eyes:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Opacities of the ocular media, limitations or pupillary dilation or any other&#xD;
                  problems sufficient to preclude good, quality stereo fundus photographs.&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Ocular disease which confounds assessment of diabetic retinopathy such as&#xD;
                  advanced age-related macular degeneration, central serous choroidopathy, optic&#xD;
                  atrophy, retinal vein occlusion, active uveitis, significant explained or&#xD;
                  unexplained visual field loss, or any other type of retinopathy or retinal&#xD;
                  degeneration.&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Chronic requirement for any ocular medication for other diseases, such as&#xD;
                  glaucoma.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winocour PD. Platelet abnormalities in diabetes mellitus. Diabetes. 1992 Oct;41 Suppl 2:26-31. doi: 10.2337/diab.41.2.s26.</citation>
    <PMID>1526332</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lupu C, Calb M, Ionescu M, Lupu F. Enhanced prothrombin and intrinsic factor X activation on blood platelets from diabetic patients. Thromb Haemost. 1993 Oct 18;70(4):579-83.</citation>
    <PMID>8115982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jaffe EA. Cell biology of endothelial cells. Hum Pathol. 1987 Mar;18(3):234-9. doi: 10.1016/s0046-8177(87)80005-9.</citation>
    <PMID>3546072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 7, 2010</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 26, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 26, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 29, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Types 1 &amp; 2 Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Cell Adhesion Molecules</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemokines</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor</keyword>
  <keyword>Cross-Sectional</keyword>
  <keyword>Serum Levels</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetic Retinopathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Retinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

