<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00004571</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000085</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-M-0085</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00004571</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) of Neuropsychiatric Patients and Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Structural and Functional Imaging of Neuropsychiatric Patients and Normal Volunteers With 3.0 Tesla MRI and Magnetoencephalography (MEG)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to use brain imaging technology to compare differences in brain&#xD;
      structure, chemistry, and functioning in individuals with brain and mental disorders compared&#xD;
      to healthy volunteers.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Schizophrenia is a brain disorder that results from subtle changes and abnormalities in&#xD;
      neurons. These deficits likely occur in localized regions of the brain and may result in&#xD;
      widespread, devastating consequences. The neuronal abnormalities are inherited through a&#xD;
      complex combination of genetic and environmental factors. Brain imaging technologies can be&#xD;
      used to better characterize brain changes in individuals with schizophrenia. This study will&#xD;
      use magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans to identify predictable, quantifiable&#xD;
      abnormalities in neurophysiology, neurochemistry and neuroanatomy that characterize&#xD;
      schizophrenia and other neurological and neuropsychiatric disorders.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This protocol is meant to provide a matrix for multiple, simultaneous brain imaging&#xD;
      investigations using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) at 3.0 Tesla (3T). We intend to study&#xD;
      regional brain structure, physiology, and biochemistry in living human subjects, both healthy&#xD;
      and ill. Based on multiple clinical, neuropathological, and functional neuroimaging studies,&#xD;
      it is clear that schizophrenia is a brain disorder arising from subtle neuronal deficits (for&#xD;
      lack of more specific terminology). These deficits likely arise in a few key regions such as&#xD;
      dorsolateral prefrontal cortex and hippocampal formation, that result in widespread,&#xD;
      multifaceted, and devastating clinical consequences. These neuronal deficits are clearly&#xD;
      heritable, although in a complex fashion from multiple genes interacting in an epistatic&#xD;
      fashion with each other and the environment. We hypothesize that these neuronal deficits,&#xD;
      clearly resulting in quantifiable behavioral abnormalities in schizophrenic patients, will&#xD;
      produce predictable, quantifiable aberrations in neurophysiology that we can &quot;map&quot; using&#xD;
      magnetic resonance imaging. In spite of numerous functional imaging findings, clinical&#xD;
      applications remain scarce and pathognomonic findings absent. Therefore, we do not anticipate&#xD;
      that an approach based solely on any one modality is likely to significantly advance our&#xD;
      knowledge base. Instead, we propose to create brain imaging datasets for individual human&#xD;
      subjects predicated on 1) the appraisal of brain function from multiple domains&#xD;
      simultaneously; 2) the characterization of brain function via summation and intercorrelation&#xD;
      of these data; and 3) the digestion of these data based on the parsing of complex clinical&#xD;
      phenomenology into quantifiable neurophysiological parameters. Thus, in addition to the&#xD;
      identification of those parameters that best characterize and identify manifest schizophrenia&#xD;
      (i.e., state variables), we hypothesize that some of these fundamental characteristics will&#xD;
      be heritable. These fundamental characteristics, so-called endo- or intermediate phenotypes,&#xD;
      represent powerful tools to find susceptibility genes and have already generated a number of&#xD;
      linkage findings.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 17, 2000</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>regional MRSI measures</measure>
    <time_frame>spectroscopy</time_frame>
    <description>GABA and glutamate measurements in schizophrenia and healthy controls.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>magnetic field potentials</measure>
    <time_frame>MEG</time_frame>
    <description>Group differences in MEG signal for patients with schizophrenia and healthy subjects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fMRI BOLD responses</measure>
    <time_frame>MRI study completion</time_frame>
    <description>Group differences between patients with schizophrenia and healthy subjects, also genotyping used to characterize subjects as well.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DTI anisotropy measures</measure>
    <time_frame>DTI</time_frame>
    <description>Compare fractional anisotropy and other measures of white matter connectivity for schizophrenic patients and controls.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>brain volumetric measures</measure>
    <time_frame>VBM</time_frame>
    <description>VBM and cortical parcellation are used in schizophrenia and healthy controls.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>neuropsychological task performance data</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3420</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <condition>Normal Physiology</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy subjects from the community</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Schizophrenia</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with schizophrenia and psychosis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Williams Syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals with copy number variation in the Williams Syndrome Region</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with schizophrenia and healthy subjects from the community.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        CONTROLS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        No psychiatric or severe chronic medical illness at the time of the study, and by history.&#xD;
        This includes the absence of substance abuse histories, learning disabilities and all DSM&#xD;
        IV disorders. The investigators will evaluate medical histories and medical conditions that&#xD;
        are judged not to interfere with the study may be allowed.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No use of psychotropic substances in the last 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        There is no upper age limit. The lower age limit is 18 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Controls will all have the capacity to consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        PATIENTS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Schizophrenia, any subtype or schizo-affective disorder according to DSM IV .&#xD;
&#xD;
        Bipolar Disorder with Psychotic Features according to DSM IV.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Menstrually-Related Mood Disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Mild to Moderate Parkinson's Disease (Hoehn and Yahr Stage 1-3).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Williams Syndrome (partial or full) with IQ in the normal range.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with Multiple Sclerosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        CONTROLS AND PATIENTS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Impaired hearing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Head trauma with loss of consciousness in the last year, or any evidence of functional&#xD;
        impairment due to and persisting after head trauma.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients or healthy volunteers with a known risk from exposure to high magnetic fields&#xD;
        (e.g. patients with pace makers) and those who have metallic implants (e.g. braces) in the&#xD;
        head region (likely to create artifact on the MRI scans) will be excluded from&#xD;
        participating in the fMRI studies.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of any (excepting nicotine-related) DSM5-defined moderate to severe substance use&#xD;
        disorder (or DSM-IV-defined substance dependence).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Cumulative lifetime history of any (excepting nicotine-related) DSM5-defined mild substance&#xD;
        use disorder (or any DSM-IV-defined substance abuse), either in excess of 5 years total or&#xD;
        not in remission for at least 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        NIMH employees and staff and their immediate family members will be excluded from the study&#xD;
        per NIMH policy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Non-NIMH NIH employees and staff may participate and will be given the NIH Frequently Asked&#xD;
        Questions (FAQs) for NIH Staff Who are Considering Participation in NIH Research.&#xD;
&#xD;
        PATIENTS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Coexistence of another major mental illness at the time of the study. If the patients&#xD;
        experienced other mental illnesses in the past (e.g. a learning disability or major&#xD;
        depression), then this should be judged to be fully recovered.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Major concurrent medical illness likely to interfere with the acquisition of the task.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concomitant medications which could interfere with performance on the task.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Involuntary movements that interfere with positioning in the MRI scanner).&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael D Gregory, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bobby Das</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-4593</phone>
    <email>bdas@ln.nimh.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michael D Gregory, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-1371</phone>
    <email>gregorymd@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2000-M-0085.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 12, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 15, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 15, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 16, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <keyword>MEG</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognition</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

