<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000588</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>308</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL042814</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000588</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chelation Therapy of Iron Overload With Pyridoxal Isonicotinoyl Hydrazone</brief_title>
  <official_title>Chelation Therapy of Iron Overload With Oral Pyridoxal Isonicotinoyl Hydrazone</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Case Western Reserve University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Case Western Reserve University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To demonstrate the safety and effectiveness of orally-administered pyridoxal isonicotinoyl&#xD;
      hydrazone (PIH) for the chronic treatment of iron overload.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Iron overload in patients with refractory anemia may be the consequence of repeated blood&#xD;
      transfusion, of excessive absorption of dietary iron, or of a combination of both. The body&#xD;
      lacks any effective means for the excretion of excess iron and in patients with refractory&#xD;
      anemia, an inexorable accumulation of iron contained in transfused red cells or absorbed from&#xD;
      the diet eventually exceeds the body's capacity for safe storage. Without treatment,&#xD;
      widespread iron-induced damage to the liver, heart, pancreas, and other organs is followed by&#xD;
      an early death, most often the result of cardiac failure.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Treatment with a chelating agent capable of sequestering iron and permitting its excretion&#xD;
      from the body is the most widely-used therapeutic approach. Desferrioxamine was first&#xD;
      introduced 30 years ago and is the only iron-chelating agent now in clinical use. A number of&#xD;
      recent studies have shown that regular chelation therapy with desferrioxamine can prevent&#xD;
      organ damage and improve survival in transfusion-dependent patients with thalassemia major&#xD;
      and other disorders. However, desferrioxamine given orally is poorly absorbed and to be&#xD;
      effective must be given by subcutaneous or intravenous infusion using a small portable&#xD;
      syringe pump, ideally for 12 hours each day. Compliance with this regimen is frequently poor,&#xD;
      particularly in adolescents with thalassemia major who may be at greatest risk for the lethal&#xD;
      complications of iron overload. With modern transfusion programs, one of the main threats to&#xD;
      life in patients with transfusion-dependent anemias is non-compliance with iron-chelation&#xD;
      therapy. Moreover, the cost of desferrioxamine therapy in transfusion-dependent therapy&#xD;
      exceeds $10,000 per year, in part because the drug must be isolated from bacterial cultures.&#xD;
      Despite the limitations, trials of desferrioxamine have validated iron chelation as a&#xD;
      therapeutic approach to iron overload.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PIH was first recognized as an effective iron chelator in vitro in 1979. It is easily&#xD;
      produced by the Schiff base condensation of two widely used, inexpensive drugs, vitamin B-6&#xD;
      (pyridoxal) and the antituberculous agent isoniazid. The recent Phase I studies of low-dose&#xD;
      PIH in healthy controls and volunteers with iron overload have found no evidence of toxicity&#xD;
      while producing an amount of iron excretion that would be clinically useful in the treatment&#xD;
      of non-transfusion-dependent patients with iron-loading anemias. The trial should provide&#xD;
      evidence that orally-administered PIH can be substituted for chronic subcutaneous infusions&#xD;
      of desferrioxamine in the management of iron overload in refractory anemia.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The trial was part of an Institute-initiated study on Iron Overload: Cooley's Anemia and&#xD;
      Other Disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      There were three studies in the Phase II trial. Study 1 demonstrated the safety and&#xD;
      effectiveness of oral PIH in reducing the body iron burden to near-normal levels in&#xD;
      non-transfusion-dependent patients with iron-loading anemias. Study 2 demonstrated the safety&#xD;
      and effectiveness of oral PIH in maintaining near-normal body iron stores in&#xD;
      transfusion-dependent patients who had previously been well-chelated with chronic&#xD;
      subcutaneous or intravenous desferrioxamine. Study 3 demonstrated safety and effectiveness of&#xD;
      oral PIH in reducing the body iron burden to near normal levels in iron-loaded&#xD;
      transfusion-dependent patients. Studies 1 and 2 were carried out concurrently. Study 3 began&#xD;
      after the methods used in the first two studies documented a sufficient level of iron&#xD;
      excretion to permit the iron-loaded transfusion patients to keep pace with ongoing&#xD;
      transfusional loading and excrete previous accumulations of iron. After an initial 21 day&#xD;
      balance study to demonstrate that a selected dose of PIH produced sufficient iron excretion,&#xD;
      patients were begun on chronic therapy. PIH or placebo were given on days 4 to 9 and days 13&#xD;
      to 18 in a randomized, double-blind, cross-over design. Study 4 demonstrated the&#xD;
      effectiveness in 21 patients of oral deferiprone in inducing sustained decreases in body iron&#xD;
      concentrations compatible with the avoidance of complications from iron overload.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Repeat balance studies were carried out at three months, six months, and thereafter at least&#xD;
      annually with hematological and biochemical parameters monitored at weekly intervals for the&#xD;
      first month, at biweekly intervals for the next two months, and at least monthly thereafter.&#xD;
      Studies were conducted at the Cleveland Metropolitan General Hospital and at Siriraj Hospital&#xD;
      in Bangkok, Thailand.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 5, 1989</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 1995</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 1993</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Chronic dose according to condition:&#xD;
Reducing the body iron burden to near-normal levels in non- transfusion-dependent patients with iron-loading anemias (requires chelate- induced iron excretion of at least 0.10 to 0.20 mg Fe/kg/day);&#xD;
Maintaining near-normal body iron stores in transfusion-dependent patients who have previously been well-chelated with chronic subcutaneous or intravenous desferrioxamine (requires chelate-induced iron excretion of at least 0.25 to 0.40 mg Fe/kg/day);&#xD;
Reducing the body iron burden to near-normal levels in iron-loaded, transfusion-dependent patients (requires chelate-induced iron excretion greater than 0.40 mg Fe/kg/day).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia (Iron-Loading)</condition>
  <condition>Beta-Thalassemia</condition>
  <condition>Hematologic Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hemoglobinopathies</condition>
  <condition>Thalassemia</condition>
  <condition>Iron Overload</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic therapy of PIH according to medical condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Half of overall participants will get one of the following doses according to their medical condition:&#xD;
Reducing the body iron burden to near-normal levels in non- transfusion-dependent patients with iron-loading anemias (requires chelate- induced iron excretion of at least 0.10 to 0.20 mg Fe/kg/day);&#xD;
Maintaining near-normal body iron stores in transfusion-dependent patients who have previously been well-chelated with chronic subcutaneous or intravenous desferrioxamine (requires chelate-induced iron excretion of at least 0.25 to 0.40 mg Fe/kg/day);&#xD;
Reducing the body iron burden to near-normal levels in iron-loaded, transfusion-dependent patients (requires chelate-induced iron excretion greater than 0.40 mg Fe/kg/day).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Half of the participants will receive a Placebo:&#xD;
Non-transfusion-dependent patients&#xD;
Transfusion-dependent patients&#xD;
Iron-loaded, transfusion-dependent patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chelation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>After an initial 21 day balance study to demonstrate that a selected dose of PIH produced sufficient iron excretion, patients were begun on chronic therapy. PIH or placebo were given on days 4 to 9 and days 13 to 18 in a randomized, double-blind, cross-over design.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic therapy of PIH according to medical condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chronic therapy of Pyridoxal Isonicotinoyl Hydrazone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo given at same time points as the Intervetnion for each clinical condition.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic therapy of PIH according to medical condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients meeting any of the following health conditions and eligible for Chronic PIH&#xD;
             Treatment&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Non- transfusion-dependent patients with iron-loading anemias&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Transfusion-dependent patients who have previously been well-chelated with chronic&#xD;
             subcutaneous or intravenous desferrioxamine&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Iron-loaded, transfusion-dependent patients&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ages: 18-75 years old&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  People who are not eligible for chronic PIH therapy and not meet the medical&#xD;
             conditions listed in the Inclusion criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ages: 17 years old or younger or 76 years old or older&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary Brittenham</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Case Western Reserve University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brittenham GM. Pyridoxal isonicotinoyl hydrazone. Effective iron chelation after oral administration. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 1990;612:315-26. doi: 10.1111/j.1749-6632.1990.tb24319.x. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>2291560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brittenham GM. Pyridoxal isonicotinoyl hydrazone: an effective iron-chelator after oral administration. Semin Hematol. 1990 Apr;27(2):112-6. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>2190317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nathan DG. An orally active iron chelator. N Engl J Med. 1995 Apr 6;332(14):953-4. doi: 10.1056/NEJM199504063321411. No abstract available. Erratum In: N Engl J Med 1995 May 11;332(19):1315.</citation>
    <PMID>7877655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olivieri NF, Brittenham GM, Matsui D, Berkovitch M, Blendis LM, Cameron RG, McClelland RA, Liu PP, Templeton DM, Koren G. Iron-chelation therapy with oral deferiprone in patients with thalassemia major. N Engl J Med. 1995 Apr 6;332(14):918-22. doi: 10.1056/NEJM199504063321404.</citation>
    <PMID>7877649</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 27, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2022</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2022</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 21, 2022</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thalassemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>beta-Thalassemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemoglobinopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Iron Overload</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pyridoxal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pyridoxal isonicotinoyl hydrazone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

