<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001725</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>980042</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>98-D-0042</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001725</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Studies of Dextromethorphan and Topiramate to Treat Oral and Facial Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Trials in Orofacial Neuralgias</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the safety and effectiveness of two drugs-dextromethorphan and&#xD;
      topiramate-in treating orofacial (mouth and face) pain. Dextromethorphan, a commonly used&#xD;
      cough suppressant, and topiramate, an anti-seizure medicine, block certain receptors on brain&#xD;
      and spinal nerve cells that may cause the cells to produce electrical discharges and pain.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients 18 years of age and older with oral and facial pain with trigeminal nerve damage and&#xD;
      who have had pain daily for at least 3 months may be eligible for this study. Candidates will&#xD;
      be screened with a medical history, physical examination, blood tests and psychiatric&#xD;
      evaluation. These results will serve as baseline values for participants. Those enrolled in&#xD;
      the study will take either dextromethorphan or topiramate in a 2-part study as follows:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Dextromethorphan&#xD;
&#xD;
      In Part 1, patients will take dextromethorphan and lorazepam (a commonly used anti-anxiety&#xD;
      drug) separately in two 6-week periods. (Lorazepam is used in this study as an &quot;active&#xD;
      placebo&quot; for comparison with dextromethorphan. An active placebo is a drug that does not work&#xD;
      for the problem being studied but whose side effects are like those of the test drug.) They&#xD;
      will take dextromethorphan for 4 weeks to determine the maximum tolerated dose (the highest&#xD;
      dose that does not cause troubling side effects) and will stay on that dose for the remaining&#xD;
      2 weeks. Then they will repeat this process with lorazepam. Patients who respond to either&#xD;
      drug may continue with Part 2 of the study, which compares these two drugs four more times to&#xD;
      confirm the response seen in Part 1. In Part 2, the maximum tolerated dose will be determined&#xD;
      in a 2-week period and that dose will be continued for another 2 weeks. This procedure will&#xD;
      be repeated eight times. Throughout the study, patients will keep a daily pain diary. They&#xD;
      will be contacted by telephone 2 to 3 times a week during dose escalation to check for side&#xD;
      effects. At the end of each of the two 6-week periods in Part 1 and at the end of each 4-week&#xD;
      period in Part 2 of the study, patients will have a 1-hour clinic visit. Participants who&#xD;
      live more than a few hours' drive from NIH will have a full telephone follow-up evaluation&#xD;
      instead of the clinic visits.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Topiramate&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients who receive topiramate will follow a plan similar to that described above for&#xD;
      dextromethorphan, with the following exceptions. They will take topiramate and an inactive&#xD;
      placebo (a look-alike pill that has no active ingredients) in two separate 12-week periods.&#xD;
      Patients' maximum tolerated dose will be determined in the first 8 weeks and they will stay&#xD;
      on that dose for the remaining 4 weeks of each period. Patients who respond to the medication&#xD;
      in Part 1 may continue with Part 2 to confirm the response. Part 2 consists of six 6-week&#xD;
      periods. The first 4 weeks of each will be used to determine the maximum tolerated dose and&#xD;
      the patient will remain on that dose for the next 2 weeks. Patients will keep a daily pain&#xD;
      diary and will be contacted by phone 2 to 3 times a week while doses are being increased.&#xD;
      Patients who complete Part 2 of the topiramate study may participate in another phase of the&#xD;
      study that will last for 2 years. Those who continue for this phase will take topiramate for&#xD;
      the 2-year period. They will be followed regularly by a study nurse and will come to NIH&#xD;
      every 6 months for a follow-up visit.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Some of the clinical features of trigeminal and other facial neuralgias suggest that these&#xD;
      painful disorders may be associated with sensitization of central nervous system neurons.&#xD;
      Laboratory evidence has shown that central sensitization can be produced and maintained by&#xD;
      excitatory amino acids (e.g. glutamate) acting on neurons at NMDA and AMPA/kainate receptor&#xD;
      sites. Given this information, and the need for more effective treatments of orofacial&#xD;
      neuropathic pain syndromes, two possible candidates worthy of study are 1) dextromethorphan,&#xD;
      an NMDA receptor antagonist and 2) topiramate, an anticonvulsant drug with AMPA/kainate&#xD;
      receptor blocking activity. Thus, the purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy and&#xD;
      safety of topiramate (TPM) or high-dose dextromethorphan (DM) versus placebo in the treatment&#xD;
      of pain in patients with trigeminal neuralgia (TN) and other orofacial neuropathic pain&#xD;
      syndromes. We propose two 6 month studies respectively evaluating dextromethorphan (60&#xD;
      patients; at least 20 with TN, 20 with definite trigeminal nerve pathology and 20 with likely&#xD;
      trigeminal nerve pathology) and topiramate (40 patients; at least 20 with TN, 20 with&#xD;
      definite trigeminal nerve pathology). These will be double-blind randomized crossover designs&#xD;
      comparing high-dose dextromethorphan (DM) versus lorazepam (LOR) (as an active placebo) OR&#xD;
      topiramate versus inactive placebo. The primary study outcome measure (in both parts) will be&#xD;
      overall daily pain assessed by Gracely pain intensity descriptors. Other recorded data will&#xD;
      include adverse drug effects, the frequency, severity and duration of pain paroxysms and a&#xD;
      questionnaire focusing on daily function (modification of the Brief Pain Inventory).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>100</enrollment>
  <condition>Facial Neuralgia</condition>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Trigeminal Neuralgia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dextromethorphan</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Facial neuralgia, not explained by bone, soft tissue or mucosal lesions.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Experiencing daily moderate pain or daily paroxysms of pain unremitting for at least 3&#xD;
        months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Previous trial of an antineuralgic medication.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients entering the study on other analgesic medications must either continue them as a&#xD;
        stable regimen throughout the study period or discontinue them 2 weeks prior to starting&#xD;
        the initial pain diary.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Adults aged 18 to 89.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Serum laboratory results obtained at study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Liver function tests: ALT/AST less than 1.2 times upper limit of normal;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Creatinine less than 1.5 times upper limit of normal;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Negative serum betaHCG for women of childbearing age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Adequate birth control (e.g., oral contraceptives, Norplant) for all women of child-bearing&#xD;
        age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Sufficient cognitive function and English language skills to complete questionnaires and&#xD;
        communicate verbally with the nursing staff to permit titration of the study drugs.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No presence of a painful condition as severe as, but distinct from their orofacial pain&#xD;
        condition.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No pregnant or lactating women.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must not have end-stage renal or hepatic disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must not have moderate to severe heart disease (MI within preceding year, unstable&#xD;
        angina or congestive heart failure).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No signs or symptoms of any central neurologic disorder (including seizures).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No psychological/psychiatric disorder as identified by a pre-study entry psychiatric&#xD;
        assessment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must not have hypersensitivity or intolerance to dextromethorphan, topiramate or&#xD;
        the active placebo.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No chronic substance abuse, including alcoholism.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must have a primary physician.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects must not have received an experimental drug or used and experimental device within&#xD;
        30 days.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Dental And Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen TS, Yaksh TL. Brainstem excitatory amino acid receptors in nociception: microinjection mapping and pharmacological characterization of glutamate-sensitive sites in the brainstem associated with algogenic behavior. Neuroscience. 1992;46(3):535-47. doi: 10.1016/0306-4522(92)90142-o.</citation>
    <PMID>1347650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burchiel KJ, Clarke H, Haglund M, Loeser JD. Long-term efficacy of microvascular decompression in trigeminal neuralgia. J Neurosurg. 1988 Jul;69(1):35-8. doi: 10.3171/jns.1988.69.1.0035.</citation>
    <PMID>2454303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calvin WH, Loeser JD, Howe JF. A neurophysiological theory for the pain mechanism of tic douloureux. Pain. 1977 Apr;3(2):147-154. doi: 10.1016/0304-3959(77)90078-1.</citation>
    <PMID>876672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2002</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Trigeminal Neuralgia</keyword>
  <keyword>Dextromethorphan</keyword>
  <keyword>Topiramate</keyword>
  <keyword>Orofacial Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuropathic Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Facial Neuralgia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Trigeminal Neuralgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Facial Neuralgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Facies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dextromethorphan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

