<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00006337</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>010001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>01-N-0001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00006337</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>KW-6002 to Treat Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Adenosine A2A Blockade With KW-6002 in Parkinson's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the effects of an experimental drug called KW-6002 on Parkinson's&#xD;
      disease symptoms and on dyskinesias (involuntary movements) that develop as a result of&#xD;
      long-term treatment with levodopa. This drug blocks the action of the neurotransmitter&#xD;
      adenosine, thought to be involved in producing Parkinson's symptoms.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with relatively advanced (Stage II to IV) Parkinson's disease between 30 and 80&#xD;
      years of age may be eligible for this 7-week study. Participants will have a complete medical&#xD;
      history and physical examination, including blood tests and an electrocardiogram, and&#xD;
      possibly brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), CT scan, and chest X-ray.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients enrolled in the study will, if possible, stop taking all antiparkinsonian&#xD;
      medications except levodopa (Sinemet) for one month before the study begins and throughout&#xD;
      its duration. For the first 1 to 3 days, patients will be admitted to the NIH Clinical center&#xD;
      to undergo a levodopa &quot;dose-finding&quot; procedure. For this study, patients will stop taking&#xD;
      Sinemet and instead will have levodopa infused through a vein for up to 8 hours/day. During&#xD;
      the infusions, the drug dose will be increased slowly until either 1) parkinsonian symptoms&#xD;
      improve, 2) unacceptable side effects occur, or 3) the maximum study dose is reached.&#xD;
      Symptoms will be monitored frequently to find two infusion rates: 1) one that is less than&#xD;
      what is needed to relieve symptoms, and 2) one that relieves symptoms but may produce&#xD;
      dyskinesias. This procedure will be repeated at the end of weeks 2, 4 and 6 of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      When the patient's optimal dose is determined treatment will begin. Patients will take&#xD;
      tablets or capsules containing KW-6002 or placebo (a look-alike pill with no active&#xD;
      ingredient) once a day for 2 weeks, in addition to their regular Sinemet. All participants&#xD;
      will receive placebo at least 2 weeks during the study; some patients will receive only&#xD;
      placebo throughout the entire 7 weeks. At the end of weeks 1, 3 and 5, patients will be&#xD;
      evaluated with a brief physical examination, routine blood and urine tests, and assessment of&#xD;
      any adverse effects.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Throughout the study, parkinsonian symptoms and dyskinesias will be evaluated and blood&#xD;
      samples will be drawn periodically to measure drug levels.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to evaluate the acute effects of adenosine A2a receptor&#xD;
      blockade on parkinsonian symptoms and levodopa-associated motor response complications in&#xD;
      patients with advanced Parkinson's disease. In a controlled clinical trial, efficacy will be&#xD;
      assessed through the use of validated motor function scales. Safety will be monitored by&#xD;
      means of frequent clinical evaluations and laboratory tests.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>16</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>KW-6002</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IV Levodopa</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Males and females between the ages of 30-80.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Carry the diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's disease based on the presence of a&#xD;
        characteristic clinical history and neurologic findings.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with relatively advanced disease (Hohen and Yahr stage II-IV in the off state).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with Parkinson's disease who have been treated with levodopa for at least one&#xD;
        year.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with Parkinson's disease who require levodopa/carbidopa dosing at qid or more&#xD;
        frequent intervals.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Will have been receiving a stable regimen of treatment for Parkinson's disease for at least&#xD;
        4 weeks prior to study admission.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with Parkinson's disease who have associated motor response complications,&#xD;
        including wearing-off fluctuations and peak-dose dyskinesias.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must be able to provide written informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with non-idiopathic parkinsonism or parkinsonian variants (e.g. juvenile&#xD;
        Parkinson's disease; atypical parkinsonism; secondary parkinsonism; progressive&#xD;
        supra-nuclear palsy; Shy-Drager syndrome; olivopontocerebellar atrophy will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with a clinically significant illness of any organ system, including hepatic,&#xD;
        renal, pancreatic, cardiovascular, endrocrinologic, gastrointestinal, respiratory, and&#xD;
        neurologic system (except for those with Parkinson's disease) who may require a change in&#xD;
        the treatment of that illness during the trial, or that may compromise the safety of the&#xD;
        patient volunteer during the trial, or that may affect the ability of the volunteer to&#xD;
        complete the trial will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No presence or history of any medical condition that can reasonably be expected to subject&#xD;
        the patient to unwarranted risk, including cancer (except basal cell carcinoma or&#xD;
        surgically excised carcinoma in situ of the cervix) as well as liver or pancreatic enzyme&#xD;
        test results above the upper limit of normal.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who have had bilateral intracranial neurosurgical procedures such as nuclear&#xD;
        ablation, stimulator implantation or tissue transplantation will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with a history of seizures, including one or more infantile febrile seizures, or&#xD;
        with a history of neuroepileptic malignant syndrome will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who, for any reason, are judged by the investigator to be inappropriate for the&#xD;
        study (including volunteers who are unable to communicate or to cooperate with the&#xD;
        investigator) will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with significant dementia (MMSE 25 or less), major psychotic illness, history of&#xD;
        drug or alcohol abuse within past two years, and those who require drug therapy for a&#xD;
        DSM-IV major depressive episode will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who satisfy DSM-IV criteria for alcohol or other drug abuse or dependence within&#xD;
        two years of being exposed to KW-6002 will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who have been treated with a centrally acting dopamine antagonist drug, including&#xD;
        neuroleptic agents, metoclopramide and buspirone within three months (within six months for&#xD;
        depot formulations) because of the potential liability for extrapyramidal side effects will&#xD;
        be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients taking nonselective monoamine oxidase inhibitors (phenelzine, isocarboxazid,&#xD;
        tranylcypromine) will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who have taken terfenadine, astemizole, cisapride, simvastatin, lovastatin,&#xD;
        felodipine, or nifedipine within seven days before being exposed to KW-6002 will be&#xD;
        excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who have previously been exposed to KW-6002 or who have been treated with any&#xD;
        other investigational agents within 12 weeks (or within five half-lives for investigational&#xD;
        agents with a half-life of longer than 2 weeks) of being exposed to KW-6002 will be&#xD;
        excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with unacceptable prior/concomitant medications as will patients who have taken an&#xD;
        investigational drug within the 2 months prior to randomization will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnant will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Females who are of childbearing potential must be using a reliable method of contraception&#xD;
        at the time they agree to study participation and must agree to continue using a reliable&#xD;
        method of contraception include hormonal products (e.g. approved oral contraceptives or&#xD;
        long-term injectable or implantable contraceptives), double barrier methods (e.g. condom&#xD;
        plus diaphragm; condom plus spermicidal foam; condom plus spermicidal sponge). an&#xD;
        intra-uterine device or tubal ligation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        All female volunteers of child-bearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test&#xD;
        on the day before first exposure to KW-6002.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients taking any medications listed in Section 6.2, Forbidden Medications.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chase TN, Oh JD, Blanchet PJ. Neostriatal mechanisms in Parkinson's disease. Neurology. 1998 Aug;51(2 Suppl 2):S30-5. doi: 10.1212/wnl.51.2_suppl_2.s30.</citation>
    <PMID>9711978</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mizuno Y, Mori H, Kondo T. Parkinson's disease: from etiology to treatment. Intern Med. 1995 Nov;34(11):1045-54. doi: 10.2169/internalmedicine.34.1045.</citation>
    <PMID>8774962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernheimer H, Birkmayer W, Hornykiewicz O, Jellinger K, Seitelberger F. Brain dopamine and the syndromes of Parkinson and Huntington. Clinical, morphological and neurochemical correlations. J Neurol Sci. 1973 Dec;20(4):415-55. doi: 10.1016/0022-510x(73)90175-5. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>4272516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2002</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 4, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 5, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Clinical Trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Dyskinesias</keyword>
  <keyword>Levodopa Infusion</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Levodopa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Istradefylline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

