<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000927</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HIVNET 009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000927</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of BufferGel in Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Vaginal Microbicide Study of BufferGel</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see if it is safe to use BufferGel in the vaginas of women&#xD;
      who do not have HIV and who have a low risk of getting HIV.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Many new cases of HIV are the result of heterosexual activity. Condom use is currently the&#xD;
      only effective way of preventing the spread of HIV and other sexually transmitted diseases&#xD;
      (STDs). However, women, who have a greater risk of getting HIV, are often unable to convince&#xD;
      their partner to use a condom. Therefore, it is important to develop methods that prevent the&#xD;
      spread of HIV and that are controlled by the woman, such as medicines used in the vagina.&#xD;
      BufferGel is known to kill the organisms that cause STDs, including HIV. BufferGel may do&#xD;
      this without causing genital irritation and sores as other medicines do. More studies are&#xD;
      needed to see if this is true.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Heterosexual transmission of HIV presently accounts for the vast majority of new HIV&#xD;
      infections worldwide. Currently the condom is the only method available that has been shown&#xD;
      to be effective against HIV and other sexually transmitted diseases (STDs). However, women&#xD;
      who are at the greatest risk for acquiring HIV are often unable to negotiate condom use.&#xD;
      Therefore, it is important that effective female-controlled barrier methods, such as topical&#xD;
      microbicides, be made available to women. BufferGel has sufficient buffer capacity to acidify&#xD;
      twice its own volume in human semen, which inactivates STD pathogens, including HIV. Unlike&#xD;
      most other topical microbicides, BufferGel is non-detergent so it should not cause genital&#xD;
      irritation and lesions. The safety and acceptability of BufferGel still need to be studied&#xD;
      more carefully.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants are divided into two cohorts. Cohort IA consists of sexually abstinent women and&#xD;
      cohort IB consists of sexually active women. Within each U.S. cohort, participants are&#xD;
      assigned to apply BufferGel either once or twice daily. Within each international cohort, all&#xD;
      participants apply BufferGel twice daily. Participants apply BufferGel for 14 days. Pelvic&#xD;
      examinations are performed at Days 7 and 14.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>40</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BufferGel</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        All participants must have:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  HIV-negativity by licensed EIA.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willingness and ability to complete a study diary.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A regular menstrual cycle with a minimum of 18 days between menses.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ability to insert BufferGel daily as required by the protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Cohort IA participants must:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agree to abstain from sexual intercourse for the duration of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Cohort IB participants must:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agree to have vaginal intercourse at least 2 times per week and use non-lubricated&#xD;
             condoms for each act of intercourse.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have currently (for 3 months or longer) a single sexual partner who is at low-risk for&#xD;
             HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Co-existing Condition:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participants with the following conditions or symptoms are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A Grade 3 or higher liver, renal, or hematology abnormality.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Menopausal.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Breakthrough menstrual bleeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any STD or symptoms, as seen on pelvic exam, consistent with an STD or other genital&#xD;
             tract infection or trauma including vaginitis, cervicitis, edema, erythema,&#xD;
             ecchymosis, petechial hemorrhage, vulvar or cervicovaginal lesions or abrasions,&#xD;
             subepithelial hemorrhage, or signs of genital tract infection (other than asymptomatic&#xD;
             bacterial vaginosis) from laboratory evaluations.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any vaginal product other than BufferGel, including lubricants and feminine hygiene&#xD;
             products.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Vaginal drying agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Douche.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participation in any other microbicide or contraceptive study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Treatment for any STD.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participants with the following prior conditions are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  IUD, abnormal PAP smear, pregnancy, abortion, or gynecologic surgery in the last 3&#xD;
             months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any of the following side effects related to Depo-provera use in the past 2 months:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  headaches, dizziness, abdominal pain, fatigue, or nervousness.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A course of antibiotic therapy (other than treatment for malaria) in the last 14 days.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any spermicide within the past month.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Initiation of Depo-provera for contraceptive purposes in the last 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Risk Behavior:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of intravenous drugs currently or within the past year.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kenneth Mayer</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kenrad Nelson</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mem Hosp of Rhode Island</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pawtucket</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02860</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>van De Wijgert J, Fullem A, Kelly C, Mehendale S, Rugpao S, Kumwenda N, Chirenje Z, Joshi S, Taha T, Padian N, Bollinger R, Nelson K. Phase 1 trial of the topical microbicide BufferGel: safety results from four international sites. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2001 Jan 1;26(1):21-7. doi: 10.1097/00126334-200101010-00003.</citation>
    <PMID>11176265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mayer KH, Peipert J, Fleming T, Fullem A, Moench T, Cu-Uvin S, Bentley M, Chesney M, Rosenberg Z. Safety and tolerability of BufferGel, a novel vaginal microbicide, in women in the United States. Clin Infect Dis. 2001 Feb 1;32(3):476-82. doi: 10.1086/318496. Epub 2001 Jan 26.</citation>
    <PMID>11170957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 1999</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 8, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 8, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 9, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Administration, Topical</keyword>
  <keyword>Mucous Membrane</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-Infective Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Cervix Uteri</keyword>
  <keyword>Vagina</keyword>
  <keyword>Vulva</keyword>
  <keyword>Buffers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

