<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000719</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG 050</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11024</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000719</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial of Alternating 2',3'-Dideoxycytidine and Zidovudine in the Treatment of Patients With Advanced HIV Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Trial of Alternating 2',3'-Dideoxycytidine and Zidovudine in the Treatment of Patients With Advanced HIV Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the long-term safety and tolerance of four alternating and two intermittent&#xD;
      regimens of zidovudine ( AZT ) and 2',3'-dideoxycytidine ( zalcitabine; ddC ) in the&#xD;
      treatment of patients with advanced HIV disease who have had to discontinue AZT because of&#xD;
      true hematologic intolerance to standard reduced doses of AZT.&#xD;
&#xD;
      AIDS is a serious infectious disease caused by a new family of retrovirus which is spread&#xD;
      primarily through sexual contact and administration of blood or blood products. Individuals&#xD;
      who are infected with HIV could therefore benefit from therapy with an effective anti-AIDS&#xD;
      virus agent. AZT and ddC have both been tested as antiviral agents and their potentially&#xD;
      beneficial effects may be limited by time- and dose-dependent toxicity. A combination regimen&#xD;
      using shorter courses of AZT and ddC might therefore be able to sustain treatment without&#xD;
      producing toxicity. In addition, since the two drugs exhibit their major toxicity on&#xD;
      different organ systems, cumulative or additive toxicity would not be expected.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      AIDS is a serious infectious disease caused by a new family of retrovirus which is spread&#xD;
      primarily through sexual contact and administration of blood or blood products. Individuals&#xD;
      who are infected with HIV could therefore benefit from therapy with an effective anti-AIDS&#xD;
      virus agent. AZT and ddC have both been tested as antiviral agents and their potentially&#xD;
      beneficial effects may be limited by time- and dose-dependent toxicity. A combination regimen&#xD;
      using shorter courses of AZT and ddC might therefore be able to sustain treatment without&#xD;
      producing toxicity. In addition, since the two drugs exhibit their major toxicity on&#xD;
      different organ systems, cumulative or additive toxicity would not be expected.&#xD;
&#xD;
      There are six study regimens. Four of these are alternating regimens: A 2-week cycle&#xD;
      consisting of 1 week of AZT followed by 1 week of ddC and an 8-week cycle consisting of 4&#xD;
      weeks of AZT followed by 4 weeks of ddC. All patients on alternating regimens will receive&#xD;
      AZT alone at the standard dose orally every 4 hours for either 1 or 4 weeks. After the AZT is&#xD;
      stopped, patients receive ddC orally every 4 hours for either 1 or 4 weeks, which completes a&#xD;
      treatment cycle. One of two doses of ddC is studied in each alternating regimen. Both doses&#xD;
      must be tested because the optimal dose cannot be inferred from tests that have already been&#xD;
      done. AZT is administered first in the hope that AZT-mediated reduction of p24 antigen load&#xD;
      may reduce the occurrence of acute ddC toxicity. Two intermittent regimens are also studied&#xD;
      and are included to assess the contribution of each drug in the alternating regimens. One&#xD;
      program consists of 1 week of AZT followed by 1 week of no drug. The other consists of 1 week&#xD;
      of ddC followed by 1 week of no drug. Drug dosing continues for a total of 48 weeks unless&#xD;
      toxicity develops. Patients who complete 48 weeks of therapy are followed for 4 additional&#xD;
      weeks off therapy. Patients removed from study because of toxicity are followed for 4 weeks&#xD;
      or until toxicity resolves. If study participants complete 48 weeks of therapy and meet&#xD;
      criteria for efficacy, the study drug regimen may be continued for an additional 32 weeks. A&#xD;
      4 week wash-out period off drug will not be required for patients continuing on study.&#xD;
      AMENDED 09/24/90 Drug dosing will be discontinued as of 11/30/90.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 1995</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>96</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zidovudine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zalcitabine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Aerosolized pentamidine at prophylactic doses, but its use is discouraged in persons&#xD;
             without a history of Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia (PCP).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acyclovir for acute disseminated zoster.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Maintenance doses of pyrimethamine, amphotericin, and pentamidine are allowed for&#xD;
             patients who recover from toxoplasmosis, cryptococcosis, or pneumocystosis acquired&#xD;
             after study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients included in the study must have HIV infection confirmed by ELISA test and must&#xD;
        have a documented history of at least 4 weeks of zidovudine (AZT) treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  While hemoglobin at the start of AZT therapy must have been = or &gt; 9.5 g/dl and&#xD;
             granulocyte count = or &gt; 1200 cells/mm3 at the start of AZT therapy, hematologic&#xD;
             toxicity due to a reduced dose of AZT will be defined as:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hematologic toxicity must have occurred during a period when AZT was administered at =&#xD;
             or &lt; 600 mg/day for at least 2 weeks.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  There must have been no evidence of a cause for toxicity other than HIV infection and&#xD;
             AZT use.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hematologic intolerance may have consisted of hemoglobin toxicity, granulocyte&#xD;
             toxicity, or both.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Recovery from hematologic toxicity must be manifested by the presence of a granulocyte&#xD;
             count of &gt; 1000 cells/mm3 and a hemoglobin of &gt; 9.5 g/dl. without transfusions during&#xD;
             the preceding 4 weeks. Patients must also have no significant bilateral symptoms of&#xD;
             peripheral neuropathy, although all patients may have any degree of stable unilateral&#xD;
             neurologic deficit. Up to 24 patients may have certain moderate bilateral&#xD;
             abnormalities of peripheral neuropathy. AZT may not have been administered within 14&#xD;
             days prior to entering the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Required:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A documented history of at least 4 weeks of zidovudine treatment which resulted in&#xD;
             hematologic toxicity at reduced dose.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Allowed but discouraged:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A1-721.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Co-existing Condition:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with the following are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Known active AIDS opportunistic infections.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Known mycobacteremia, although cultures may be pending at the time of enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Symptomatic visceral Kaposi's sarcoma (KS), progression of KS within the month prior&#xD;
             to entry into the study or with concurrent neoplasms other than KS, basal cell&#xD;
             carcinoma of the skin or in situ carcinoma of the cervix.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Significant malabsorption as manifested by steatorrhea with greater than 10 percent&#xD;
             weight loss within the last 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diabetes.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Experimental medications.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Aspirin.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acetaminophen.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents should be minimized, with continuous use for &gt;&#xD;
             72 hours discouraged.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chronic suppressive anti-infective therapy other than inhaled pentamidine and&#xD;
             neurotoxic drugs should be avoided.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Continuous therapy for &gt; 7 days of acyclovir is prohibited except for the acute&#xD;
             treatment of disseminated herpes zoster infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with the following are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Known mycobacteremia, although cultures may be pending at the time of enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Symptomatic visceral Kaposi's sarcoma (KS), progression of KS within the month prior&#xD;
             to entry into the study or with concurrent neoplasms other than KS, basal cell&#xD;
             carcinoma of the skin or in situ carcinoma of the cervix.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Significant malabsorption as manifested by steatorrhea with greater than 10 percent&#xD;
             weight loss within the last 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diabetes.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Known active AIDS opportunistic infections. Patients must also have no significant&#xD;
             bilateral symptoms of peripheral neuropathy, although all patients may have any degree&#xD;
             of stable unilateral neurologic deficit. Up to 24 patients may have certain moderate&#xD;
             bilateral abnormalities of peripheral neuropathy. AZT may not have been administered&#xD;
             within 14 days prior to entering the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded within 30 days of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any antiretroviral agents except zidovudine (AZT).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Discouraged:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A1-721.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pentamidine at prophylactic doses in persons without a history of Pneumocystis carinii&#xD;
             pneumonia (PCP).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Active substance and/or alcohol abuse.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>S Bozzette</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>D Richman</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>USC CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ucsd, Avrc Crs</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ. of Miami AIDS CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush Univ. Med. Ctr. ACTG CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tulane Med. Ctr. - Charity Hosp. of New Orleans, ACTU</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota, ACTU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lathey JL, Marschner IC, Kabat B, Spector SA. Deterioration of detectable human immunodeficiency virus serum p24 antigen in samples stored for batch testing. J Clin Microbiol. 1997 Mar;35(3):631-5. doi: 10.1128/jcm.35.3.631-635.1997.</citation>
    <PMID>9041402</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gries JM, Troconiz IF, Verotta D, Jacobson M, Sheiner LB. A pooled analysis of CD4 response to zidovudine and zalcitabine treatment in patients with AIDS and AIDS-related complex. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 1997 Jan;61(1):70-82. doi: 10.1016/S0009-9236(97)90183-1.</citation>
    <PMID>9024175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fichtenbaum CJ, Clifford DB, Powderly WG. Risk factors for dideoxynucleoside-induced toxic neuropathy in patients with the human immunodeficiency virus infection. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr Hum Retrovirol. 1995 Oct 1;10(2):169-74. doi: 10.1097/00042560-199510020-00009.</citation>
    <PMID>7552481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bozzette SA, Richman DD. Salvage therapy for zidovudine-intolerant HIV-infected patients with alternating and intermittent regimens of zidovudine and dideoxycytidine. Am J Med. 1990 May 21;88(5B):24S-26S. doi: 10.1016/0002-9343(90)90418-d.</citation>
    <PMID>2159706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>LeLacheur SF, Simon GL. Exacerbation of dideoxycytidine-induced neuropathy with dideoxyinosine. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr (1988). 1991;4(5):538-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1849990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bozzette S, Skowron G, Arrezo J, Spector SA, Pettinelli C, Richman DD. ACTG 050: alternating (alt) and intermittent (INT) ddc and AZT in the treatment of persons with advanced HIV infection and hematologic intolerance to AZT. Int Conf AIDS. 1990 Jun 20-23;6(3):192 (abstract no SB425)</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2021</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 27, 2021</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 27, 2021</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 3, 2021</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Zalcitabine</keyword>
  <keyword>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Zidovudine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Zidovudine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Zalcitabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

