<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00006278</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000178</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-CH-0178</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00006278</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Cushing's Syndrome Not Related to ACTH Production</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Molecular and Cellular Etiology of ACTH-Independent Adrenal Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to provide information about the cause of two unusual types of&#xD;
      Cushing's syndrome and to evaluate quality of life before and after cure of the disease. In&#xD;
      Cushing's syndrome, the adrenal glands produce too much of the hormone cortisol. This often&#xD;
      causes weight gain, skin changes (bruising and stretch marks), and mood changes such as&#xD;
      irritability, easy crying and depression. Adrenocorticotrophic hormone (ACTH) normally&#xD;
      regulates cortisol production; when cortisol is low, ACTH rises, stimulating the adrenals to&#xD;
      produce more cortisol, and when cortisol is high, ACTH levels fall. In two forms of Cushing's&#xD;
      syndrome, however, the adrenal glands produce cortisol even when ACTH is low.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients 18 years of age and older with Cushing's syndrome not related to ACTH production may&#xD;
      participate in this study. Candidates will be have a history and physical examination,&#xD;
      electrocardiogram, urine, blood and saliva tests, and a computerized tomography (CT) scan of&#xD;
      one or both adrenal glands. They will fill out questionnaires on their disease symptoms,&#xD;
      quality of life, and on basic information about themselves, such as marital status, education&#xD;
      level, place of residence, etc. Finally, they will have a corticotropin-releasing hormone&#xD;
      (CRH) test to confirm that they have the form of Cushing's syndrome under study in this&#xD;
      protocol. This test involves collecting blood samples at intervals before and after&#xD;
      administration of sheep CRH to measure cortisol and ACTH levels.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants will undergo 3 to 7 days of testing to determine if their cortisol level rises&#xD;
      after taking certain medicines or eating certain foods. These foods and medicines, chosen to&#xD;
      mimic or stimulate substances already in the body, are: glucagon, ACTH,&#xD;
      gonadotropin-releasing hormone, vasopressin, thyrotropin-releasing hormone, and a mixed meal&#xD;
      consisting of a protein, carbohydrate and fat (usually chicken breast and a milkshake-like&#xD;
      drink). Blood will be collected at intervals before and after taking the food or medicine to&#xD;
      measure cortisol blood levels. Blood will also be collected while the patient is in a&#xD;
      standing position and while lying in bed, because changes in posture can cause substances in&#xD;
      the body to increase or decrease. Depending on the individual's response to these tests,&#xD;
      additional tests may be done with insulin, glucose, luteinizing hormone and&#xD;
      follicle-stimulating hormone.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients who do not respond to these substances will undergo adrenalectomy (surgery to remove&#xD;
      one or both adrenal glands). This is standard treatment for this type of Cushing's syndrome.&#xD;
      It is usually done by laparoscopy, in which air is injected into the abdomen through tubes&#xD;
      inserted through a small incision, enabling the surgeon to see the organs and remove the&#xD;
      gland. Part of the removed tissue will be examined to learn about what causes this type of&#xD;
      Cushing's syndrome; it may also be used for genetic studies related to the disease. Patients&#xD;
      will stay in the hospital for a week to 10 days for observation and treatment and then will&#xD;
      be discharged to the care of their own doctor. They will continue to complete the quality of&#xD;
      life questionnaire every 3 months for 2 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with normal adrenal glands who are participating in National Cancer Institute&#xD;
      studies and are scheduled for adrenalectomy as part of their standard treatment will also be&#xD;
      recruited for this study to serve as controls. The patients will have a 24-hour urine&#xD;
      collection, and part of the adrenal gland tissue removed for their treatment will be used for&#xD;
      research purposes of this study, possibly including genetic study.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In healthy individuals, ACTH is the major stimulus for cortisol production and cellular&#xD;
      growth of the adrenal cortex. Normal or elevated ACTH levels can amplify this stimulus,&#xD;
      leading to hypercortisolism and growth of the adrenal gland, a clinical condition recognized&#xD;
      as Cushing's syndrome. However, some patients with hypercortisolism of Cushing's syndrome&#xD;
      have suppressed rather than normal or high levels of ACTH. This pilot study seeks to better&#xD;
      understand the apparently autonomous nature of hypercortisolism in two benign causes of&#xD;
      Cushing's syndrome, adrenal adenomas and massive macronodular adrenal disease (MMAD).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with low levels of ACTH and Cushing's syndrome will undergo routine tests to confirm&#xD;
      that they have hypercortisolism, low ACTH, and adenoma or MMAD on CT scans. They will fill&#xD;
      out a questionnaire about quality of life. They will also undergo 3-7 days of research&#xD;
      testing with a variety of agents to investigate whether these agents increase cortisol.&#xD;
      Following this, patients will be scheduled for adrenalectomy at the NIH. This is the standard&#xD;
      treatment for these conditions. The abnormal tissue obtained at surgery will be used for&#xD;
      laboratory studies to evaluate whether the same or other agents may be the cause of excess&#xD;
      cortisol production.&#xD;
&#xD;
      After surgery, patients will be discharged to the care of their local health care provider,&#xD;
      but will continue to fill out questionnaires on the quality of life for two years.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>September 2002</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>18</enrollment>
  <condition>Cushing's Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        PATIENTS WITH NORMAL ADRENAL GLANDS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with normal adrenal glands will be recruited from those studied under NCI&#xD;
        protocols.&#xD;
&#xD;
        They will not have taken suppressive doses of glucocorticoids for 12 months, and will not&#xD;
        have any known adrenal pathology, either of the cortex or medulla.&#xD;
&#xD;
        They will not have Von-Hippel Lindau syndrome.&#xD;
&#xD;
        PATIENTS WITH ACTH-INDEPENDENT CUSHING'S SYNDROME:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Will be aged 18 or older;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Will have plasma ACTH levels of 10 pg/mL or less;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Will have an outside physician who will follow them after surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must not weigh greater than 380 pounds. These patients are unable to undergo CT scans.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must not have a CT scan showing normal or atrophic bilateral adrenal glands.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must not have a CRH test showing a response as defined above. The diagnosis of these&#xD;
        patients will need further evaluation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must not have any condition that would preclude surgery, including advanced heart failure,&#xD;
        significant coronary artery disease, severe pulmonary disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must not have a hematocrit less than 30 or research blood withdraw greater than 450 mL in&#xD;
        the previous six weeks.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must not be pregnant.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must not have a history of angina or known coronary artery disease, because these patients&#xD;
        are at risk for exacerbation during the vasopressin test.&#xD;
&#xD;
        The SF-36 questionnaire will only be given to individuals who speak and read English&#xD;
        fluently. Patients may participate in the remainder of the study, however, if they do not&#xD;
        meet this criterion.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonner RF, Emmert-Buck M, Cole K, Pohida T, Chuaqui R, Goldstein S, Liotta LA. Laser capture microdissection: molecular analysis of tissue. Science. 1997 Nov 21;278(5342):1481,1483. doi: 10.1126/science.278.5342.1481. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>9411767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dickstein G, DeBold CR, Gaitan D, DeCherney GS, Jackson RV, Sheldon WR Jr, Nicholson WE, Orth DN. Plasma corticotropin and cortisol responses to ovine corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH), arginine vasopressin (AVP), CRH plus AVP, and CRH plus metyrapone in patients with Cushing's disease. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1996 Aug;81(8):2934-41. doi: 10.1210/jcem.81.8.8768855.</citation>
    <PMID>8768855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doppman JL, Nieman LK, Travis WD, Miller DL, Cutler GB Jr, Chrousos GP, Norton JA. CT and MR imaging of massive macronodular adrenocortical disease: a rare cause of autonomous primary adrenal hypercortisolism. J Comput Assist Tomogr. 1991 Sep-Oct;15(5):773-9. doi: 10.1097/00004728-199109000-00009.</citation>
    <PMID>1653280</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2002</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Cushing's Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Adrenal Glands</keyword>
  <keyword>Proteomics</keyword>
  <keyword>Cortisol</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cushing Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

