<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00002775</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000064755</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CPMC-IRB-7386</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-V96-0888</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00002775</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Docetaxel Plus Estramustine in Treating Patients With Metastatic Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>PHASE I/II STUDY OF DOCETAXEL (TAXOTERE) AND ESTRAMUSTINE COMBINATION CHEMOTHERAPY IN PATIENTS WITH PROSTATE CANCER</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so&#xD;
      they stop growing or die. Combining more than one drug may kill more tumor cells.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PURPOSE: Phase I/II trial to study the effectiveness of combining docetaxel and estramustine&#xD;
      in treating patients who have metastatic prostate cancer.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine the maximum tolerated dose, toxicity, and pharmacokinetic profile of&#xD;
      docetaxel in combination with estramustine in patients with metastatic adenocarcinoma of the&#xD;
      prostate. II. Determine the safe dose level of this regimen for Phase II evaluation. III.&#xD;
      Determine the efficacy of this regimen with evaluation of objective response rate, duration&#xD;
      of response, and time to disease progression in these patients. IV. Determine the duration of&#xD;
      survival of these patients on this regimen. V. Evaluate the symptomatic and quality of life&#xD;
      effects in these patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      OUTLINE: This is a dose escalation study (phase I). Patients are stratified into one of two&#xD;
      risk groups by number of prior chemotherapy regimens (0-2 vs greater than 2) and occurrence&#xD;
      and site(s) of prior radiation. Patients receive oral estramustine three times daily&#xD;
      beginning 24 hours prior to docetaxel and continuing for 4 days after infusion. Patients&#xD;
      receive docetaxel IV over 1 hour every 21 days. Cohorts of 3-6 patients receive escalating&#xD;
      doses of docetaxel until the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is reached (phase I). The MTD is&#xD;
      defined as the dose preceding that at which 2 of 6 patients experience dose limiting&#xD;
      toxicity. A minimum of 6 patients receive treatment at the MTD. Phase II: Patients receive&#xD;
      docetaxel IV at the MTD from phase I. Treatment continues in the absence of disease&#xD;
      progression or unacceptable toxicity for both phases. Quality of life is assessed. Patients&#xD;
      are followed every 3 months until death.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: Approximately 12-37 patients will be accrued for this study within 13-19&#xD;
      months.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 1998</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">37</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>docetaxel</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>estramustine phosphate sodium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed metastatic adenocarcinoma of the prostate&#xD;
        Failure of androgen ablation (orchiectomy or luteinizing hormone releasing hormone,&#xD;
        flutamide) -Rise in PSA greater than 50% of nadir confirmed by 2 measurements 1 week apart&#xD;
        -Appearance of new soft tissue lesions -Appearance of new lesions on bone scan Measurable&#xD;
        or evaluable disease No symptomatic ascites, pleural effusions, or peripheral edema greater&#xD;
        than trace No brain or leptomeningeal involvement&#xD;
&#xD;
        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Performance status: ECOG 0-2 Life expectancy: Not&#xD;
        specified Hematopoietic: WBC at least 3,500/mm3 Absolute neutrophil count at least&#xD;
        1,500/mm3 Platelet count at least 100,000/mm3 No history of coagulopathy Hepatic: Bilirubin&#xD;
        no greater than upper limit of normal (ULN) SGOT or SGPT no greater than 2.0 times ULN&#xD;
        Alkaline phosphatase no greater than 5.0 times ULN Renal: Creatinine no greater than 2.0&#xD;
        times ULN Cardiovascular: No myocardial infarction within past 6 months Pulmonary: No prior&#xD;
        pulmonary embolus Neurologic: No prior cerebrovascular accident No symptomatic peripheral&#xD;
        neuropathy greater than grade 1 No significant neurologic or psychiatric disorder&#xD;
        (psychotic disorder, dementia, or seizure) Other: No other prior malignancy within past 5&#xD;
        years, except: Excised or curatively irradiated nonmelanomatous skin cancer No other&#xD;
        serious illness or medical condition No active infection&#xD;
&#xD;
        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: Not specified Chemotherapy: At least 4 weeks&#xD;
        since prior chemotherapy Endocrine therapy: At least 4 weeks since prior hormonal therapy&#xD;
        Radiotherapy: At least 4 weeks since prior radiotherapy At least 6 weeks since prior&#xD;
        isotope therapy No prior radiotherapy to greater than 30% of bone marrow Surgery: Not&#xD;
        specified Other: At least 4 weeks since prior investigational drugs&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel P. Petrylak, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2000</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 1, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 2, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>adenocarcinoma of the prostate</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent prostate cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estramustine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

