<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001087</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG 364</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10691</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001087</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effectiveness of Nelfinavir and Efavirenz, Used Alone or Together, Combined With Other Anti-HIV Drugs in Patients Who Have Taken Anti-HIV Drugs</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of the Virologic Efficacy of Nelfinavir and/or DMP 266 (Efavirenz, EFV) in Combination With One or Two New Nucleoside Analogs in Nucleoside Experienced Subjects: A Roll-Over Study to ACTG 302/303</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Steps I and II: The purpose of this study is the following: To look at how many patients&#xD;
      achieve undetectable HIV blood levels at Week 16. To look at the absolute change in HIV blood&#xD;
      levels from the beginning of the study to Week 16. To look at the safety and tolerability of&#xD;
      nelfinavir (NFV) and efavirenz (EFV) when used in combination or separately in regimens&#xD;
      containing reverse transcriptase inhibitors (RTIs). For the 2 extension studies (Weeks 49 to&#xD;
      144): To look at the proportion of patients whose long-term viral load remains undetectable&#xD;
      at Week 96. To look at the time from the beginning of the study to treatment failure, with&#xD;
      patients evaluated through Week 144. Step III: To look at the proportion of patients whose&#xD;
      HIV blood levels are undetectable 16 weeks after starting the salvage study treatment. To&#xD;
      assess safety, toxicity, and tolerance of salvage study drug treatment. (This study has been&#xD;
      changed by adding new objectives.) Achieving viral suppression has been widely endorsed as&#xD;
      the primary goal of HIV therapy. However, there are few established guidelines for devising&#xD;
      combinations of different classes of drugs which will enhance the potential for achieving&#xD;
      viral suppression, reducing the risk of toxicity, and preserving therapeutic options for&#xD;
      future use. This study includes 2 anti-HIV drugs, NFV (a protease inhibitor [PI]) and EFV (a&#xD;
      nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor [NNRTI]), for use either alone or in&#xD;
      combination with RTI therapy for the purpose of limiting HIV replication. Patients with&#xD;
      treatment failure at Week 16 choose 1 of the following 3 alternative salvage therapies:&#xD;
      2-drug PI regimen (saquinavir and ritonavir) plus adefovir dipivoxil and L-carnitine; EFV or&#xD;
      NFV (if not already given) plus 2 new approved anti-HIV drugs outside the study; or the best&#xD;
      available treatment outside the study. The new RTI, adefovir dipivoxil, is added to the&#xD;
      2-drug PI regimen to achieve suppression of viral replication and thereby delay disease&#xD;
      progression. (This rationale reflects a change in the treatment given to patients with&#xD;
      treatment failure at Week 16.)&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Achieving viral suppression has been widely endorsed as the primary goal of HIV therapy, yet&#xD;
      there are few established guidelines to provide the framework by which to devise combinations&#xD;
      of different classes of drugs which will not only enhance the potential for achieving viral&#xD;
      suppression while reducing the risk of toxicity but will also preserve therapeutic options&#xD;
      for future use. This study includes 2 antiretroviral compounds, NFV (a protease inhibitor&#xD;
      [PI]) and EFV (a nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor [NNRTI]), for use either alone&#xD;
      or in combination with reverse transcriptase inhibitor (RTI) therapy for the purpose of&#xD;
      limiting HIV replication. [AS PER AMENDMENT 3/5/98: Patients who experience treatment failure&#xD;
      at Week 16 or later choose 1 of the following alternative potent salvage therapy regimens: a&#xD;
      dual-PI regimen (saquinavir/ritonavir) plus adefovir dipivoxil and L-carnitine; EFV or NFV&#xD;
      (if not already given) plus 2 new approved antiretroviral drugs outside the study; or the&#xD;
      best available treatment outside the study. The new reverse transcriptase inhibitor, adefovir&#xD;
      dipivoxil, is added to the dual-PI regimen to achieve suppression of viral replication and&#xD;
      thereby delay disease progression.]&#xD;
&#xD;
      Step I: Patients with detectable plasma HIV RNA levels are assigned to Group A, and those&#xD;
      with undetectable levels are assigned to Group B (control).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Group A: Patients are randomized to 1 of 3 treatment arms: NFV plus EFV placebo on Arm I; NFV&#xD;
      placebo plus EFV on Arm II; or NFV plus EFV on Arm III. Concurrent with their randomly&#xD;
      assigned therapy, patients receive open-label RTI therapy comprising 1 of the following 3&#xD;
      combinations that provides 1 or 2 new RTIs: didanosine (ddI) plus stavudine (d4T); lamivudine&#xD;
      (3TC) plus d4T; or ddI plus 3TC. [AS PER AMENDMENT 12/02/97: Patients with virologic failure&#xD;
      at Week 16 seek the best available therapy outside the study or continue study medication for&#xD;
      up to 120 days.] [AS PER AMENDMENT 3/5/98: Patients with virologic failure at Week 16 now&#xD;
      proceed to Step III.] Patients without virologic failure continue therapy during Weeks 1 to&#xD;
      48 [AS PER AMENDMENT 3/5/98: and those without virologic failure at Week 48 may continue&#xD;
      therapy during Weeks 49 to 96 (first extension study)]. [AS PER AMENDMENT 5/27/99: After Week&#xD;
      96, patients in Arm I may switch to Arm III or seek the best available antiretroviral therapy&#xD;
      outside the study. Patients in Arm II or III with undetectable plasma HIV RNA levels at Week&#xD;
      96 may continue therapy during Weeks 97 to 144 (second extension study) or seek the best&#xD;
      alternative antiretroviral therapy. Patients in Arm II or III with detectable plasma HIV RNA&#xD;
      levels but without virologic failure at Week 48 continue their current study therapy or&#xD;
      proceed to Step III. Patients with confirmed virologic failure at Week 48 or later proceed to&#xD;
      Step III or seek the best available alternative therapy outside the study.] Group B: Patients&#xD;
      receive treatment on their assigned, open-label ACTG 302/303 regimen. Patients with&#xD;
      detectable plasma HIV RNA levels discontinue Group B therapy and proceed to Step II. Patients&#xD;
      with undetectable plasma HIV RNA levels continue therapy during Weeks 1 to 48 [AS PER&#xD;
      AMENDMENT 6/24/98: and those with undetectable levels at Week 48 may continue therapy during&#xD;
      Weeks 49 to 96 (first extension study)]. [AS PER AMENDMENT 5/27/99: Patients with&#xD;
      undetectable levels at Week 96 may continue therapy during Weeks 97 to 144 (second extension&#xD;
      study).] Step II: Patients receive treatment as in Group A. [Step III: AS PER AMENDMENT&#xD;
      3/5/98: Patients choose 1 of 3 alternative therapies: saquinavir soft gel capsule, ritonavir,&#xD;
      adefovir dipivoxil, and L-carnitine on Arm X; EFV or NFV plus 2 new approved antiretroviral&#xD;
      drugs outside the study on Arm Y (if no prior EFV or NFV); or best available medication&#xD;
      outside the study on Arm Z.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients in Arm X or Y are followed on salvage therapy for 24 to 48 weeks. Patients with&#xD;
      detectable plasma HIV RNA levels after 16 weeks on salvage therapy are encouraged to&#xD;
      discontinue study medication and seek best alternative treatment.]&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2000</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>300</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ritonavir</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nelfinavir mesylate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Efavirenz</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levocarnitine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adefovir dipivoxil</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saquinavir</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lamivudine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stavudine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zidovudine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zalcitabine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Didanosine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Required:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chemoprophylaxis for Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia for all patients who have a CD4&#xD;
             count of 200 cells/mm3 or less.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Topical and oral antifungal except for oral ketoconazole.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Treatment, maintenance, or chemoprophylaxis with approved agents for opportunistic&#xD;
             infections as clinically indicated.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  All antibiotics as clinically indicated.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Systemic corticosteroid use for no more than 21 days for acute problems as medically&#xD;
             indicated. Note: Steroid use for more than 21 days is considered on a case-by-case&#xD;
             basis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Recombinant erythropoietin (rEPO) and granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF) as&#xD;
             medically indicated.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Regularly prescribed medications such as antipyretics, analgesics, allergy&#xD;
             medications, antidepressants, sleep medications, oral contraceptives, megestrol&#xD;
             acetate, testosterone, or any other medications as medically indicated.&#xD;
&#xD;
        [AS PER AMENDMENT 4/25/00:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed with caution:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pentamidine, allopurinol, hydroxyurea. Use of these medications may increase exposure&#xD;
             to ddI.]&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Treatment:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Dependency of less than 3 units of blood per 21-day period.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Alternative therapies such as acupuncture and visualization techniques.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must have:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  HIV infection documented by a licensed ELISA and confirmed by Western blot, positive&#xD;
             HIV culture, positive HIV antigen, positive plasma HIV RNA, or second antibody test&#xD;
             positive by a method other than ELISA. Repeat HIV-antibody testing is not required for&#xD;
             enrollment in this trial (implicit in patients having been enrolled in ACTG 302/303).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Signed, informed consent from parent or legal guardian for patients under 18 years of&#xD;
             age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Co-existing Condition:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with the following conditions or symptoms are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Inability to tolerate ddI at 200-400 mg/day, 3TC at 300 mg/day, or d4T at 60-80&#xD;
             mg/day, with intolerance defined as recurrent toxicities requiring dose interruptions&#xD;
             and reductions or permanent discontinuation of the drugs (other than Grade 3 or 4&#xD;
             anemia).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Grade 2 or higher peripheral neuropathy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Malignancy requiring systemic therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Co-enrollment in other antiretroviral protocols; co-enrollment in other ACTG protocols&#xD;
             is encouraged, particularly those involving prophylaxis for opportunistic infections.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  All antiretroviral therapies other than study medications.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Investigational drugs and vaccines without specific approval from the Protocol&#xD;
             Chair/Vice Chairs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Systemic cytotoxic chemotherapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Interferon, interleukins, GM-CSF, and HIV-1 vaccines.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Rifabutin and rifampin.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ketoconazole, astemizole, cisapride, midazolam, terfenadine, and triazolam.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acute therapy for an infection or other medical illness.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Herbal medications.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Vitamins. [10. AS PER AMENDMENT 3/5/98:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ergot alkaloids or drugs containing derivatives or ergot alkaloids.]&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with the following prior conditions are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of acute or chronic pancreatitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  PIs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  NNRTIs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acute therapy for an infection or other medical illness within 14 days prior to the&#xD;
             time of study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chronic long-term steroid use is not permitted unless it is within physiologic&#xD;
             replacement levels; protocol chair/vice chairs must be contacted in these instances.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Risk Behavior:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current ethanol abuse by personal history or a report from a primary physician.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary Albrecht</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Katzenstein</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott Hammer</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cook County Hosp. CORE Ctr.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush Univ. Med. Ctr. ACTG CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Adult AIDS CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NY Univ. HIV/AIDS CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Puerto Rico-AIDS CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Juan</city>
        <zip>009365067</zip>
        <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Puerto Rico</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albrecht MA, Bosch RJ, Hammer SM, Liou SH, Kessler H, Para MF, Eron J, Valdez H, Dehlinger M, Katzenstein DA; AIDS Clinical Trials Group 364 Study Team. Nelfinavir, efavirenz, or both after the failure of nucleoside treatment of HIV infection. N Engl J Med. 2001 Aug 9;345(6):398-407. doi: 10.1056/NEJM200108093450602.</citation>
    <PMID>11496850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albrecht M, Hammer S, Liou S, Bosch R, Katzenstein D. Long-term virologic and immune responses in subjects maintained on exclusive nucleoside analog (NRTI)based therapy in ACTG 364. 8th Conf Retro and Opportun Infect. 2001 Feb 4-8 (abstract no 322)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katzenstein DA, Bosch RJ, Hellmann N, Wang N, Bacheler L, Albrecht MA; ACTG 364 Study Team. Phenotypic susceptibility and virological outcome in nucleoside-experienced patients receiving three or four antiretroviral drugs. AIDS. 2003 Apr 11;17(6):821-30. doi: 10.1097/00002030-200304110-00007.</citation>
    <PMID>12660529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winters MA, Bosch RJ, Albrecht MA, Katzenstein DA; AIDS Clinical Trials Group 364 Study Team. Clinical impact of the M184V mutation on switching to didanosine or maintaining lamivudine treatment in nucleoside reverse-transcriptase inhibitor-experienced patients. J Infect Dis. 2003 Aug 15;188(4):537-40. doi: 10.1086/377742. Epub 2003 Jul 24.</citation>
    <PMID>12898440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bosch RJ, Downey GF, Katzenstein DA, Hellmann N, Bacheler L, Albrecht MA; ACTG 364 Study Team. Evaluation of cutpoints for phenotypic hypersusceptibility to efavirenz. AIDS. 2003 Nov 7;17(16):2395-6. doi: 10.1097/00002030-200311070-00016. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>14571193</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2021</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 28, 2021</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 28, 2021</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 1, 2021</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy, Combination</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiviral Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Protease Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Ritonavir</keyword>
  <keyword>Saquinavir</keyword>
  <keyword>Nelfinavir</keyword>
  <keyword>Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Adenine</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-HIV Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>efavirenz</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ritonavir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nelfinavir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Saquinavir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lamivudine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Zidovudine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Didanosine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stavudine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Zalcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Efavirenz</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adefovir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adefovir dipivoxil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

