<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005068</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000067673</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA069912</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015083</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>970109</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005068</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination Chemotherapy In Treating Patients With Metastatic or Unresectable Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Oxaliplatin, CPT-11, 5-FU and Leucovorin in Patients With Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so&#xD;
      they stop growing or die. Combining more than one drug may kill more tumor cells.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PURPOSE: Phase I trial to determine the effectiveness of two different regimens of&#xD;
      combination chemotherapy in treating patients who have metastatic or unresectable solid&#xD;
      tumors.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine the maximum tolerated dose of irinotecan, fluorouracil, and&#xD;
      leucovorin calcium (Saltz regimen vs Mayo regimen) plus oxaliplatin (arm I vs arm II) in&#xD;
      patients with metastatic or unresectable solid tumors. II. Determine the effect of irinotecan&#xD;
      on the disposition of oxaliplatin in these patients. III. Assess the development of&#xD;
      peripheral neuropathy in these patients on the Mayo regimen. IV. Determine the activity of&#xD;
      these regimens in patients with metastatic solid tumors.&#xD;
&#xD;
      OUTLINE: This is a dose escalation study. Patients are entered to one of two treatment arms:&#xD;
      Arm I (Saltz regimen): Patients receive irinotecan IV over 90 minutes, leucovorin calcium IV,&#xD;
      and fluorouracil IV on days 1, 8, 15, and 22, followed by oxaliplatin IV over 2 hours on days&#xD;
      1 and 15. Courses repeat every 6 weeks. Arm II (Mayo regimen): Patients receive irinotecan IV&#xD;
      over 90 minutes and oxaliplatin IV over 2 hours on day 1, followed by leucovorin calcium IV&#xD;
      and fluorouracil IV over 90 minutes on days 2-5. Courses repeat every 3 weeks. Cohorts of 3-6&#xD;
      patients receive escalating doses of fluorouracil (one of two treatment doses for arm II),&#xD;
      and one of two treatment doses of irinotecan and oxaliplatin until the maximum tolerated dose&#xD;
      (MTD) is determined. The MTD is defined as the dose preceding that at which 2 of 6 patients&#xD;
      experience dose limiting toxicity. Patients are followed for 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: Up to 60 patients will be accrued for this study within 8-14 months.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2003</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2003</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Unspecified Adult Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorouracil</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>irinotecan hydrochloride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>leucovorin calcium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>oxaliplatin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically proven metastatic or unresectable solid tumor for&#xD;
        which no standard or curative therapy exists No CNS metastases&#xD;
&#xD;
        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Performance status: ECOG 0-2 Life expectancy: At&#xD;
        least 12 weeks Hematopoietic: Absolute neutrophil count at least 1,500/mm3 Platelet count&#xD;
        at least 100,000/mm3 Hepatic: Bilirubin no greater than 1.5 times upper limit of normal&#xD;
        (ULN) AST no greater than 5 times ULN Renal: Creatinine normal OR Creatinine clearance at&#xD;
        least 60 mL/min Cardiovascular: No symptomatic congestive heart failure No unstable angina&#xD;
        pectoris No cardiac arrhythmias No New York Heart Association class III or IV heart disease&#xD;
        Neurologic: No peripheral neuropathy grade 2 or greater No uncontrolled seizure disorders&#xD;
        Other: Not pregnant or nursing Fertile patients must use effective contraception No&#xD;
        uncontrolled concurrent illness No active infection No history of allergy to platinum&#xD;
        compounds, irinotecan, antiemetics, or antidiarrheals&#xD;
&#xD;
        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: At least 4 weeks since prior immunotherapy At&#xD;
        least 4 weeks since prior biologic therapy No concurrent immunotherapy Chemotherapy: At&#xD;
        least 4 weeks since prior chemotherapy (6 weeks since nitrosoureas or mitomycin) and&#xD;
        recovered No greater than 3 prior chemotherapy regimens for metastatic disease No other&#xD;
        concurrent chemotherapy Endocrine therapy: Not specified Radiotherapy: No prior pelvic&#xD;
        radiotherapy At least 4 weeks since other prior radiotherapy No prior radiotherapy to&#xD;
        greater than 25% of bone marrow No concurrent radiotherapy Surgery: Not specified Other: No&#xD;
        concurrent antiretroviral therapy for HIV positive patients&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard M. Goldberg, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Goetz MP, Erlichman C, Windebank AJ, Reid JM, Sloan JA, Atherton P, Adjei AA, Rubin J, Pitot H, Galanis E, Ames MM, Goldberg RM. Phase I and pharmacokinetic study of two different schedules of oxaliplatin, irinotecan, Fluorouracil, and leucovorin in patients with solid tumors. J Clin Oncol. 2003 Oct 15;21(20):3761-9. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2003.01.238. Epub 2003 Sep 8.</citation>
    <PMID>12963697</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2011</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 6, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 2, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 2, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 2, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 3, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Richard M. Goldberg, M.D.</name_title>
    <organization>Mayo Clinic Cancer Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Calcium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

