<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00006425</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>010008</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>01-C-0008</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00006425</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00012402</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Breast Imaging Studies in Women at High Genetic Risk of Breast Cancer: Menstrual Cycle Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Breast Imaging Studies in Women at High Genetic Risk of Breast Cancer: Menstrual Cycle Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Women who carrying a BRCA1 or BRCA2 gene mutation or who are the first- or second-degree&#xD;
      relative of an individual with a BRCA-associated cancer in a family documented to have a&#xD;
      BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation will be eligible for enrollment into this pilot study of breast&#xD;
      cancer screening modalities. We will recruit up to fifty women (twenty-five women who carry&#xD;
      an altered BRCA1 or BRCA2 gene and 25 non-carriers matched by age and family mutation type)&#xD;
      with regular menstrual cycling (documented by menstrual history and premenopausal FSH level).&#xD;
      A physical exam including exam of the breast and pelvis, a standard four view mammogram,&#xD;
      breast MRI and PET scan will be scheduled initially during either the follicular or&#xD;
      mid-luteal phase of the menstrual cycle. A unilateral cranio-caudal mammogram, and bilateral&#xD;
      MRI and PET scan will be repeated three months after entry during the phase not initially&#xD;
      studied. A CA125 and transvaginal color doppler ultrasonography will be done in the&#xD;
      follicular phase. Carriers and non-carriers will be compared with respect to menstrual cycle&#xD;
      differences in: (1) two measures of mammographic density (qualitative and semiquantitative);&#xD;
      (2) a semiquantitative measure of fibroglandular volume (MRI); (3) a semiquantitative measure&#xD;
      of contrast enhancement (MRI); and (4) FDG uptake measured over time (PET scan). On the&#xD;
      initial and three-month visit, all participants will undergo breast duct lavage to&#xD;
      investigate if there are consistent menstrual cycle differences in breast ductal cytologies.&#xD;
      Participants will be seen annually thereafter for an additional three years of follow-up. A&#xD;
      physical exam, standard four-view mammography, breast MRI, CA 125, transvaginal color doppler&#xD;
      ultrasonography and breast duct lavage will be done annually. Consent for a PET study will be&#xD;
      requested if an abnormality is detected on mammography or breast MRI requiring additional&#xD;
      clinical or radiographic follow-up.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants in the Menstrual Cycle Pilot Study, will complete a self-administered&#xD;
      questionnaire and telephone interview and will complete periodic follow-up questionnaires to&#xD;
      assess various behavioral and psychosocial endpoints.&#xD;
&#xD;
      As part of the Menstrual Cycle Pilot Study, we will recruit 25 volunteers to assist in&#xD;
      training study investigators in performing breast duct lavage. Cytologies obtained from&#xD;
      volunteers will be used to develop oncogene probe panels to be used in the study.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Asymptomatic, premenopausal women are (1) known carriers of an altered BRCA1 or BRCA2 gene,&#xD;
      or (2) first- or second-degree relatives of individuals with a BRCA-associated cancer in a&#xD;
      family documented to have a BRCA1 or BRCA2 gene mutation will be eligible for inclusion in&#xD;
      this pilot study to assess new approaches to early detection of breast and ovarian cancer in&#xD;
      high-risk women. We will recruit up to fifty women (twenty-five women who carry an altered&#xD;
      BRCA1 or BRCA2 gene and 25 non-carriers matched by age and family mutation type) with regular&#xD;
      menstrual cycling (documented by menstrual history and premenopausal FSH level). A physical&#xD;
      exam including exam of the breast and pelvis, a standard four view mammogram and breast MRI&#xD;
      will be scheduled initially during either the follicular or mid-luteal phase of the menstrual&#xD;
      cycle. A unilateral cranio-caudal mammogram and bilateral MRI will be repeated three months&#xD;
      after entry during the phase not initially studied. A CA125 and transvaginal color doppler&#xD;
      ultrasonography will be done in the follicular phase. Carriers and non-carriers will be&#xD;
      compared with respect to menstrual cycle differences in: (1) two measures of mammographic&#xD;
      density (qualitative and semiquantitative); (2) a semiquantitative measure of fibroglandular&#xD;
      volume (MRI); and (3) a semiquantitative measure of contrast enhancement (MRI). On the&#xD;
      initial and three-month visit, all participants will undergo breast duct lavage to&#xD;
      investigate if there are consistent menstrual cycle differences in breast ductal cytologies.&#xD;
      Participants will be seen annually thereafter for an additional three years of follow-up. A&#xD;
      physical exam, standard four-view mammography, breast MRI, CA 125, transvaginal color doppler&#xD;
      ultrasonography and breast duct lavage will be done annually.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants in the Menstrual Cycle Pilot Study, will complete a self-administered&#xD;
      questionnaire and telephone interview and will complete periodic follow-up questionnaires to&#xD;
      assess various behavioral and psychosocial endpoints.&#xD;
&#xD;
      As part of the Menstrual Cycle Pilot Study, we will recruit 25 volunteers to assist in&#xD;
      training study investigators in performing breast duct lavage. Cytologies obtained from&#xD;
      volunteers will be used to develop oncogene probe panels to be used in the study.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 19, 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 3, 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the effect of menstrual cycle phase on five breast imaging outcome measures.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of study</time_frame>
    <description>These are: 2 measures of mammographic density (qualitative and semiquantitative), a semiquantitative measure of fibroglandular volume and of dynamic contrast enhancement (MRI), and FDG uptake over time (PET scan). We will determine if these measures vary between the carriers &amp;amp; non carriers of BRCA1/2 mutations.Due to the difficulty in tracking and timing menstrual cycles in women who resided great distances from the NIH, we abandoned further recruitment after the pilot study of ductal lavage.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>25 women undergoing ductal lavage</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        As part of the Menstrual Cycle Pilot Study, we recruited 25 volunteers to assist in&#xD;
        training study investigators in performing breast duct lavage. Cytologies obtained from&#xD;
        volunteers were used to develop expertise in interpretation and management of women&#xD;
        undergoing ductal lavage.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Inclusion Criteria - Menstrual Cycle Study:&#xD;
&#xD;
        To participate in the Menstrual Cycle Pilot Study, a woman must:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must be at least 25 years of age (or 5 years younger than the age at diagnosis of the&#xD;
        youngest family member with a tumor associated with the Breast-Ovarian Cancer Syndrome) and&#xD;
        less than 46 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must be premenopausal as determined by menstrual history (no change in menstrual pattern in&#xD;
        prior 6 months) and an FSH level less than 15 mIU/ml obtained on the third day of the&#xD;
        menstrual cycle.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Have undergone genetic counseling and risk assessment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must be a known mutation carrier or be a first- or second-degree relative of an individual&#xD;
        with a tumor associated with the Breast-Ovarian Cancer Syndrome in a family with a known&#xD;
        BRCA mutation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Agree to release of genetic test result for stratification purposes, whether or not she has&#xD;
        chosen to receive individual test results for clinical decision-making.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Be willing to use non-hormonal methods of contraception until completion of the 3 month&#xD;
        follow-up studies.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Have an ECOG performance status of 0-1.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Be able to provide informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria - Menstrual Cycle Study:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Any of the following will result in exclusion from the Menstrual Cycle Pilot Study:&#xD;
&#xD;
        A history of menstrual cycle irregularities over the previous 6 months, including history&#xD;
        of cycles less than 26 days or more than 35 days.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Steroid therapy, use of selective estrogen receptor modulators (SERMs) or hormonal agents&#xD;
        (including tamoxifen, raloxifene, estrogen, DHEA, anabolic steroids, oral contraceptives,&#xD;
        depoprovera, progestin IUD, oral progestins, norplant, or drugs to induce ovulation) within&#xD;
        6 months prior to study entry and must agree not to use these compounds until completion of&#xD;
        the three-month follow-up study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnancy or lactation within 12 months of enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of infertility with a suspected ovarian etiology or persistent ovarian cyst.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Abnormal CA-125 level.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of invasive cancer except for non-melanoma skin cancer or cervical carcinoma in&#xD;
        situ.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Creatinine greater than 2.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Previous bilateral mastectomy, bilateral radiation therapy to the breast, or oophorectomy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of DCIS or LCIS .&#xD;
&#xD;
        Weight over 136 kilograms.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allergy to gadolinium.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allergy to lidocaine or Marcaine (bupivacaine) (excluded from breast duct lavage only).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Medical or psychiatric disorder which, in the opinion of the Principal Investigator, would&#xD;
        preclude informed consent or ability to participate in clinical research.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Inclusion Criteria - Training Cohort:&#xD;
&#xD;
        To participate in the Training Cohort a volunteer must:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Be female and at least 18 years and less than 51 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have at least one breast considered eligible for study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Provide evidence (either films or radiologist's report) of a mammogram done within the&#xD;
             12 months prior to enrollment showing low or no suspicion of carcinoma in at least one&#xD;
             breast. (Mammograms will not be provided to participants as part of the training&#xD;
             cohort.)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a physical examination of the breast to be studied consistent with low or no&#xD;
             suspicion of carcinoma at the time of enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Provide the name of a primary care physician to whom the results of breast duct lavage&#xD;
             cytologies can be sent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have signed the informed consent for breast duct lavage.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria - Training Cohort:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Any of the following will exclude a potential participant from the Training Cohort:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnancy or lactation within the past 12 prior to enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subareolar or other surgery of the breast to be studied (papilloma resection, biopsy&#xD;
             or fine needle aspirations which might disrupt the ductal systems within 2 cm of the&#xD;
             nipple. (Biopsies of fine needle aspirations of the breast greater than or equal to 2&#xD;
             cm from the nipple are acceptable.)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A breast implant or prior silicone injections in the breast to be studied.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Radiation therapy to a breast to be studied.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active infections or inflammation in a breast to be studied.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chemotherapy or a selective estrogen receptor modifier (e.g., tamoxifen or raloxifen)&#xD;
             taken within 12 months prior to enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A known allergy to lidocaine, prilocaine or Marcaine (bupivacaine).&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer T Loud, C.R.N.P.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2001-C-0008.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 31, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 31, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 1, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Ductal lavage</keyword>
  <keyword>Nipple Aspirate Fluid</keyword>
  <keyword>Transvaginal ultrasound</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

