<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00006091</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000068094</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MDA-DM-00058</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-311</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ID00-058</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00006091</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Arsenic Trioxide in Treating Patients With Chronic Phase Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia That Has Not Responded to Previous Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Arsenic Trioxide Therapy for Interferon Alpha Refractory or Intolerant Chronic Phase Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop cancer cells from dividing&#xD;
      so they stop growing or die.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PURPOSE: Phase II trial to study the effectiveness of arsenic trioxide in treating patients&#xD;
      who have chronic phase chronic myelogenous leukemia that has not responded to previous&#xD;
      treatment.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:&#xD;
&#xD;
      I. Determine the rate of complete or major cytogenetic response to arsenic trioxide as&#xD;
      demonstrated by a decrease in the percentage of Philadelphia chromosome positive (or&#xD;
      breakpoint cluster region bcr positive) cells in the bone marrow in patients with interferon&#xD;
      alfa refractory or intolerant chronic phase chronic myelogenous leukemia.&#xD;
&#xD;
      II. Determine the rate and duration of complete hematological response to this treatment in&#xD;
      these patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      III. Determine the duration of complete and major cytogenetic response to this treatment in&#xD;
      these patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      IV. Determine the pattern of clinical adverse experience and improvement in symptomatic&#xD;
      parameters with this treatment in these patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      V. Determine the time to accelerated disease or blast crisis and overall survival in these&#xD;
      patients after receiving this treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      VI. Determine the effects of this treatment on cytokines, apoptosis, and angiogenesis in&#xD;
      these patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      OUTLINE: Patients receive arsenic trioxide intravenous (IV) over 2 hours either daily for 15&#xD;
      consecutive days or 5 days on, 2 days off for a total of 15 doses. Treatment repeats every&#xD;
      2-5 weeks after the previous course for a maximum of 12 courses in the absence of disease&#xD;
      progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving complete remission are followed&#xD;
      every month for 3 months, every 2 months for 6 months, every 3-4 months for 1 year, and then&#xD;
      every 6 months thereafter. All other patients are followed every 3 months for 1 year and then&#xD;
      annually thereafter.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 17-53 patients will be accrued for this study within 2.5 years.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    No enrollment.&#xD;
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 19, 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2002</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2002</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>arsenic trioxide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diagnosis of Philadelphia (Ph) chromosome positive (or breakpoint cluster region bcr&#xD;
             positive) chronic myelogenous leukemia in chronic phase&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ineligible for or refused allogeneic bone marrow transplantation&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Interferon alfa refractory or intolerant as defined by the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Refractory: Failure to achieve a complete hematologic response lasting for at least 1&#xD;
             month after prior therapy with interferon alfa based regimen for at least 3 months 65%&#xD;
             or more Ph positive chromosomes in bone marrow after one year of interferon alfa based&#xD;
             therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  At least a 30% increase in Ph positive chromosomes in bone marrow in samples taken at&#xD;
             least one month apart OR&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  An increase of at least 65% in Ph positive chromosomes in bone marrow&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Intolerant: Grade 3 or greater nonhematologic toxicity Autoimmune phenomenon at any&#xD;
             grade&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No accelerated phase or blastic phase disease as defined by the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Greater than 15% blasts or basophils in the peripheral blood or bone marrow&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Greater than 30% blasts plus promyelocytes in the peripheral blood or bone marrow&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Documented extramedullary blastic disease outside liver or spleen&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Platelet count less than 100,000/mm3 unrelated to therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Clonal evolution (additional chromosomal abnormalities other than Ph chromosome) as&#xD;
             solitary feature is not considered accelerated disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No known brain metastases or central nervous system (CNS) disease&#xD;
&#xD;
        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age: 12 and over&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Performance status: Zubrod 0-2&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Life expectancy: At least 2 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hematopoietic: See Disease Characteristics&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hepatic: Unless due to direct disease infiltration of the liver:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ALT and AST no greater than 2.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Bilirubin no greater than 1.5 times ULN (unless due to Gilbert's disease)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No hepatic disease that would preclude study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Renal: Creatinine no greater than 1.5 times ULN Creatinine clearance at least 60&#xD;
             mL/min&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cardiovascular: No history of New York Heart Association grade III or IV cardiac&#xD;
             disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No cardiovascular disease that would preclude study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No unstable angina pectoris or cardiac arrhythmia that would shorten life expectancy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other: No history of grand mal seizures other than infantile febrile seizures&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No active secondary malignancy or other uncontrolled concurrent medical problem that&#xD;
             would shorten life expectancy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No neurologic, endocrine, or other major systemic disease that would preclude study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No active infection uncontrolled by oral or IV antibiotics&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No history of hypersensitivity to the study drug or drugs with similar chemical&#xD;
             structure&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No mental condition that would preclude study Not pregnant or nursing&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Negative pregnancy test&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Fertile patients must use effective contraception&#xD;
&#xD;
        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Biologic therapy: See Disease Characteristics&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No concurrent bone marrow or peripheral blood stem cell transplantation&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chemotherapy: At least 14 days since prior chemotherapy (48 hours for hydroxyurea and&#xD;
             6 weeks for busulfan) and recovered (unless evidence of rapidly progressive disease)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No other concurrent cytotoxic chemotherapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No prior arsenic trioxide&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Endocrine therapy: No concurrent steroids for the treatment of neoplasms (except for&#xD;
             new adrenal failures)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No concurrent hormones for the treatment of neoplasms (except for nondisease related&#xD;
             conditions)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Radiotherapy: At least 14 days since prior radiotherapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No concurrent radiotherapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Surgery: Not specified&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other: At least 14 days since other prior investigational agent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No other concurrent investigational or antileukemic agents&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Deborah A. Thomas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 3, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 15, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 16, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>relapsing chronic myelogenous leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic phase chronic myelogenous leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic myelogenous leukemia, BCR-ABL1 positive</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Chronic-Phase</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arsenic Trioxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

