<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001952</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000017</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-D-0017</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001952</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using a Narcotic to Enhance the Numbing Effect of the Local Anesthetic Lidocaine on Inflamed Molar Teeth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analgesic Effects of Peripherally Administered Opioids in a Clinical Model of Chronic Inflammation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The effectiveness of local anesthetics is reduced if inflammation is present, making it&#xD;
      difficult to control pain during such procedures as root canals and wisdom teeth removal.&#xD;
      This set of studies will assess the effectiveness of the opioid (synthetic narcotic) fentanyl&#xD;
      in enhancing the local anesthetic lidocaine (delivered with epinephrine) when used on&#xD;
      inflamed molar teeth.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the first study, a topical anesthetic patch or a placebo will be placed on the gum tissues&#xD;
      next to four or five lower posterior teeth. The patch will removed at either 5, 10, or 15&#xD;
      minutes. An electronic test that sends a light electronic impulse into the tooth, lip&#xD;
      sensitivity testing (&quot;Is your lip numb?&quot;), and discomfort reports will be started immediately&#xD;
      after removal of the patch and repeated every 5 minutes for 30 minutes. An oral surgeon will&#xD;
      then remove the patient's wisdom teeth (tooth).&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the second and third studies, a topical anesthetic will be placed on the gum tissue. An&#xD;
      electronic test that sends a light electronic impulse into the tooth, lip sensitivity testing&#xD;
      (&quot;Is your lip numb?&quot;), and discomfort reports will be started and done several times&#xD;
      throughout the test. Then two small openings, one on each side of the tooth, will be drilled&#xD;
      into the bony tissues surrounding the tooth. A narcotic drug fentanyl or a placebo drug will&#xD;
      be delivered through these openings, allowing placement of the drug next to the nerves that&#xD;
      are difficult to numb. Lidocaine, along with a small amount of epinephrine, will be&#xD;
      delivered. An oral surgeon will then remove the patient's wisdom teeth or tooth (study 2) or&#xD;
      do a root canal (study 3).&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the fourth study, a topical anesthetic will be placed on the gum tissue. Then two small&#xD;
      openings, one on each side of the tooth, will be drilled into the bony tissues surrounding&#xD;
      the tooth. A narcotic drug fentanyl or a placebo drug will be delivered through these&#xD;
      openings. Lidocaine, along with a small amount of epinephrine, will be delivered at one of&#xD;
      three rates (15 patients for each rate). Blood pressure, heart rate, and breathing rate will&#xD;
      be taken before the topical anesthetic patch is applied, 2 minutes after, and every 5 minutes&#xD;
      for the next 45 minutes. Blood samples will be taken 6 times over the course of 60 minutes.&#xD;
      When testing is complete, an oral surgeon will remove the wisdom teeth (tooth). One month&#xD;
      later, blood samples will be taken using a different drug delivery method in order to compare&#xD;
      results.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The clinical efficacy of local anesthetics is reduced in the presence of inflammation,&#xD;
      sometimes limiting the ability to perform necessary therapeutic procedures. Recent studies&#xD;
      suggest, however, that opiate receptors are expressed in the dental pulp and oral mucosal&#xD;
      tissues and increase in number under conditions of inflammation. The proposed clinical study&#xD;
      will assess the therapeutic effectiveness of the opioid, fentanyl, to enhance the&#xD;
      profoundness of the local anesthetic lidocaine with 1:100,000 epinephrine when used on&#xD;
      inflamed mandibular molar teeth. Delivering lidocaine 2% with 1:100,000 epinephrine&#xD;
      intraosseously immediately after delivering fentanyl intraosseously is predicted to increase&#xD;
      the success rate of local anesthesia on the inflamed pulpal tissues of mandibular molars.&#xD;
      Three different strategies will be studied to assess fentanyl as an adjunct to local&#xD;
      anesthesia. The first study will assess the efficacy of individual drugs under normal&#xD;
      conditions in patients whose mandibular molars have healthy pulpal tissues. Pulpal anesthesia&#xD;
      will be measured by an electronic pulp tester and drugs will be delivered intraosseously. A&#xD;
      second study will evaluate local anesthetic success using the same drugs and route of&#xD;
      administration in patients whose mandibular molars have inflamed pulpal tissues. Root canal&#xD;
      treatment will test for the clinical effectiveness of local anesthesia. A third study will&#xD;
      assess systemic side effects using different rates of intraosseous drug delivery. This series&#xD;
      of studies may provide a rationale for the adjunctive administration of opioids in clinical&#xD;
      conditions where inflammation limits the effectiveness of local anesthetics alone.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2002</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>275</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <condition>Mouth Disease</condition>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women whose mandibular molars are either: intact, caries-free, and have no signs or&#xD;
        symptoms of pulpal disease or carious, symptomatic (to hot/cold and percussion), but have&#xD;
        no evidence of pulpal necrosis or infection. At least one intact caries-free contralateral&#xD;
        mandibular molar must be present.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Individuals should be healthy and over the age of 16.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No history of stomach ulcers, asthma, lung problems, or allergy to lidocaine, fentanyl or&#xD;
        any of the standard or test medications.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No body weight which is 30% greater or less than standard height-weight tables.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No pregnant or lactating females. Also, no females who are sexually active and will not&#xD;
        submit to a pregnancy test.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No history of taking any analgesics or antihistamines for 24 hr period prior to study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients taking steroids or other anti-inflammatory drugs.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Willing to accept root canal treatment without parenteral sedation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Willing to participate in data collection procedures.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No clinically significant medical history or signs of debilitation including patients with&#xD;
        heart, respiratory, renal, or liver dysfunction.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No history of personality disorder, alcohol abuse or drug abuse.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No chronic use of drugs which would confound assessment including barbituates,&#xD;
        anticonvulsants, tranquilizers, antiarrythmics, beta blockers, and antidepressants.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients whose mandibular molars are heavily restored (i.e., crowns, large fillings).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No hypersensitivity to drugs used (epinephrine, lidocaine, fentanyl).&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Dental And Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aberg G. Studies on the duration of local anesthesia: a possible mechanism for the prolonging effect of &quot;vasoconstrictors&quot; on the duration of infiltration anesthesia. Int J Oral Surg. 1980 Apr;9(2):144-7. doi: 10.1016/s0300-9785(80)80051-2.</citation>
    <PMID>6773898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andreev N, Urban L, Dray A. Opioids suppress spontaneous activity of polymodal nociceptors in rat paw skin induced by ultraviolet irradiation. Neuroscience. 1994 Feb;58(4):793-8. doi: 10.1016/0306-4522(94)90456-1.</citation>
    <PMID>8190256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dionne RA, Gordon SM, McCullagh LM, Phero JC. Assessing the need for anesthesia and sedation in the general population. J Am Dent Assoc. 1998 Feb;129(2):167-73. doi: 10.14219/jada.archive.1998.0173.</citation>
    <PMID>9495047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2002</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 19, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Fentanyl</keyword>
  <keyword>Intraosseous-Anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Endodontics</keyword>
  <keyword>Denti Patch</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Inflammation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mouth Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

