<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005902</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000140</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-N-0140</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005902</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Brain and Spinal Cord Tumor Growth and Cyst Development in Patients With Von Hippel Lindau Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Natural History Study of VHL Patients With CNS Hemangioblastomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to learn more about the growth of brain and spinal cord tumors&#xD;
      and cysts that develop in association with them in patients with von Hippel-Lindau disease.&#xD;
      It will examine how fast the tumors grow and try to determine what factors (for example,&#xD;
      puberty , pregnancy, menopause, blood proteins, etc.) affect their growth.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients between the ages of 8 and 75 years who are enrolled in NIH s study of von&#xD;
      Hippel-Lindau disease may be eligible for this 5-year study. Participants will have magnetic&#xD;
      resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain and spinal cord and a thorough neurological history and&#xD;
      examination at the start of the study. A blood sample will be taken for analysis of factors&#xD;
      (hormones or other proteins) that may predict tumor growth. Follow-up clinic visits every 6&#xD;
      months will include a physical and neurological examination, blood tests, and MRI scans of&#xD;
      the brain and spine. If symptoms or tumor growth requires more frequent follow-up, scans will&#xD;
      be done at 3-month intervals.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Surgical removal of brain and spinal cord tumors is currently the treatment of choice when&#xD;
      these lesions cause neurological problems. A better understanding of which tumors are likely&#xD;
      to grow and which will remain stable may help guide physicians in treatment decisions and&#xD;
      avoid unnecessary procedures.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hemangioblastomas of the cerebellum, brainstem and spinal cord are frequent tumors in&#xD;
      patients with von Hippel-Lindau (VHL) disease. Rarely, these lesions also affect the&#xD;
      cerebrum. Patients often have multiple lesions, many of which are associated with cysts or&#xD;
      syrinx. The current treatment for symptomatic lesions is surgical resection. Focused&#xD;
      radiation is also being used in selected cases in an attempt to provide tumor control. The&#xD;
      natural history of central nervous system (CNS) lesions in patients with VHL has not been&#xD;
      addressed in a prospective study. It is not clear at which point these lesions will begin to&#xD;
      grow, or develop cysts in the cerebellum or syrinx in the spinal cord, and systemic factors&#xD;
      that influence tumor growth have not been identified. By identifying factors that predict or&#xD;
      influence tumor progression or cyst development, we can more accurately recommend surgical or&#xD;
      medical intervention at appropriate times and avoid unnecessary treatment for stable lesions.&#xD;
      This study will collect prospective radiological and clinical data on growth of the central&#xD;
      nervous system (CNS) hemangioblastomas and associated cysts. We will also prospectively&#xD;
      collect information on systemic processes that may influence tumor progression, such as&#xD;
      puberty, menopause, pregnancy, effects of hormone therapy, tumor load, serum erythropoeitin&#xD;
      level and hemoglobin/hematocrit levels.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This natural history study has resulted in significant improvement in our understanding of&#xD;
      the pathophysiology of VHL disease. Data from this study have resulted in a better&#xD;
      understanding of the origin and growth patterns of hemangioblastomas, and endolymphatic sac&#xD;
      tumors in patients with VHL disease. New therapies targeting hemangioblastomas in VHL disease&#xD;
      are being devised based on information gathered from this study. We expect this natural&#xD;
      history disease to continue to inspire new hypothesis driven studies while improving the&#xD;
      understanding and management of hemangioblastomas in VHL disease.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 15, 2001</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the course of clinical and radiographic progression of VHL</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12-24 month intervals</time_frame>
    <description>The questions to be answered fall in the following general categories: 1. Course of Clinical Progression 2. Radiographic Progression 3. Post-treatment outcome (surgery and radiation) 4. Contributing factors 5. Genetic variability and effects on disease progression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the course of tumor and cyst growth after surgical and/or radiation intervention.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 24 months after surgery until withdrawal or death</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemangioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Hippel Lindau Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>250 subjects with von Hippel-Lindau (VHL) disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This study will enroll 250 subjects with von Hippel-Lindau (VHL) disease.&#xD;
        Withdrawal/dropouts will not be replaced.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Ages 8-75.&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Confirmed diagnosis of von Hippel-Lindau disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Presence of one or more cerebral, cerebellar or spinal cord hemangioblastomas on&#xD;
                  screening MRI.&#xD;
&#xD;
               4. Able to give informed consent (or assent), or have a parent able to provide&#xD;
                  informed consent if a child.&#xD;
&#xD;
               5. Karnofsky Performance Scale Score greater than or equal to 60.&#xD;
&#xD;
               6. Have the capacity to undergo serial MRI scanning of the CNS without IV sedation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Clinically unstable condition.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Being treated by any chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or steroids.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Allergy to CT or MRI contrast agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Contraindication to MRI scanning such as surgery that involves metal clips or wires&#xD;
             which might be expected to cause tissue damage or produce image artifacts.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prashant Chittiboina, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2000-N-0140.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 18, 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brain</keyword>
  <keyword>Brainstem</keyword>
  <keyword>Cysts</keyword>
  <keyword>Spinal Cord</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI (Magnetic Resonance Imaging)</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemangioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Von Hippel-Lindau Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>.We do plan to share IPD. we will share all IPD that results in a publication on a public repository, as required by most journals. the data will be de-identified and anonymized.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

