<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001551</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>960088</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>96-N-0088</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001551</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characteristics of Idiopathic Familial Speech Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Characteristics of Idiopathic Familial Speech Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      According to studies, speech disorders with unknown causes (idiopathic) affect approximately&#xD;
      5% of the population at some point in their life. Some of these disorders like, stuttering&#xD;
      and cluttering, are known for being detected early, during speech development.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Stuttering is characterized by sound and syllable repetitions and consonant/vowel&#xD;
      prolongations. When stuttering is moderate to severe, it can interfere with a person's job&#xD;
      and social activities.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Speech articulation disorders are characterized by omissions, or substitutions of speech&#xD;
      sounds. The speech of a person who clutters is often difficult to understand. People are&#xD;
      often unaware of the errors they make when speaking causing treatment of the condition to be&#xD;
      very difficult.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The purpose of this research is to study an extended family whose members exhibit a pure form&#xD;
      of speech articulation disorders&#xD;
&#xD;
      In addition, the study will use data and information gathered from the study and use it to&#xD;
      develop guidelines (criteria) for defining and differentiating patients with speech&#xD;
      disorders.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Our objective is to determine which factors are involved in the development of stuttering and&#xD;
      familial phonological processing disorder and are associated with a familial pattern of&#xD;
      inheritance.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study population: The study population is comprised of 8 groups:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Children and adults with persistent developmental stuttering;&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Unaffected siblings of the individuals affected with developmental stuttering or&#xD;
           recovered from stuttering&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Children and adults who have recovered from developmental stuttering;&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. Children and adults with persistent familial phonological processing disorders (FPPD);&#xD;
&#xD;
        5. Unaffected siblings of the individuals affected with FPPD or have recovered from FPPD&#xD;
&#xD;
        6. Children and adults who have recovered from FPPD;&#xD;
&#xD;
        7. Unaffected siblings of the individuals who have recovered from FPPD;&#xD;
&#xD;
        8. Children and adults with normal speech and language development who will comprise the&#xD;
           control groups.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Design: A Natural history design will be used to compare affected and unaffected family&#xD;
      members with healthy volunteers with normal speech and language.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Outcome Measures: Genetic markers and pedigree analyses will be used to test familial&#xD;
      inheritance patterns. Speech and language development will be compared using indices of&#xD;
      speech perception, auditory perception, self monitoring of one's own speech, language&#xD;
      complexity, motor complexity, speech learning, phonological processing and verbal/nonverbal&#xD;
      memory.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 22, 1996</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 13, 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>375</enrollment>
  <condition>Developmental Articulation Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Speech Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Stuttering</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        i. Normal Language Development, Hearing and Cognition&#xD;
&#xD;
        ii. The following screening tests previously published with norms were found to have a good&#xD;
        distribution for determining normal functioning in adolescents and adults as all subjects&#xD;
        did not hit ceiling and all had scores greater than or equal to the 80th percentile. These&#xD;
        tests are being used to ensure that subjects affected with stuttering or FPPD do not have&#xD;
        other disorders such as hearing loss, language delay, or mental retardation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test III (PPVT-III)&#xD;
&#xD;
        Expressive Vocabulary Test (EVT)&#xD;
&#xD;
        Oral Speech Mechanism Screening Examination&#xD;
&#xD;
        Revised Token Test; Token test for Children&#xD;
&#xD;
        Test of Non verbal intelligence (TONI-2)&#xD;
&#xD;
        Digit Span subtest of the WICS-R&#xD;
&#xD;
        Audiometric Screening&#xD;
&#xD;
        Goldman Fristoe Test of Articulation&#xD;
&#xD;
        WUG Test of Morphological Encoding&#xD;
&#xD;
        Test of Auditory Comprehension of Language (TACL)&#xD;
&#xD;
        Khan-Lewis Phonological Analysis&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA FOR IDENTIFYING AND QUANTIFYING STUTTERING:&#xD;
&#xD;
        The Stuttering Severity Index -3 (Riley, 1981) has been found to be accurate for&#xD;
        identifying and assessing the severity of stuttering during conversational speech. For the&#xD;
        inclusion of a stuttering subject we require:&#xD;
&#xD;
        i. A total overall score of 11 or greater between 3 and 17 years,&#xD;
&#xD;
        ii. A total overall score of 18 or greater from age 18 and above.&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA FOR IDENTIFYING FPPD:&#xD;
&#xD;
        i. A family history of an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance of the speech disorder&#xD;
        over several generations with persistence into adulthood in some cases,&#xD;
&#xD;
        ii. Speech symptoms during conversational speech include: deletion of final consonants;&#xD;
        syllable reduction and syllable deletion; deletion of grammatical markers such as copulas,&#xD;
        auxiliaries, prepositions, connectives; poor ability to self-correct; poor awareness of&#xD;
        errors; and consonant cluster reduction.&#xD;
&#xD;
        iii. Greater than 9% discourse errors during analysis of a sample of 300 syllables.&#xD;
&#xD;
        iv. A discrepancy of 30 points (1 and 1/2 Standard Deviations) between receptive (the&#xD;
        higher score) and expressive percentile score on the PPVT III and Expressive Vocabulary&#xD;
        Test.&#xD;
&#xD;
        v. For subjects greater than 7 years of age, a phonological process rating of 3 or more for&#xD;
        any phonological process on the Khan-Lewis Phonological Analysis. For subjects less than 7&#xD;
        years of age, a phonological process rating of 3 or more on 2 phonological processes on the&#xD;
        Khan-Lewis Phonological Analysis. Finally, any subjects with a non developmental&#xD;
        phonological process error will be identified as potentially having FPPD.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        i. Anyone with a hearing loss will be excluded from participation during the diagnostic&#xD;
        testing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        ii. Children with delayed language, more than 1 year delay from norms on receptive and&#xD;
        expression language testing will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        iii. Language impairment: scores more than 2 standard deviations below the age appropriate&#xD;
        score on the standardized language tests listed under the inclusion criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
        iv. Cognitive impairment: scores more than 2 standard deviations below the age appropriate&#xD;
        score on the standardized cognitive tests listed under the inclusion criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
        v. Bilingual non-native English speakers - Studies have demonstrated that brain&#xD;
        organization for speech and language may differ in bilingual persons. It is hypothesized&#xD;
        that this may alter speech motor learning and thus kinematic data from non-native English&#xD;
        speakers would differ from native English speakers. Therefore, only native-American English&#xD;
        speakers, with only one language spoken in the home, will be included.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland, College Park</name>
      <address>
        <city>College Park</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plomin R, Owen MJ, McGuffin P. The genetic basis of complex human behaviors. Science. 1994 Jun 17;264(5166):1733-9. doi: 10.1126/science.8209254.</citation>
    <PMID>8209254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cox NJ, Seider RA, Kidd KK. Some environmental factors and hypotheses for stuttering in families with several stutterers. J Speech Hear Res. 1984 Dec;27(4):543-8. doi: 10.1044/jshr.2704.543.</citation>
    <PMID>6521460</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Felsenfeld S, McGue M, Broen PA. Familial aggregation of phonological disorders: results from a 28-year follow-up. J Speech Hear Res. 1995 Oct;38(5):1091-107. doi: 10.1044/jshr.3805.1091.</citation>
    <PMID>8558878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 13, 2009</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Stuttering</keyword>
  <keyword>Linkage</keyword>
  <keyword>Pedigree</keyword>
  <keyword>Speech Articulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Phonological Processing Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Speech Disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stuttering</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Speech Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Articulation Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

