<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00002221</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY 2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00002221</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gene Therapy in HIV-Positive Patients With Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>High Dose Chemotherapy and Autologous Peripheral Stem Cell Transplantation for HIV Lymphomas: A Phase IIA Study of Comparative Marking Using a Ribozyme Gene and a Neutral Gene</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ribozyome</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NIH AIDS Clinical Trials Information Service</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see if it is safe and effective to use gene therapy to treat&#xD;
      non-Hodgkin's lymphoma (NHL) in HIV-positive patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Stem cell transplantation is a procedure used to treat NHL. Stem cells are very immature&#xD;
      cells that develop to create all of the different types of blood cells. In this study, some&#xD;
      of your stem cells will be treated with gene therapy, meaning the cells are treated with a&#xD;
      virus that does not cause disease. Some cells will receive a virus that contains ribozymes,&#xD;
      enzymes that may help fight HIV. Other cells will be treated with a virus that does not&#xD;
      contain ribozymes to see how the virus works alone. Some cells will not be treated at all.&#xD;
      Doctors would like to see whether giving patients stem cells with ribozymes can treat NHL and&#xD;
      stop HIV from growing at the same time.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this study, CD34+ cells (stem cells) are transduced with a retroviral vector construct&#xD;
      that incorporates multiple ribozymes, a form of RNA with the ability to selectively inhibit&#xD;
      gene expression, targeting different sites within the HIV virus. These transduced cells are&#xD;
      reinfused into patients as part of a bone marrow transplant procedure for AIDS/lymphoma.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients undergoing autologous bone marrow transplantation are entered into this study. A&#xD;
      &quot;neutral&quot; retrovirus named &quot;LN&quot; and a retrovirus that contains two ribozyme sequences named&#xD;
      &quot;L-TR/Tat-neo&quot; are introduced into the patient's PBPC. The L-TR/Tat-neo retrovirus has been&#xD;
      shown in tissue culture experiments to inhibit the replication of HIV. The LN retrovirus&#xD;
      serves as an internal control to examine selective advantage of the gene therapy. Patients&#xD;
      have a bone marrow sample taken. After an additional round of chemotherapy with their&#xD;
      referring physician, patients receive daily injections of G-CSF to aid in the collection of&#xD;
      stem cells. Daily stem cell collections are performed. It is anticipated that three to four&#xD;
      collections will be required, but as many as six may be necessary. To prepare for the&#xD;
      transplantation of stem cells, patients are admitted for a 7-day series of intensive&#xD;
      chemotherapy. Following this conditioning, the gene-modified and untreated stem cells are&#xD;
      infused back into the patient. The collected cells are divided into three pools. One is set&#xD;
      aside without modification, one is modified with the LN control vector, and one is modified&#xD;
      with the L-TR/Tat-neo construct. The LN and L-TR/Tat-neo samples are pooled and given to the&#xD;
      patient by IV infusion over about 15 minutes. The unmodified cells are then infused over 10&#xD;
      to 15 minutes. Patients remain in the hospital until their blood cells return to adequate&#xD;
      levels and they are well enough to be released. Following transplantation, all patients are&#xD;
      followed at Months 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 18, and 24. Because of the experimental nature of gene&#xD;
      therapy, patients are followed periodically throughout their lifetimes.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>5</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peripheral blood stem cells</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        You may be eligible for this study if you:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are 18 to 60 years old.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have been HIV-positive at least since you were diagnosed with non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have an HIV level less than or equal to 25,000 copies/ml and a CD4 count of at least&#xD;
             100 cells/mm3.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are currently about to undergo bone marrow transplantation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have responded well to cancer treatments, including chemotherapy and previous bone&#xD;
             marrow transplantation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agree to use effective barrier methods of birth control, such as condoms, during the&#xD;
             study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are on anti-HIV therapy (HAART).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        You will not be eligible for this study if you:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have lymphoma affecting your nervous system.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have had any AIDS-related opportunistic infections in the past year.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have heart disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are pregnant or breast-feeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have severe diarrhea.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a history of cytomegalovirus (CMV) retinitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have dementia or encephalopathy (an infection of the brain).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a history of another type of cancer (except for skin cancer) before your&#xD;
             diagnosis of NHL.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are allergic to etoposide or have had a toxic reaction to prior chemotherapy.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Zaia</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope Natl Med Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2003</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Marrow</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphocyte Transformation</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-1</keyword>
  <keyword>Retroviridae</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma, AIDS-Related</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic Vectors</keyword>
  <keyword>Transduction, Genetic</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene Transfer Techniques</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

