<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00006207</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HIVNET 020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00006207</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Tolerability of the Vaginal Gel PRO 2000/5</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Multicenter Dose Escalation Safety and Acceptability Study of the Investigational Vaginal Microbicide Agent PRO 2000/5 Gel (P)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Procept</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the vaginal gel PRO 2000/5 causes&#xD;
      irritation when used daily.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Studies have shown PRO 2000/5 is safe and well tolerated as a vaginal gel in healthy women&#xD;
      who are not sexually active. However, it was not determined what side effects to skin in the&#xD;
      vaginal area there might be in sexually active women.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Vaginal microbicides are designed to inhibit the sexual transmission of HIV-1 and other&#xD;
      disease pathogens. Two Phase I clinical trials were conducted to evaluate the safety and&#xD;
      tolerance of the gel, PRO 2000/5, in sexually abstinent volunteers. Both demonstrated that&#xD;
      multiple application of the gel was safe and well tolerated in healthy, sexually abstinent&#xD;
      women but no clear association between the use of the gel and epithelial disruption was&#xD;
      indicated. Because genital ulceration and inflammation may increase the risk of HIV&#xD;
      infection, additional clinical evaluation of PRO 2000/5 gel is warranted, especially for&#xD;
      study participants with active sexual behavior.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants apply PRO 2000/5 gel intravaginally either once or twice daily for 14 days.&#xD;
      HIV-negative participants in sexually active cohorts (Cohorts A1-A4) are instructed to engage&#xD;
      in vaginal intercourse at least twice a week. Participants in the HIV-positive cohort (Cohort&#xD;
      B1) abstain from sexual intercourse for the dosing period. Researchers conduct physical exams&#xD;
      to see if the gel is having any harmful effects on the woman's vulva, vagina, or cervix.&#xD;
      Women and their male partners are questioned about gel usage.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>60</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PRO 2000</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Volunteers may be eligible for this study if they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are female and 18-45 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are willing and able to complete daily study records.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are willing to undergo clinical exams and testing.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Either have regular menstrual periods or do not menstruate due to use of hormones.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agree to stop using female barrier methods of birth control during the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Additionally, volunteers may be eligible for HIV-negative groups in this study if&#xD;
             they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have not changed their use of hormonal birth control over the last 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are HIV-negative.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a single male partner at low-risk for HIV infection and agree that he can be&#xD;
             asked for his consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agree to the following: To have vaginal intercourse 2 or more times a week; to use&#xD;
             condoms provided by the study for each act of intercourse; to use the gel as directed;&#xD;
             not to be in similar studies; not to receive oral sex; not to use IV drugs, except for&#xD;
             medical treatment; not to use any other vaginal products; not to douche; and not to&#xD;
             use vaginal drying agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Additionally, volunteers may be eligible for the HIV-positive group in this study if&#xD;
             they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are HIV-positive.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a CD4 count greater than 200 cells/mm3.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a normal Pap smear at screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are on stable anti-HIV drug therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agree to have no sexual intercourse during the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have HIV care by qualified medical caregivers.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agree to allow study staff access to their HIV medical care information.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agree to the following: To use the gel as directed; not to use IV drugs other than for&#xD;
             medical treatment; not to use any other vaginal products; not to participate in&#xD;
             similar studies; not to receive oral sex; not to douche; and not to use any vaginal&#xD;
             drying agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Volunteers will not be eligible for this study if they:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are menopausal.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have certain liver, kidney, or blood problems.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have genital problems such as sores.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are allergic to anything used in the study, including latex.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have used spermicides or condoms treated with spermicides within the week before&#xD;
             enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have been in another drug study within the past 30 days.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have participated in this trial before and study gel has been permanently&#xD;
             discontinued.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have had an IUD or begun using hormonal birth control, or had an abnormal Pap smear, a&#xD;
             pregnancy, an abortion, gynecologic surgery, breakthrough menstrual bleeding, or&#xD;
             vaginal bleeding during or following sexual intercourse, in the last 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have had or received treatment for sexually transmitted diseases in the past 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Show signs, on a pelvic exam, indicating a sexually transmitted disease or other&#xD;
             genital tract problems.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Used IV drugs, except for medical reasons, within the past year.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Received antibiotics in the last 14 days.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have had a reaction to an anticoagulant (such as warfarin or heparin).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Are pregnant or breast-feeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a positive urine culture.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ken Mayer</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Salim Abdool Karim</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Julia Welch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27709</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mayer KH, Karim SA, Kelly C, Maslankowski L, Rees H, Profy AT, Day J, Welch J, Rosenberg Z; HIV Prevention Trials Network (HPTN) 020 Protocol Team. Safety and tolerability of vaginal PRO 2000 gel in sexually active HIV-uninfected and abstinent HIV-infected women. AIDS. 2003 Feb 14;17(3):321-9. doi: 10.1097/00002030-200302140-00005.</citation>
    <PMID>12556685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2003</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 11, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 29, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 29, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 30, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>HIV Seropositivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Dose-Response Relationship, Drug</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Seronegativity</keyword>
  <keyword>Mucous Membrane</keyword>
  <keyword>Ulcer</keyword>
  <keyword>Vagina</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-HIV Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Sexual Abstinence</keyword>
  <keyword>Irritants</keyword>
  <keyword>PRO 2000</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

