<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00006452</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NABTT-9712 CDR0000066986</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA006973</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NABTT-9712</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>JHOC-NABTT-9712</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00006452</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gadolinium Texaphyrin Plus Radiation Therapy in Treating Patients With Supratentorial Glioblastoma Multiforme</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial to Evaluate Repetitive Intravenous Doses of Gadolinium-Texaphyrin as a Radiosensitizer in Patients With Glioblastoma Multiforme</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to damage tumor cells. Drugs such as&#xD;
      gadolinium texaphyrin may make tumor cells more sensitive to radiation therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PURPOSE: Phase I trial to study the effectiveness of gadolinium texaphyrin plus radiation&#xD;
      therapy in treating patients who have supratentorial glioblastoma multiforme that has not&#xD;
      been previously treated.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Evaluate the toxic effects of gadolinium texaphyrin administered to patients&#xD;
      receiving cranial radiotherapy for glioblastoma multiforme. II. Determine the maximum&#xD;
      tolerated dose of this regimen in these patients. III. Determine the pharmacokinetic profile&#xD;
      of this regimen in these patients. IV. Determine the biodistribution of gadolinium texaphyrin&#xD;
      in both neoplastic tissue and normal brain parenchyma. V. Evaluate the effect and&#xD;
      accumulation of this regimen in normal brain parenchyma and neoplastic tissue by following&#xD;
      the change in enhancing volume and percent change in signal intensity over time.&#xD;
&#xD;
      OUTLINE: This is an open label, multicenter study. Arm I: Patients receive radiotherapy once&#xD;
      a day, 5 days a week, for 6 weeks. Gadolinium texaphyrin IV is administered every other day&#xD;
      within 2-5 hours prior to radiotherapy. Patients are evaluated at 1 month, and if no more&#xD;
      than 1 of 3 patients experiences unacceptable toxicity, 3 patients are entered on the imaging&#xD;
      portion of the study. Once arm I has successfully entered 3 patients with acceptable toxicity&#xD;
      profiles and 3 patients in the imaging portion of the study, patient enrollment begins for&#xD;
      arm II. Arm II: Cohorts of 3-9 patients receive radiotherapy as in arm I and escalating doses&#xD;
      of gadolinium texaphyrin IV administered within 2-5 hours prior to each radiation dose. The&#xD;
      maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of gadolinium texaphyrin is defined as the dose at which no more&#xD;
      than one third of the patients experience dose limiting toxicity. Arm III: Patients&#xD;
      experiencing dose limiting toxicity in arm II requiring dose reduction below predetermined&#xD;
      once a day limit receive gadolinium every other day, with radiotherapy as in arm II. The MTD&#xD;
      is defined as in arm II. Arm IV: An additional 3 patients are enrolled at the MTD and enter&#xD;
      the imaging portion of the study. Patients are followed for 1 month after final radiation&#xD;
      therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: At least 18 patients will be accrued for this study within 6 months.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 10, 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 16, 2004</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 9, 2003</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>motexafin gadolinium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>radiation therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed, previously untreated, supratentorial&#xD;
        grade IV glioblastoma multiforme Measurable and contrast enhancing disease on postoperative&#xD;
        MRI&#xD;
&#xD;
        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Performance status: Karnofsky 60-100% Life&#xD;
        expectancy: Not specified Hematopoietic: WBC at least 3,000/mm3 Absolute granulocyte count&#xD;
        at least 1,500/mm3 Platelet count at least 100,000/mm3 Hemoglobin at least 10 g/dL Hepatic:&#xD;
        Bilirubin no greater than 2.0 mg/dL Alkaline phosphatase no greater than 4 times upper&#xD;
        limit of normal (ULN) SGOT or SGPT no greater than 4 times ULN PT and aPTT normal Renal:&#xD;
        Creatinine no greater than 1.5 mg/dL Other: Not pregnant or nursing Fertile patients must&#xD;
        use effective contraception Negative pregnancy test No serious infection or medical illness&#xD;
        No history of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency No known porphyria No other&#xD;
        prior malignancy within the past 5 years except curatively treated basal or squamous cell&#xD;
        carcinoma of the skin or carcinoma in situ of the cervix or breast&#xD;
&#xD;
        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: No prior immunotherapy for glioblastoma&#xD;
        multiforme No prior immunotoxins, immunoconjugates, antisense, peptide receptor&#xD;
        antagonists, interferons, interleukins, tumor infiltrating lymphocytes, lymphokine&#xD;
        activated killer cells, or gene therapy for glioblastoma multiforme Chemotherapy: No prior&#xD;
        chemotherapy for glioblastoma multiforme Endocrine therapy: No prior hormonal therapy for&#xD;
        glioblastoma multiforme Stable corticosteroid regimen for at least 5 days prior to study&#xD;
        Radiotherapy: No prior radiotherapy for glioblastoma multiforme Surgery: Recovered from&#xD;
        postoperative complications Other: No other concurrent investigational agents&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>120 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James L. Pearlman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 6, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 8, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adult glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult giant cell glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Motexafin gadolinium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

