<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000642</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG 146</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>D0190g</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000642</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I Study of the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Recombinant CD4 Immunoglobulin G (rCD4-IgG) in HIV-1 Seropositive Women During the Last Trimester of Pregnancy and Their Newborns</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Recombinant CD4 Immunoglobulin G (rCD4-IgG) in HIV-1 Seropositive Women During the Last Trimester of Pregnancy and Their Newborns</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Part 1: To determine both the safety, tolerance, and pharmacokinetic profile (blood levels)&#xD;
      of recombinant CD4 immunoglobulin G (rCD4-IgG) by intravenous bolus administration (given&#xD;
      through the vein) in women with HIV infection who are in their third trimester (last three&#xD;
      months of pregnancy). To determine the safety of maternal/fetal transfer of rCD4-IgG in&#xD;
      infants born to mothers entered into the study. To obtain a preliminary indication of the&#xD;
      antiviral and immunologic effects of rCD4-IgG in HIV seropositive pregnant women and their&#xD;
      newborns.&#xD;
&#xD;
      AMENDED: Part 2: To determine the safety profile of rCD4-IgG in HIV-1-infected women at the&#xD;
      onset of labor and in their newborns. To determine the extent of placental transfer of&#xD;
      rCD4-IgG when administered to the mother at onset of labor. To determine the pharmacokinetics&#xD;
      of rCD4-IgG in newborns. To obtain preliminary evidence of the ability of rCD4-IgG to prevent&#xD;
      intrapartum transmission of HIV-1 from mother to fetus.&#xD;
&#xD;
      An agent that can prevent HIV infection is desirable for those at risk of infection as well&#xD;
      as in the pregnant female and newborn populations. Such an agent may help prevent the&#xD;
      progression of the disease in infants and children in early stages of infections. In theory,&#xD;
      rCD4-IgG has antiviral effects.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An agent that can prevent HIV infection is desirable for those at risk of infection as well&#xD;
      as in the pregnant female and newborn populations. Such an agent may help prevent the&#xD;
      progression of the disease in infants and children in early stages of infections. In theory,&#xD;
      rCD4-IgG has antiviral effects.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Part 1: Per the original protocol, a total of six pregnant women were enrolled in Groups A&#xD;
      and B. Patients in Group A received rCD4-IgG at the onset of labor, and those in Group B&#xD;
      received rCD4-IgG twice per week, beginning 1 week before the expected date of delivery.&#xD;
      Newborns were not treated in Part 1 of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      AMENDED: In Part 2 of the study, a total of nine pregnant women are enrolled in Groups C, D,&#xD;
      and E and receive a higher dose of rCD4-IgG at the onset of labor. If the mother has not&#xD;
      delivered 18 hours after rCD4-IgG injection, a second injection at the same dose is&#xD;
      administered; daily injections are given thereafter until delivery. The newborns receive 1 of&#xD;
      3 doses of rCD4-IgG daily for the first 5 days of life. Infants are enrolled sequentially to&#xD;
      each dose level.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>30</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CD4-IgG</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Iron, multivitamins, short courses of treatment for correctable medical problems&#xD;
             (e.g., urinary tract infection), oral trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole (TMP/SMX) or&#xD;
             aerosolized pentamidine for prophylaxis of Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia (PCP),&#xD;
             prophylactic antifungal therapy, or isoniazid (INH) therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acetaminophen.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other supportive therapy (blood and blood products, vaginal creams, antiemetics,&#xD;
             antidiarrheals, cough medicines).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Specific agents used during delivery, such as oxytocic agents or anesthetics.&#xD;
             Participation in this protocol will not prevent a newborn from receiving any&#xD;
             medication.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Treatment:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Blood and blood product transfusions.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Gamma globulin as prophylaxis against infection with varicella virus and hepatitis&#xD;
             virus, or RhoGAM in case of maternal-fetal incompatibility.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Risk Behavior:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Illicit drug use.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must be:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  In their third trimester of pregnancy, or join the study with their newborn children.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willing and able to sign informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Available for follow-up for at least 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  The child should be available for follow-up for at least 1 year after delivery, and&#xD;
             preferably longer.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Co-existing Condition:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with the following conditions or symptoms are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Medical complications including, but not limited to, insulin dependent diabetes&#xD;
             mellitus (IDDM), hypertensive disorders such as severe pre-eclampsia, eclampsia,&#xD;
             chronic hypertension, cardiovascular disease including rheumatic or congenital heart&#xD;
             disease, collagen vascular disease, endocarditis, and renal disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hematological conditions including, but not limited to, hemoglobinopathies,&#xD;
             coagulopathy, idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP), and maternal-fetal blood&#xD;
             incompatibilities with isoimmunization (e.g., Rh-negative mother with a positive&#xD;
             indirect Coomb's test at any time during this pregnancy).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Neurological disease(s) including seizure disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Bronchopulmonary diseases, such as severe asthma.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Evidence of fetal intolerance of the intrauterine environment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Antiretroviral agents:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Suramin, ribavirin, HPA23, phosphonoformate, ansamycin, zidovudine (AZT), didanosine&#xD;
             (ddI), or dideoxycytidine (ddC).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other antiviral drugs, including acyclovir or ganciclovir.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Immunomodulating agents:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Interleukin 2, interferons, thymic hormones, or other agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cytolytic chemotherapeutic agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Corticosteroids.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Immunoglobulin preparations.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Treatment:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Radiation therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Regular administration of gamma globulin.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with the following are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Serious medical or surgical complication of the pregnancy and/or delivery that&#xD;
             required treatment during delivery or that might compromise the health of the mother&#xD;
             or fetus.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Any HIV-related complications requiring antiretroviral therapy during the pregnancy,&#xD;
        including encephalopathy and opportunistic infections.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Systemic infection requiring IV therapy in the month prior to enrollment in this study&#xD;
             (IV treatment for pyelonephritis is permitted).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Recombinant CD4 immunoglobulin G (rCD4-IgG).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded within 4 weeks of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Antiretroviral agents:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Suramin, ribavirin, HPA23, phosphonoformate, ansamycin, zidovudine (AZT), didanosine&#xD;
             (ddI), or dideoxycytidine (ddC).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other antiviral drugs, including acyclovir or ganciclovir.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Immunomodulating agents:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Interleukin 2, interferons, thymic hormones, or other agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cytolytic chemotherapeutic agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Corticosteroids.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Immunoglobulin preparations.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Treatment:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded within 4 weeks of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Radiation therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of poor medical compliance (at the discretion of the investigator). Current illicit&#xD;
        drug use.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Day</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SUNY - Brooklyn</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Children's Hosp / Baylor Univ</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duliege AM, Shearer WT, Hammill H, Kline MW, Minkoff HL, Izu A, Ammann A. Transplacental transfer of rCD4-IgG given one week and immediately prior to birth: safety and pharmacokinetics in HIV-1 seropositive pregnant women and their newborn infants. Int Conf AIDS. 1992 Jul 19-24;8(2):B91 (abstract no PoB 3028)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shearer WT, Duliege AM, Kline MW, Hammill H, Minkoff H, Ammann AJ, Chen S, Izu A, Mordenti J. Transport of recombinant human CD4-immunoglobulin G across the human placenta: pharmacokinetics and safety in six mother-infant pairs in AIDS clinical trial group protocol 146. Clin Diagn Lab Immunol. 1995 May;2(3):281-5. doi: 10.1128/cdli.2.3.281-285.1995.</citation>
    <PMID>7664172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2003</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Recombinant Proteins</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy Trimester, Third</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy Complications, Infectious</keyword>
  <keyword>IgG</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug Evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>Antigens, CD4</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS-Related Complex</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunization, Passive</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>CD4 Immunoadhesins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

