<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005719</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4928</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL044898</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005719</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sustaining Women's Smoking Cessation Postpartum</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To conduct a five-year demonstration and education project to sustain smoking cessation&#xD;
      postpartum by women who had stopped smoking in pregnancy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The results from this study were expected to demonstrate the effectiveness of a practical&#xD;
      program to protect women and their families from direct and indirect smoke exposure and to&#xD;
      contribute longitudinal data on change processes involved in smoking cessation, especially&#xD;
      those over the maintenance, relapse, and recycling stages, in a relatively complete&#xD;
      population through a critical transition.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The TLC Program, unique in its focus on the postpartum period, used a researched model of&#xD;
      behavior change that matched messages and skill training with the woman's stage of change. It&#xD;
      also addressed the whole family to create a supportive environment for individual change,&#xD;
      included other steps for families to protect children from passive smoke and negative&#xD;
      modeling, and focused on smoking and smoke exposure directly as well as through self-care and&#xD;
      child-care messages. The program used innovative materials, including videotapes and&#xD;
      intervention.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study took place in two multi-ethnic health-care sites where the research team had&#xD;
      conducted previous studies. The study used a randomized mixed design with 500 women who&#xD;
      smoked regularly before pregnancy and who had been abstinent for &gt; 30 days at their 28th week&#xD;
      of pregnancy. The primary outcome was abstinence at one year postpartum. Secondary outcomes&#xD;
      were partner smoking status and exposure of the index baby. Self report was validated&#xD;
      biochemically in samples of mothers and babies. The study design separated data collection&#xD;
      from the experiments by enrolling subjects in a university-sponsored study of new mothers'&#xD;
      health-care site.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1990</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 1996</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Lung Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>0 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dolan-Mullen P, Ramirez G, Groff JY. A meta-analysis of randomized trials of prenatal smoking cessation interventions. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1994 Nov;171(5):1328-34. doi: 10.1016/0002-9378(94)90156-2.</citation>
    <PMID>7977542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mullen PD, Simons-Morton DG, Ramirez G, Frankowski RF, Green LW, Mains DA. A meta-analysis of trials evaluating patient education and counseling for three groups of preventive health behaviors. Patient Educ Couns. 1997 Nov;32(3):157-73. doi: 10.1016/s0738-3991(97)00037-2.</citation>
    <PMID>9423498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Groff JY, Mullen PD, Mongoven M, Burau K. Prenatal weight gain patterns and infant birthweight associated with maternal smoking. Birth. 1997 Dec;24(4):234-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1523-536x.1997.tb00596.x.</citation>
    <PMID>9460314</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hudmon KS, Mullen PD, Nicol L, Hammond SK, Sockrider MM, Sajak T, Thompson J. Telephone-guided placement and removal of nicotine monitors for the assessment of passive exposure to environmental tobacco smoke. Toxicol Ind Health. 1997 Jan-Feb;13(1):73-80. doi: 10.1177/074823379701300107.</citation>
    <PMID>9098952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stotts AL, DiClemente CC, Carbonari JP, Mullen PD. Pregnancy smoking cessation: a case of mistaken identity. Addict Behav. 1996 Jul-Aug;21(4):459-71. doi: 10.1016/0306-4603(95)00082-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8830904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stotts AL, DiClemente CC, Carbonari JP, Mullen PD. Postpartum return to smoking: staging a &quot;suspended&quot; behavior. Health Psychol. 2000 Jul;19(4):324-32. doi: 10.1037//0278-6133.19.4.324.</citation>
    <PMID>10907650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2021</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 29, 2021</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 29, 2021</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 1, 2021</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

