<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001408</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>940203</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>94-I-0203</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001408</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Role of T-Cells in Asthma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cytokine Expression in Allergic Asthma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the movement of T cells (a type of white blood cell) from the blood&#xD;
      to the lungs in patients with asthma after exposure to an allergen, such as cat dander or&#xD;
      pollen. Asthma is in large part due to inflammation of the bronchi (the breathing tubes of&#xD;
      the lungs), causing heat, swelling and redness. T cells play a major role in the inflammatory&#xD;
      reaction. A better understanding of T cell migration to the lungs after allergen exposure may&#xD;
      lead to improved therapies for asthma.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients between 18 and 50 years of age with mild allergic asthma may be eligible for this&#xD;
      study. In addition, patients and healthy normal volunteers between 18 and 65 years of age may&#xD;
      participate in a sub-study (blood draw) of this protocol. Participants will undergo the&#xD;
      following procedures:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Visit 1 (screening visit)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Blood tests for blood counts and HIV&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Urine pregnancy test for women of childbearing potential.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Visit 2&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Physical examination and electrocardiogram (EKG)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Prick skin testing - A drop of allergen extract is put on the skin and the underlying&#xD;
           skin is scratched with a needle. A positive test resembles an insect bite and may itch.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Intradermal skin tests - Increasing concentrations of a drop of diluted allergen are&#xD;
           injected into the skin and the allergic response is monitored until a 5-mm swelling (1/4&#xD;
           inch) swelling develops.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Methacholine challenge - The subject has repeated pulmonary function (breathing) tests&#xD;
           after breathing methacholine, a drug that temporarily (for 5 to 10 minutes) worsens&#xD;
           asthma symptoms.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Physician evaluation and repeat pulmonary function test&#xD;
&#xD;
      Visit 3&#xD;
&#xD;
      - Allergen bronchoprovocation - This test will be done in patients whose physical evaluation&#xD;
      and breathing test permit them to continue with the study. A heparin lock (needle device that&#xD;
      stays in a vein to allow multiple blood draws without repeated sticks) is placed. The subject&#xD;
      breathes 5 breaths of allergen through a nebulizer (device that creates a mist), followed by&#xD;
      a breathing test. This procedure will be repeated with increasingly higher allergen doses&#xD;
      until lung function significantly declines or for a maximum of 6 doses. Subjects are&#xD;
      monitored for 8 hours after the last dose. Blood samples of 50 ml each (3.5 tablespoons) are&#xD;
      collected at 1, 3, 5 and 8 hours, and a physician evaluation is done at the end of the 8&#xD;
      hours. Additional 50-mm blood samples are collected the following two mornings.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Visit 4&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Physician evaluation, blood test for anemia and pulmonary function test&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Serial blood draws - 50 ml of blood will be drawn, followed by salt-water nebulization&#xD;
           and another 50-ml blood draw after 1 hour. Additional 50-ml blood samples will be drawn&#xD;
           7 hours later and then on the next two mornings.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants in the sub-study portion of this protocol will undergo the screening blood test,&#xD;
      prick skin testing, breathing test after methacholine inhalation and a 100 ml-blood draw.&#xD;
      These tests will be done in three sessions.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the last 10 years it has become generally accepted that asthma is an inflammatory disease&#xD;
      of the airways. T lymphocytes play a key role in regulating this inflammatory response,&#xD;
      through the elaboration of cytokines such as IL-4, IL-5, and IFN-gamma. IL-5 is of particular&#xD;
      interest because it is the major eosinophil survival factor in vivo. Eosinophils are felt to&#xD;
      be the major effector cells in asthma, causing damage to various airway structures.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The pulmonary late phase response, a worsening of airflow seen 4-8 hours after allergen&#xD;
      inhalation, is associated with many of the inflammatory changes seen in chronic asthma.&#xD;
      Current studies suggest that during the late phase response peripheral blood T cells traffic&#xD;
      to the lungs and express cytokines, specifically IL-4 and IL-5.&#xD;
&#xD;
      We propose to investigate this trafficking by determining the frequencies and phenotype of&#xD;
      cells capable of producing the above cytokines in the peripheral blood in subjects with mild&#xD;
      allergic asthma. These studies should lead to a clearer understanding of the cells and&#xD;
      processes that lead to T cell trafficking to the lung and may yield a tool to evaluate the&#xD;
      proposed anti-inflammatory therapies for asthma.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 14, 1994</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 1, 1995</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 1, 1995</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>250</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA - BLOOD DRAW/ASTHMA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age 18-65.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Asthma of greater than one year duration.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Willingness to adhere to effective contraception in women of child bearing age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Negative HIV test.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA - BLOOD DRAW/ASTHMA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        For blood draws of greater than 100 ml, a hemoglobin of less than 12.5 g/dl. For blood&#xD;
        draws of 100 ml or less, performed less frequently than every 56 days, a hemoglobin of less&#xD;
        than 10.0 g/dl.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Current pregnancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Medical history suggesting lung diseases other than asthma.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of immunodeficiency or HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA - BLOOD DRAW/NORMAL CONTROL:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age 18-65.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Willingness to adhere to effective contraception in women of child bearing age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Negative HIV test.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA - BLOOD DRAW/NORMAL CONTROL:&#xD;
&#xD;
        For blood draws of greater than 100 ml, a hemoglobin of less than 12.5 g/dl. For blood&#xD;
        draws of 100 ml or less, performed less frequently than every 56 days, a hemoglobin of less&#xD;
        than 10.0 g/dl.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Current pregnancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Positive skin test to one or more allergens in the battery tested.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of asthma or other allergic diseases, such as hay fever.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Medical history suggesting lung diseases other than asthma.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of immunodeficiency or HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA - EXHALED BREATH CONDENSATE/ASTHMA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age 18-65.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Asthma as diagnosed by a physician or use of medications consistent with the treatment of&#xD;
        asthma.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects must have a doctor outside NIH and they will provide routine and emergency care.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA - EXHALED BREATH CONDENSATE/ASTHMA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of immunodeficiency or HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of allergy to latex.&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA - EXHALED BREATH CONDENSATE/HEALTHY CONTROL:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age 18 - 65.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA - EXHALED BREATH CONDENSATE/HEALTHY CONTROL:&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of asthma or other allergic diseases, such as allergic rhinitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Medical history suggesting lung diseases other than asthma.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of allergy to latex.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of immunodeficiency or HIV infection.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guidelines for the diagnosis and management of asthma. National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute. National Asthma Education Program. Expert Panel Report. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 1991 Sep;88(3 Pt 2):425-534. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>1890276</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robinson D, Hamid Q, Bentley A, Ying S, Kay AB, Durham SR. Activation of CD4+ T cells, increased TH2-type cytokine mRNA expression, and eosinophil recruitment in bronchoalveolar lavage after allergen inhalation challenge in patients with atopic asthma. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 1993 Aug;92(2):313-24. doi: 10.1016/0091-6749(93)90175-f.</citation>
    <PMID>8349942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerblich AA, Campbell AE, Schuyler MR. Changes in T-lymphocyte subpopulations after antigenic bronchial provocation in asthmatics. N Engl J Med. 1984 May 24;310(21):1349-52. doi: 10.1056/NEJM198405243102103.</citation>
    <PMID>6232459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 25, 2009</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Lymphocytes</keyword>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytokines</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin-5</keyword>
  <keyword>Late Phase Response</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

