<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001012</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG 022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001012</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of AL721 in HIV-Infected Patients With Swollen Lymph Nodes</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label, Multiple Dose Ranging Trial of AL721 in Patients With Persistent Generalized Lymphadenopathy and Symptomatic HIV Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To study the tolerance and safety of increasing doses of AL-721 in patients with persistent&#xD;
      generalized lymphadenopathy (PGL) and symptomatic HIV infection, and to obtain preliminary&#xD;
      information on the effectiveness of AL-721 against the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) in&#xD;
      HIV-infected persons with PGL and symptomatic HIV infection. Although zidovudine (AZT)&#xD;
      prolongs life in certain AIDS patients, it is not a cure for AIDS and it also has toxic&#xD;
      effects in many patients. Therefore, it is necessary to test other drugs in HIV-infected&#xD;
      patients. AL-721 is a mixture of lipids (fats) extracted from egg yolks. Laboratory tests&#xD;
      suggest that it might inhibit the infectivity of the HIV. AL-721 has been tried so far in a&#xD;
      few patients for short periods of time and has been found to be well tolerated.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although zidovudine (AZT) prolongs life in certain AIDS patients, it is not a cure for AIDS&#xD;
      and it also has toxic effects in many patients. Therefore, it is necessary to test other&#xD;
      drugs in HIV-infected patients. AL-721 is a mixture of lipids (fats) extracted from egg&#xD;
      yolks. Laboratory tests suggest that it might inhibit the infectivity of the HIV. AL-721 has&#xD;
      been tried so far in a few patients for short periods of time and has been found to be well&#xD;
      tolerated.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients receive AL-721 twice daily. The first dose is taken on an empty stomach 1 hour&#xD;
      before a fat-free breakfast, with specific instructions given on foods that are allowed; the&#xD;
      second dose is taken at least 3 hours after the evening meal. No snacks are permitted after&#xD;
      the evening meal or after the evening dose of study medication. The study is scheduled to&#xD;
      last for 16 weeks of treatment and 4 weeks of follow-up. Throughout the study, frequent blood&#xD;
      samples will be taken from an arm vein. The blood samples are studied to evaluate any changes&#xD;
      in the patient's immune system, any toxic effects that might be detected in the blood, and&#xD;
      any changes in the presence of the HIV in the blood.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>50</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AL 721</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Persistent generalized lymphadenopathy (PGL) (CDC-Group III), defined as palpable&#xD;
             lymphadenopathy (nodes of 1 cm or greater) at two or more noncontiguous extrainguinal&#xD;
             sites persisting for &gt; 3 months in the absence of an illness other than HIV infection&#xD;
             to account for the findings.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  AIDS related complex (ARC), defined as the presence of at least one of the following&#xD;
             findings within 12 months prior to entry and the absence of a concurrent illness or&#xD;
             condition other than HIV infection to explain the findings:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any findings which define CDC-Group IV A.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of any one of the findings that define CDC-Group IV C2.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with any of the ARC symptoms can also have PGL and be enrolled in the&#xD;
             protocol as ARC patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A positive antibody to HIV by any federally licensed ELISA test kit within 30 days of&#xD;
             entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication: Allowed:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Topical or oral antifungal, antiviral, or antibiotic agents to treat oral candidiasis,&#xD;
             herpes simplex, herpes zoster, or bacterial infections that develop during the course&#xD;
             of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Exclude hemophiliacs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active substance abuse.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Alcohol consumption should be kept to a minimum.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Co-existing Condition:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with the following will be excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hemophilia.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History or presence of an AIDS-defining opportunistic infection or malignancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  AIDS related complex (ARC) patients with prior (within the last 12 months) or current&#xD;
             history of diarrhea defined as = or &gt; 3 liquid stools per day persisting for longer&#xD;
             than 1 month.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Significant malabsorption:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Greater than 10 percent weight loss within past 3 months with serum carotene &lt; 75&#xD;
             IU/ml or vitamin A &lt; 75 IU/ml.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Significant cardiac, liver, renal, or neurologic disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active ARC-defining secondary infection (oral candidiasis, oral hairy leukoplakia,&#xD;
             multidermatomal herpes zoster, recurrent nontyphoidal Salmonella bacteremia or&#xD;
             Nocardiosis) undergoing therapy or prophylaxis within 7 days of study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active tuberculosis under treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Concurrent neoplasm other than basal cell carcinoma of the skin or in situ carcinoma&#xD;
             of the cervix.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any medication that will interfere with the assessment of AL-721, including&#xD;
             nutritional supplements, vitamins, laxatives, and over-the-counter products containing&#xD;
             lecithin.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chemoprophylaxis for Pneumocystis carinii (PCP), candida, herpes simplex, herpes&#xD;
             zoster infections, or bacterial infections.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Intravenous topical or oral antifungal, antiviral, or antibiotic agents to treat oral&#xD;
             candidiasis, herpes simplex, herpes zoster, or bacterial infections that develop&#xD;
             during the course of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Systemic chemotherapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded within 30 days of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any investigational drug.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Biologic response modifiers.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Corticosteroids.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chemotherapeutic agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Excluded within 90 days of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any antiretroviral agent or AL-721.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mildvan D</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Armstrong D</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles County - USC Med Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charity Hosp / Tulane Univ Med School</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Louisiana State Univ Med Ctr / Tulane Med School</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tulane Univ School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bronx Veterans Administration / Mount Sinai Hosp</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10468</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Med Ctr / Peter Krueger Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mem Sloan - Kettering Cancer Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Med Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mildvan D, Armstrong D, Antoniskis D, Sacks H, Balfour H, Buzas J, Pettinelli C. An open label dose-ranging trial of al721 in pgl and ARC. Int Conf AIDS. 1989 Jun 4-9;5:403 (abstract no WBP312)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mildvan D, Buzas J, Armstrong D, Antoniskis D, Sacks HS, Rhame FS, Mosbach EW, Pettinelli C. An open-label, dose-ranging trial of AL 721 in patients with persistent generalized lymphadenopathy and AIDS-related complex. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr (1988). 1991;4(10):945-51.</citation>
    <PMID>1890604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2021</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 28, 2021</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 28, 2021</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 1, 2021</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Virus Replication</keyword>
  <keyword>T-Lymphocytes</keyword>
  <keyword>Dose-Response Relationship, Drug</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug Evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>AL 721</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS-Related Complex</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiviral Agents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

