<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001230</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>880083</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>88-I-0083</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001230</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Host Response to Infection and Treatment in Filarial Diseases</brief_title>
  <official_title>Host Response to Infection and Treatment in the Filarial Diseases of Humans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate and treat patients with filarial infections to explore in depth the&#xD;
      immunology of the disease, including susceptibility to infection, disease development, and&#xD;
      response to treatment. Filarial infections are caused by parasitic worms. The immature worm&#xD;
      (larva) is transmitted to a person through a mosquito bite and grows in the human body to 2&#xD;
      to 4 inches in length. Although many of these infections do not produce symptoms, especially&#xD;
      in the early stages of infection, others can have serious consequences, including swelling of&#xD;
      the limbs or genitalia, allergic-lung problems, skin rash, eye inflammation that can lead to&#xD;
      blindness, and heart disease. This protocol does not involve any experimental diagnostic&#xD;
      procedures or treatments, and will use only procedures employed in the standard practice of&#xD;
      medicine.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Persons between 3 and 100 years of age diagnosed with or suspected of infection with&#xD;
      Wuchereria bancrofti, Bugia malayi, Onchocerca volvulus, Loa loa, or other parasitic worms&#xD;
      may be eligible for this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants will have routine tests to determine the specific type of filarial infection.&#xD;
      These may include special tests of the lungs, skin or heart, depending on the type of&#xD;
      parasite suspected. Patients with skin reactions may have a &quot;punch biopsy&quot; to examine a small&#xD;
      piece of affected skin. For this procedure, an area of skin is numbed with an anesthetic and&#xD;
      a small circular area, about 1/3-inch in diameter and 1/2-inch thick, is removed using a&#xD;
      sharp cookie cutter-type instrument. Some patients may require bronchoalveolar lavage. For&#xD;
      this procedure, the mouth and throat are numbed with lidocaine jelly and spray and, if&#xD;
      needed, a sedative is given for comfort. A small plastic tube is placed in a vein to give&#xD;
      medications. A pencil-thin tube is then passed through the nose or mouth into the lung&#xD;
      airways to examine the airways. Salt water is injected through the bronchoscope into the air&#xD;
      passage, acting as a rinse. A sample of the fluid is then withdrawn and examined for&#xD;
      infection, inflammatory cells and inflammatory chemicals. (Bronchoalveolar lavage is done&#xD;
      only if medically necessary and only on patients 21 years or older.) Once the diagnosis is&#xD;
      established, standard treatment will be instituted with either diethylcarbamazine or&#xD;
      ivermectin, depending on the type of infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Additional procedures for research purposes include:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Extra blood draws to study immune cells and other immune substances. (This is the only&#xD;
           research procedure that will be done in - More frequent and extensive follow-up&#xD;
           evaluations than usual for routine care. They will include physical examination and&#xD;
           blood studies.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Urine collections at specified periods, possibly including 24-hour collections.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Skin tests to examine the body s reaction to allergens-common environmental substances,&#xD;
           such as cat dander or pollen-that cause an allergic reaction. The test is done in one of&#xD;
           two ways: either the skin is lightly scratched and an allergen extract is placed over&#xD;
           the just-broken skin, or a very fine needle is used to inject a small amount of allergen&#xD;
           under the skin. In both methods, the site is monitored for swelling or hives in the next&#xD;
           48 hours.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Leukapheresis (only on patients 21 or older ) to collect quantities of white blood&#xD;
           cells. Whole blood is collected through a needle in an arm vein, similar to donating&#xD;
           blood. The blood circulates through a machine that separates it into its components, and&#xD;
           the white cells are removed. The rest of the blood is returned to the body, either&#xD;
           through the same needle or through another needle in the other arm.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients admitted on this protocol will have, or be suspected of having, one of the filarial&#xD;
      infections affecting humans. After routine clinical evaluation they will be studied in depth&#xD;
      immunologically, and their blood cells and/or serum will be collected to provide reagents&#xD;
      (eg., specific antibodies, T-cell clones, etc.) that will be used in the laboratory to&#xD;
      address the broader questions of diagnosis, immunoregulation, pathology and&#xD;
      immunoprophylaxis. Careful observations of the patients' clinical and immunologic responses&#xD;
      to therapy will be made, as well as long-term follow-up of these changes. It is anticipated&#xD;
      both that the patients will receive optimal clinical care for their infections and that the&#xD;
      specimens collected from them will prove to be valuable reagents for the laboratory studies&#xD;
      of the immunologic responses unique to filarial or other related helminth infections.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 15, 1991</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Define the determinants of the susceptibility to filarial infection, the development of filarial disease and the beneficial or adverse response to chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Susceptibilities to filarial infection will be determined</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To identify clinical and biological markers of successful treatment in filarial-infected individuals</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Identification of clinical and biological markers of successful treatments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize the immunoregulatory mechanisms at play in filaria-infected individuals</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Characterization of immunoregulatory mechanisms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To create a serum and cell bank for the study of filarial infections of humans both before and at fixed times following definitive treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cell and serum bank will be maintained.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To understand the natural history of filarial infections in expatriates and other travelers and in immigrant populations</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Better understanding of natural history of infections in expatriates and travels</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Filariasis</condition>
  <condition>Helminthiasis</condition>
  <condition>Parasitic Infection</condition>
  <condition>Mansonelliasis</condition>
  <condition>Onchocerciasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients that have, or are suspected of having, one of the filarial infections affecting humans</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diethylcarbamazine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Males and females having or suspected of having a filarial infections will be enrolled. The&#xD;
        participants will either have been native residents of endemic regions where these filarial&#xD;
        infections are prevalent or they would have acquired the infection while traveling to such&#xD;
        regions.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age 3-100 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Access to a primary medical care provider outside of the NIH.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Ability to give informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Clinical evidence suggestive of a filarial infection&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Although pregnant or nursing women can be enrolled, they will be excluded from receiving&#xD;
        treatment while pregnant or breastfeeding&#xD;
&#xD;
        Less than 3 year of age; greater than 100 years of age&#xD;
&#xD;
        Any condition that the investigator feels put the subject at unacceptable risk for&#xD;
        participation in the study&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas B Nutman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicole C Holland-Thomas, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-5969</phone>
    <email>hollandnc@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Thomas B Nutman, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-5399</phone>
    <email>tnutman@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1988-I-0083.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klion AD, Horton J, Nutman TB. Albendazole therapy for loiasis refractory to diethylcarbamazine treatment. Clin Infect Dis. 1999 Sep;29(3):680-2. doi: 10.1086/598654.</citation>
    <PMID>10530467</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Showler AJ, Kubofcik J, Ricciardi A, Nutman TB. Differences in the Clinical and Laboratory Features of Imported Onchocerciasis in Endemic Individuals and Temporary Residents. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2019 May;100(5):1216-1222. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.18-0757.</citation>
    <PMID>30761981</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herrick JA, Metenou S, Makiya MA, Taylar-Williams CA, Law MA, Klion AD, Nutman TB. Eosinophil-associated processes underlie differences in clinical presentation of loiasis between temporary residents and those indigenous to Loa-endemic areas. Clin Infect Dis. 2015 Jan 1;60(1):55-63. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciu723. Epub 2014 Sep 18.</citation>
    <PMID>25234520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 30, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 1, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Wuchereria Bancrofti</keyword>
  <keyword>Loa Loa</keyword>
  <keyword>Brugia Malayi</keyword>
  <keyword>Onchocerca Volvulus</keyword>
  <keyword>Filarial Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Filariasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Onchocerciasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Helminthiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parasitic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mansonelliasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diethylcarbamazine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

