<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001951</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000045</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-CH-0045</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001951</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hormone Replacement in Young Women With Premature Ovarian Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hormone Replacement in Young Women With Premature Ovarian Failure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The human ovary produces male sex hormones (androgen) and female sex hormones (estrogen).&#xD;
      Currently, androgen is not included in hormone replacement therapy for women with premature&#xD;
      ovarian failure. Present hormone replacement therapy (HRT) was designed to treat women who&#xD;
      experience ovarian failure at menopause (around the age of 50). However, 1% of women will&#xD;
      experience premature failure of the ovaries before the age of 40. There have been no studies&#xD;
      conducted to determine proper hormone replacement therapies for these younger women. Some&#xD;
      research suggests that the usual menopausal hormone replacement therapy is not adequate to&#xD;
      protect young women with premature ovarian failure from developing osteoporosis. Women with&#xD;
      premature ovarian failure have abnormally low levels of androgens circulating in their blood.&#xD;
      This may contribute to the increase risk for osteoporosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will compare two treatment plans for women with premature ovarian failure.&#xD;
      Treatment plan one will be physiological estrogen hormone replacement. Treatment plan two&#xD;
      will be physiological estrogen hormone replacement plus androgen. The study will attempt to&#xD;
      determine which plan is more beneficial to women in relation to osteoporosis and heart&#xD;
      disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The hormones will be contained in patches and given by placing the patches against the&#xD;
      patient's skin. The patches were designed to deliver the same amount of hormone as would be&#xD;
      normally produced by the ovary in young women.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The success of the treatment will be measured by periodically checking the density of&#xD;
      patient's bone in the leg (femoral neck bone) . Researchers will take an initial (baseline)&#xD;
      measurement of bone density before beginning treatment and then once a year, for 3 additional&#xD;
      years, during treatment. The study will also consider bone density of the spine, bone&#xD;
      turnover, heart disease risk factors, and psychological state.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Present menopausal hormone replacement therapy regimens were designed for women who&#xD;
      experience ovarian failure around age 50. At least 1% of women, however, experience premature&#xD;
      ovarian failure before the age of 40, but there have been no studies establishing optimal&#xD;
      hormone replacement therapy regimens for these younger women. Available evidence suggests&#xD;
      that the usual menopausal hormone replacement therapy is not adequate to protect young women&#xD;
      with premature ovarian failure from developing osteoporosis. Women with premature ovarian&#xD;
      failure have abnormally low circulating androgen levels, which may contribute to their risk&#xD;
      for osteoporosis. We plan to compare physiological estrogen replacement with physiological&#xD;
      estrogen plus androgen replacement in young women with premature ovarian failure to determine&#xD;
      which regimen is more beneficial for bone mineral density and other metabolic parameters&#xD;
      related to the risk for cardiovascular disease. This study employs transdermal estradiol and&#xD;
      testosterone &quot;patches&quot; designed to deliver the same amount for each sex steroid normally&#xD;
      produced by the ovary in young women in a physiological manner. Women with premature ovarian&#xD;
      failure will be randomized to receive either estradiol plus placebo patches or estradiol plus&#xD;
      testosterone patches. Both groups will receive cyclic progestin treatment. A group of&#xD;
      age-matched women with normal ovarian function will serve as contemporaneous controls for&#xD;
      bone density and other study measures. The primary outcome parameter is femoral neck bone&#xD;
      mineral density, to be assessed at baseline, and after 1, 2, and 3 years of treatment. Other&#xD;
      outcome parameters include lumbar spine bone mineral density, markers of bone turnover,&#xD;
      cardiovascular disease risk factors, and cognitive function.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>250</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Osteoporosis</condition>
  <condition>Premature Ovarian Failure</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMTDS</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with karyotypically normal spontaneous premature ovarian failure (as defined by&#xD;
        screening protocol 91-CH-0127, i.e. women who have at least 4 months of amenorrhea, two FSH&#xD;
        levels above 40 mIU/ml, at least one month apart, and a normal 46, XX karotype, diagnosed&#xD;
        with premature ovarian failure prior to the age of 40) who are between the age of 18 and 42&#xD;
        years will be candidates.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        General:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Smokers (more than 2 cigarettes per day).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Alcohol users (more than 2 drinks of alcohol per day).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Body mass index (BMI, kg/m(2)) greater than or equal to 30 and less than or equal to 19.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Previous history of hip fracture or other active hip pathology.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Abnormalities of the hip precluding the assessment of bone mineral density.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Major dermatologic disorders, or a history of skin sensitivity to adhesive bandages, tape&#xD;
        or transdermal matrix patches.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Hirsutism score greater than 8.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Acne score greater than 1.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Hysterectomy&#xD;
&#xD;
        Baseline free testosterone (FT) levels above the normal range (greater than 6.3 pg/ml in&#xD;
        our current essay) and/or SHBG levels less than 36 nmol/L.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Medical use:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Any prior treatment in the past 6 months known to affect bone other than estrogen (i.e.,&#xD;
        calcitonin, biphosphonates, fluoride, anabolic steroids, testosterone, or herbal therapy&#xD;
        that contains androstenedione, and DHEA).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Current and/or past use of: diuretics, anticoagulants (heparin, Coumadin), glucocorticoid&#xD;
        drugs, gonadotropin-releasing hormone agonist or antagonist therapy, chemotherapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Medical history of:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Anorexia nervosa, hyperprolactinemia, insulin-dependent diabetes, Cushing's syndrome,&#xD;
        gastrectomy, osteogenesis imperfecta, mastocytosis, rheumatoid arthritis, long-term&#xD;
        parenteral nutrition, hemolytic anemia, hemochromatosis and thalassemia, ankylosing&#xD;
        spondylitis, multiple myeloma, Vitamin D deficiency, Paget's disease, primary&#xD;
        hyperparathyroidism, hyperthyroidism, hypothyroidism, any cancer or any other major&#xD;
        illness.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Contraindications to hormone replacement therapy:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Thromboembolic event associated with previous estrogen use History of endometrial cancer or&#xD;
        hyperplasia&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of breast cancer&#xD;
&#xD;
        Hypertriglyceridemia (fasting triglyceride levels greater than 500 mg/dL)&#xD;
&#xD;
        LDL greater than 190mg/dl&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients taking &quot;statins&quot;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Serum Alkaline phosphatase greater than or equal to 2X the upper limit of normal&#xD;
&#xD;
        Serum GGT greather than or equal to 2X the upper limit of normal&#xD;
&#xD;
        Abnormal values on two or more hepatic panel tests&#xD;
&#xD;
        Undiagnosed Vaginal Bleeding&#xD;
&#xD;
        Known sensitivity to agents&#xD;
&#xD;
        Note: We will include patients with premature ovarian failure on antidepressant&#xD;
        medications, since today's most common antidepressant medication (Prozac) does not have a&#xD;
        major import on cognitive function. However, we will note whether they are on these&#xD;
        medications.&#xD;
&#xD;
        CONTROL SELECTION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Healthy non-pregnant regularly menstruating women (cycles between 21 and 35 days),&#xD;
        non-smokers, non-alcohol users, under no medications, using non-hormonal contraceptive&#xD;
        methods (i.e. barrier methods of contraception, or sterilization) and with no intention to&#xD;
        conceive within the following 3 years.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>32 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalantaridou SN, Davis SR, Nelson LM. Premature ovarian failure. Endocrinol Metab Clin North Am. 1998 Dec;27(4):989-1006. doi: 10.1016/s0889-8529(05)70051-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9922918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2006</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 19, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 27, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Bone</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognition</keyword>
  <keyword>Estrogen</keyword>
  <keyword>Mood</keyword>
  <keyword>Testosterone</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteoporosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovarian Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormone Replacement Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>POF</keyword>
  <keyword>Premature Ovarian Failure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Primary Ovarian Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Menopause, Premature</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

