<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000546</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>90</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL051519</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000546</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stress Reduction and Atherosclerotic CVD in Blacks</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the effectiveness of stress reduction with Transcendental Meditation (TM) on left&#xD;
      ventricular hypertrophy, left ventricular function, blood pressure, psychosocial stress and&#xD;
      quality of life, and cardiovascular disease risk factors.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Blacks in the United States have disproportionately high rates of cardiovascular disease and&#xD;
      mortality. Left ventricular hypertrophy, the primary manifestation of hypertensive heart&#xD;
      disease and a major independent predictor of cardiovascular mortality, is twice as prevalent&#xD;
      in Blacks with hypertension as in whites. Research has implicated chronic socio-environmental&#xD;
      and psychological stress in the etiology of hypertension and left ventricular hypertrophy in&#xD;
      Blacks. The trial seeks to investigate directly the impact of stress reduction programs for&#xD;
      treating hypertensive heart disease in Blacks, since conventional antihypertensive drug&#xD;
      therapies are less successful than expected. Moreover, these therapies frequently have&#xD;
      adverse side effects on quality of life, and have low compliance rates, particularly in&#xD;
      minorities.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The first study conducted between 1994 and 1999 used transcendental meditation for stress&#xD;
      reduction in hypertensive heart disease. The study was randomized and blind. Subjects were&#xD;
      randomized to practice TM for twelve months or to receive health education. The following&#xD;
      measurements were obtained: left ventricular mass and function using echocardiography; clinic&#xD;
      blood pressure and ambulatory blood pressure monitoring; urinary sodium excretion; alcohol&#xD;
      consumption, weight, physical activity, cigarette smoking, and previous use of&#xD;
      antihypertensive medication; various quality of life measures including physical functioning,&#xD;
      psychosocial functioning, subjective symptoms, trait anger and anger-expression, stress&#xD;
      impact scale, personal efficacy and health locus of control, social supports, ego&#xD;
      development, and social desirability.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The trial was part of the Collaborative Projects on Minority Health, an Institute- initiated&#xD;
      program to foster collaborative clinical research that focused on new and improved approaches&#xD;
      for diagnosis, management, and prevention of cardiovascular, lung, and blood diseases in&#xD;
      minorities. The trial was part of a two-grant collaboration on Nonpharmacologic Treatments&#xD;
      for Managing Hypertension in African American Adults. Ernest Johnson (R01HL50516),the Program&#xD;
      Coordinator collaborated with Robert Schneider (R01HL51519). The objectives of their studies&#xD;
      were complementary and the collaborative arrangements allowed them to determine the&#xD;
      effectiveness of different approaches to stress management in comparison with a control group&#xD;
      that was comparable at both sites. In addition, the treatment schedules in both studies&#xD;
      resulted in identical contact time, length of interventions, expectations regarding treatment&#xD;
      effectiveness, and follow-up assessment periods. As a result, a considerable degree of&#xD;
      pooling of data for analysis was possible.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Dr. Schneider's study was renewed in FY 1999 to conduct a randomized, single-blind,&#xD;
      controlled, community-based trial involving 184 African American subjects with known coronary&#xD;
      heart disease. Male and female subjects are enrolled at the on-going field site, Martin&#xD;
      Luther King-Drew Medical Center in inner city Los Angeles. After baseline testing, subjects&#xD;
      are randomized to either active stress reduction with TM or health education control-both in&#xD;
      addition to usual medical care-and posttested after 12 months. The primary outcome is carotid&#xD;
      artery atherosclerosis (IMT) measured non-invasively by quantitative B-mode ultrasonography.&#xD;
      Secondary measures include traditional CVD risk factors (blood pressure, lipids, smoking,&#xD;
      exercise), psychosocial stress, quality of life and cost effectiveness.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in&#xD;
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 1994</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>meditation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Schneider</last_name>
    <affiliation>Maharishi International University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneider RH, Castillo-Richmond A, Alexander CN, Myers H, Kaushik V, Aranguri C, Norris K, Haney C, Rainforth M, Calderon R, Nidich S. Behavioral treatment of hypertensive heart disease in African Americans: rationale and design of a randomized controlled trial. Behav Med. 2001 Summer;27(2):83-95. doi: 10.1080/08964280109595775.</citation>
    <PMID>11763829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castillo-Richmond A, Schneider RH, Alexander CN, Cook R, Myers H, Nidich S, Haney C, Rainforth M, Salerno J. Effects of stress reduction on carotid atherosclerosis in hypertensive African Americans. Stroke. 2000 Mar;31(3):568-73. doi: 10.1161/01.str.31.3.568.</citation>
    <PMID>10700487</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calderon R Jr, Schneider RH, Alexander CN, Myers HF, Nidich SI, Haney C. Stress, stress reduction and hypercholesterolemia in African Americans: a review. Ethn Dis. 1999 Autumn;9(3):451-62.</citation>
    <PMID>10600068</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2005</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 27, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

