<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001979</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>920156</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>92-DK-0156</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001979</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immune System Related Kidney Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Studies of Immunologically-Mediated Kidney Diseases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Kidney diseases related to the immune system include, nephrotic syndrome, glomerulonephritis,&#xD;
      membranous nephropathy, lupus nephritis, and nephritis associated with connective tissue&#xD;
      disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will allow researchers to admit and follow patients suffering from autoimmune&#xD;
      diseases of the kidney. It will attempt to provide information about the causes and specific&#xD;
      abnormalities associated with autoimmune kidney disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with kidney disease as a result of their immune system, and patients with diseases&#xD;
      of the immune system who may later develop kidney disease, will be potential subjects for&#xD;
      this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will undergo a history and physical examination, and standard laboratory test to&#xD;
      more closely understand the causes, signs, symptoms, and responses to medication of these&#xD;
      diseases. Based on these evaluations the patients may qualify as candidates for other&#xD;
      experimental studies. At any time these patients may be asked to submit blood or urine&#xD;
      samples for further research....&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Description:&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study evaluates participants with known or suspected immunologically-mediated kidney&#xD;
      diseases, including but not limited to nephrotic syndrome, glomerulonephritis, membranous&#xD;
      nephropathy, lupus nephritis, and nephritis associated with other systemic or connective&#xD;
      tissue disorders. Participants who have immunologically-mediated diseases with potential for&#xD;
      kidney disease will be evaluated as well. Studies will include characterization of the&#xD;
      clinical and laboratory features of these disorders, studies of natural history and&#xD;
      complications, evaluation of responses to standard treatment. Blood and urine samples will be&#xD;
      collected for immunological research conducted under this protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Objectives:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  To facilitate the program of research on immunologically-mediated kidney diseases:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Better understand rare forms of immunologically-mediated renal disorders, those with&#xD;
           atypical renal disease, or those whose renal diseases have not been fully characterized.&#xD;
           Enrolled participants will serve as a catalyst for development of new therapeutic&#xD;
           interventions.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Exploratory:&#xD;
&#xD;
      To conduct further research to fully characterize immunologicallymediated kidney diseases:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Development of assays for novel antibodies.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Search for additional antibodies involved in the pathogenesis of membranous nephropathy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Assess changes in metabolic and endocrine function during nephrotic state and during&#xD;
           remission.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Identify disease-causing memory B cells in participants with membranous nephropathy and&#xD;
           correlation with membranous nephropathy relapse. Assess biological effects of&#xD;
           phospholipase A2-receptor antibody epitope on the isolated memory B-cells.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Computational analysis of renal structures which may provide predictive method that&#xD;
           would discriminate progressors from non-progressors beyond sclerosis in membranous&#xD;
           nephropathy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 25, 1992</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Provision of biospecimens</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>Patients with autoimmune diseases for whom there are no current experimental treatment protocols can be admitted for study and follow-up; they will provide a ready pool of candidates who can be asked to provide blood specimens for ongoing laboratory studies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Disease</condition>
  <condition>Nephrotic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with known or suspected immunologically-mediated kidney diseases or immunologically-mediated diseases with potential for kidney disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with known or suspected immunologically-mediated kidney diseases, including but&#xD;
        not limited to, nephrotic syndrome, glomerulonephritis, membranous nephropathy, lupus&#xD;
        nephritis, and nephritis associated with other systemic or connective tissue disorders, or&#xD;
        immunologically-mediated diseases with the potential for kidney disease.@@@&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Male or female participants greater than or equal to 18 years of age and children 10-17&#xD;
        years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participants with known, proven, or suspected immunologically-mediated kidney diseases,&#xD;
        including but not limited to nephrotic syndrome, glomerulonephritis, membranous&#xD;
        nephropathy, lupus nephritis, and nephritis associated with other systemic or connective&#xD;
        tissue disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participants who have Immunologically-mediated diseases with the potential for kidney&#xD;
        disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Ability of the participant or guardian to understand and the willingness of the participant&#xD;
        or guardian to provide written informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concomitant medical problems which would confound the interpretation of studies of the&#xD;
        immunologic kidney disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concomitant medical, surgical or other conditions for which inadequate facilities or funds&#xD;
        are available to support their care at the NIH.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Meryl A Waldman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Meryl A Waldman, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-6990</phone>
    <email>waldmanm@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY dial 711</phone_ext>
      <email>ccopr@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1992-DK-0156.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 23, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 20, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 21, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kidney Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Kidney Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nephrotic Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nephrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

