<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005366</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4253</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL049427</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005366</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Biobehavioral Mechanisms of Blood Pressure Regulation</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate the role of biobehavioral factors in the pathogenesis of concentric left&#xD;
      ventricular hypertrophy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Hypertension is more prevalent in Black than white men, and is more prevalent in men than&#xD;
      women. Furthermore, even controlling for blood pressure, concentric left ventricular&#xD;
      hypertrophy, an early structural adaptation of hypertension, is more prevalent in Black than&#xD;
      white men, and more prevalent in men than women. Concentric left ventricular hypertrophy is&#xD;
      the strongest predictor, other than age, of the cardiovascular morbidity associated with high&#xD;
      blood pressure.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      In a biracial sample, concentric left ventricular hypertrophy and concentric remodelling were&#xD;
      assessed by echocardiographic measures of left ventricular mass and relative wall thickness.&#xD;
      Laboratory procedures were used to: (i) assess hemodynamic and neurohumoral responses during&#xD;
      exposure to a diverse battery of physical and psychological stressors, and; (ii) evaluate&#xD;
      alpha and beta adrenergic receptor responsiveness, baroreceptor reflex gain and minimal&#xD;
      forearm vascular resistance. Since blood pressure during a typical workday was an established&#xD;
      predictor of left ventricular hypertrophy, it was also assessed. A new biobehavioral model&#xD;
      was tested that implicated the hemodynamic pattern of behaviorally-evoked pressor responses&#xD;
      in the pathogenesis of concentric left ventricular hypertrophy. One prediction of this model&#xD;
      was that a predisposition to exhibit increased vascular resistance during stress&#xD;
      (characteristic of black men) would favor the development of concentric hypertrophy. Thus,&#xD;
      systemic vascular resistance responses, evaluated in the laboratory, were hypothesized to&#xD;
      independently predict left ventricular mass and relative wall thickness, even after&#xD;
      controlling for established risk factors, including workday blood pressure. Sympathetic&#xD;
      nervous system function was examined to test hypothesized mechanisms responsible for race and&#xD;
      gender differences in the hemodynamic patterns of blood pressure regulation. The results of&#xD;
      these studies emphasized the importance of race and gender in prescribing pharmacological&#xD;
      and/or behavioral treatment for hypertensive heart disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in&#xD;
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1993</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 1998</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>39 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watkins LL, Grossman P, Sherwood A. Noninvasive assessment of baroreflex control in borderline hypertension. Comparison with the phenylephrine method. Hypertension. 1996 Aug;28(2):238-43. doi: 10.1161/01.hyp.28.2.238.</citation>
    <PMID>8707388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sherwood A, May CW, Siegel WC, Blumenthal JA. Ethnic differences in hemodynamic responses to stress in hypertensive men and women. Am J Hypertens. 1995 Jun;8(6):552-7. doi: 10.1016/0895-7061(95)00036-O.</citation>
    <PMID>7662238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blumenthal JA, Thyrum ET, Gullette ED, Sherwood A, Waugh R. Do exercise and weight loss reduce blood pressure in patients with mild hypertension? N C Med J. 1995 Feb;56(2):92-5.</citation>
    <PMID>7898595</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sherwood A, Hinderliter AL, Light KC. Physiological determinants of hyperreactivity to stress in borderline hypertension. Hypertension. 1995 Mar;25(3):384-90. doi: 10.1161/01.hyp.25.3.384.</citation>
    <PMID>7875764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carels RA, Blumenthal JA, Sherwood A. Emotional responsivity during daily life: relationship to psychosocial functioning and ambulatory blood pressure. Int J Psychophysiol. 2000 Apr;36(1):25-33. doi: 10.1016/s0167-8760(99)00101-4.</citation>
    <PMID>10700620</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sherwood A, Johnson K, Blumenthal JA, Hinderliter AL. Endothelial function and hemodynamic responses during mental stress. Psychosom Med. 1999 May-Jun;61(3):365-70. doi: 10.1097/00006842-199905000-00017.</citation>
    <PMID>10367618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carels RA, Szczepanski R, Blumenthal JA, Sherwood A. Blood pressure reactivity and marital distress in employed women. Psychosom Med. 1998 Sep-Oct;60(5):639-43. doi: 10.1097/00006842-199809000-00022.</citation>
    <PMID>9773771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watkins LL, Grossman P, Krishnan R, Sherwood A. Anxiety and vagal control of heart rate. Psychosom Med. 1998 Jul-Aug;60(4):498-502. doi: 10.1097/00006842-199807000-00018.</citation>
    <PMID>9710297</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carels RA, Sherwood A, Blumenthal JA. Psychosocial influences on blood pressure during daily life. Int J Psychophysiol. 1998 Mar;28(2):117-29. doi: 10.1016/s0167-8760(97)00090-1.</citation>
    <PMID>9545650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carels RA, Sherwood A, Szczepanski R, Blumenthal JA. Ambulatory blood pressure and marital distress in employed women. Behav Med. 2000 Summer;26(2):80-5. doi: 10.1080/08964280009595755.</citation>
    <PMID>11147293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2001</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

