<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005453</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4441</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01HL048992</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005453</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adherence in Clinical Trials-Induction Strategies</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To examine the effects of two strategies of inducing enhanced adherence to medication in the&#xD;
      context of a clinical trial: habit training versus habit training plus problem solving.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The success of any therapeutic intervention, whether preventive or curative, is ultimately&#xD;
      dependent on the individual's adherence to treatment. Unfortunately, the failure of a large&#xD;
      percentage of patients to adhere to prescribed medical regimens is a widely recognized and&#xD;
      well documented phenomenon. It has been estimated that as many as 50 percent of patients do&#xD;
      not take their prescribed medications, and of those remaining, less than two-thirds take&#xD;
      their medication as prescribed.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The interventions, implemented at the outset of pharmacologic intervention within the&#xD;
      clinical trial, were timed to yield maximum effectiveness. Such randomized induction studies&#xD;
      had not yet been undertaken. By capitalizing on a new unobtrusive assessment technique that&#xD;
      generated the time of medication intake over prolonged periods, the study produced a unique&#xD;
      set of data suitable for the study of recurring cycles in medication intake patterns.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study was part of a two grant initiative entitled &quot;Evaluation of Adherence Interventions&#xD;
      in Clinical Trials&quot;. The initiative was developed by the Behavioral Medicine Branch staff and&#xD;
      Clinical Trials Branch staff as well as members of the Clinical Applications and Prevention&#xD;
      Advisory Committee Behavioral Medicine and Prevention Working Groups. The initiative was&#xD;
      released in September, 1991 and awarded in September, 1992.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Randomized, double-blind, two-group design. Within each of the groups, half of the subjects&#xD;
      were on lovastatin and half on placebo. The main outcome measure was medication intake&#xD;
      monitored daily and unobtrusively with the MEMS electronic monitor. For each subject, event&#xD;
      time series of six months duration were obtained. The effect of these interventions were&#xD;
      determined on average adherence at two and six months; and variability of adherence. In&#xD;
      addition, the relative cost effectiveness of each intervention was examined by a&#xD;
      recalculation of sample size needs based upon increased adherence and related cholesterol&#xD;
      lowering. Ancillary goals of the study included: determining the components of variability of&#xD;
      medication intake using statistical modeling techniques; and covariates of treatment effects,&#xD;
      including baseline daily hassles, problem solving skills, and generalized expectancy for&#xD;
      success.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in&#xD;
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1992</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1997</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burke LE, Dunbar-Jacob JM, Hill MN. Compliance with cardiovascular disease prevention strategies: a review of the research. Ann Behav Med. 1997 Summer;19(3):239-63. doi: 10.1007/BF02892289.</citation>
    <PMID>9603699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2002</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 13, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

