<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00006204</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NIAAASAL11929</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00006204</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Drug Treatment for Depressed Alcoholics (Naltrexone/Fluoxetine)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Combined Pharmacotherapy in Depressed Alcoholics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the effects of combing naltrexone and fluoxetine (Prozac) versus&#xD;
      fluoxetine and placebo in alcoholics with co-occurring major depression. Both groups will&#xD;
      actively participate in the 6-month study, which includes weekly individual Dual Disorders&#xD;
      Recovery Counseling during the first month and every two weeks during the second through&#xD;
      sixth months, plus the naltrexone and fluoxetine or fluoxetine and placebo. Subjects will&#xD;
      complete follow-up assessments at 9 and 12 months.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We propose to test the efficacy of the combination of naltrexone and fluoxetine versus&#xD;
      fluoxetine alone in the treatment of patients with alcoholism and co-morbid major depression&#xD;
      in a double-blind, placebo- controlled, randomized, parallel group trial. With nearly eight&#xD;
      million affected individuals in the U.S., co-morbid alcoholism and major depressive disorder&#xD;
      represent a significant public health problem. The presence of co-morbidity has a significant&#xD;
      negative impact on treatment response and outcome, resulting in increased risk for suicide&#xD;
      and increased rates of costly inpatient psychiatric care. Effective pharmacologic treatments&#xD;
      addressing thee dual disorders are lacking. Only partial response has been obtained in&#xD;
      studies evaluating anti- depressant monotherapy in depressed alcoholics. Our previous work&#xD;
      with the SSRI fluoxetine has demonstrative the positive results published to date in severely&#xD;
      depressed alcoholics. Our previous work with the SSRI fluoxetine has demonstrative the most&#xD;
      positive results published to date in severely depressed alcoholics. The fluoxetine group in&#xD;
      that study, however, displayed only a partial treatment response, with low abstinence rates&#xD;
      and persistent depressive symptoms and alcohol abuse. However, our original and extended&#xD;
      pilot work evaluating the usefulness of combined naltrexone and fluoxetine suggest a robust&#xD;
      response, with a significant decrease in alcohol use and depressive symptoms. Our study of&#xD;
      potential interactions between these two medications documents that naltrexone does not&#xD;
      increase fluoxetine or norfluoxetine blood levels in most patients. Our proposed study will&#xD;
      build on our previous work and established record both in conducting medication efficacy&#xD;
      trials in this complex and high risk population, and in developing fundamental&#xD;
      pharmacological methodologies necessary to investigate the proposed rug interaction studies.&#xD;
      The timeliness of our proposed study is underscored by the high prevalence of this co-morbid&#xD;
      condition and by the widely but untested use of the combined medication treatment in clinical&#xD;
      practice. Thus, our study our will fill an important gap in our knowledge regarding the&#xD;
      treatment of high risk clinical population. We hypothesize that combined fluoxetine and&#xD;
      naltrexone treatment will offer enhanced treatment for alcoholics with co-morbid major&#xD;
      depression. While the fluoxetine will target the depressive disorders in addition to the&#xD;
      compulsive consumatory behavior related to alcoholism, the naltrexone will target the&#xD;
      positive reinforcing effect and release risk related to pathological alcohol use. We request&#xD;
      five years of support to achieve the following aims: 1) Examine the efficacy of naltrexone&#xD;
      plus fluoxetine compared to fluoxetine and placebo in the treatment of patients with co-&#xD;
      morbid DSM-IV alcohol dependence and unipolar major depression.; 2) Assess specific&#xD;
      predictors of medication response; 3) Conduct a prospective assessment of the effect of&#xD;
      persistent depressive symptoms on alcohol use. One hundred and six acutely depressed and&#xD;
      actively drinking subjects will be randomized and prospectively followed during a 6 month&#xD;
      double-blind study, and a 6-month post-treatment follow-up phase.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol use as measured by the Timeline</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Follow-back method</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depressive symptoms as measured by the Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment>106</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcoholism</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>naltrexone (Revia)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluoxetine (Prozac)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Meets criteria for alcohol dependence and comorbid major depressive disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Absence of any hazardous drinking within 48 to 120 hours (defined as more than or&#xD;
             equal to three drinks/day for females and more than or equal to four drinks/day for&#xD;
             males).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No more than 15 days of complete abstinence prior to study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Psychiatric conditions including schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, any&#xD;
             non-bipolar psychiatric disorder, bipolar disorders, primary anxiety disorder, mental&#xD;
             retardation, and signs of impaired cognitive functioning.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any non-alcohol substance dependence except for nicotine.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Opioid abuse, opioid dependence, or on opioid maintenance treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Neurological conditions including epilepsy, history of brain injury, encephalitis, or&#xD;
             any organic brain syndrome or focally abnormal electroencephalograph examination&#xD;
             (EEG).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Medical conditions including severe cardiac, liver, kidney, endocrine, hematologic,&#xD;
             other impairing or unstable medical condition or impending surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Persistent elevation of liver enzymes indicating active liver disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Females who are pregnant, or unable or unwilling to use reliable birth control&#xD;
             methods.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unable to read or understand study forms and agree to informed consent.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ihsan M. Salloum, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Western Psychiatric Institute, Clinic of the University of Pittsburgh Medical Center, Pittsburgh, PA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Psychiatry, Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic of the University of Pittsburgh Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2007</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 11, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 12, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 7, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 7, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Alcoholism</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol Dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Naltrexone</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluoxetine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Naltrexone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluoxetine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

