<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005909</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000141</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-HG-0141</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005909</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Alkaptonuria</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical, Biochemical, and Molecular Investigations Into Alkaptonuria</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to gain a better understanding of alkaptonuria and collect&#xD;
      medical data on patients who may later participate in new drug trials for this rare genetic&#xD;
      disease. In alkaptonuria, a pigment called homogentisic acid collects in bone and connective&#xD;
      tissue, causing arthritis and eventually bone fractures, and also causes discoloration in the&#xD;
      ears and whites of the eyes. Some patients also develop kidney stones and heart valve&#xD;
      problems. Alkaptonuria has not been studied for decades; and scientists expect to gain&#xD;
      comprehensive clinical information using current medical techniques.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with alkaptonuria who are at least two years of age may be eligible for this study.&#xD;
      Participants will be evaluated at NIH s Clinical Center for 3 to 5 days every 2 to 3 years.&#xD;
      They will have a medical history, physical examination, routine blood and urine tests. Blood&#xD;
      may also be collected to measure a type of collagen that indicates new bone formation and to&#xD;
      analyze DNA for genetic studies. 24-hour urine collections will be done to measure organic&#xD;
      acids and homogentisic acid excretion, assess overall kidney function, and evaluate bone&#xD;
      metabolism. A total of 89.5 ml (about 6 tablespoons) of blood will be drawn for these studies&#xD;
      in adults and 51 ml (about 3 tablespoons) in children.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will (may) also have bone X-rays, kidney ultrasound, brain and chest computerized&#xD;
      tomography (CT) scans, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans of affected joints,&#xD;
      electrocardiograms, echocardiogram, lung function tests, and a hearing test. Photographs of&#xD;
      the face and full body (with underwear on) will be taken.&#xD;
&#xD;
      As medically indicated, patients will also have consultations with dentistry and&#xD;
      ophthalmology, with physical therapy and rehabilitation medicine for arthritis management,&#xD;
      and with cardiology for heart valve evaluation. When appropriate, patients may also have&#xD;
      dermatology, pulmonology and neurology consultations.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The information from this study will enable doctors to better advise patients with&#xD;
      alkaptonuria about their disease and treatment options. It will also prepare the way for&#xD;
      clinical studies of a new drug that blocks production of homogentisic acid.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Alkaptonuria is a rare autosomal recessive disorder in which homogentisic acid accumulates&#xD;
      and destroys connective tissue and bone, creating a condition called ochronosis. Symptoms&#xD;
      generally begin in the third or fourth decade and progress to incapacitating spondylosis,&#xD;
      arthropathy, and fractures by the sixth to eighth decades. Cardiac valve deterioration and&#xD;
      renal and prostrate calculi also occur. Diagnosis is made by measurement of gram quantities&#xD;
      of urinary homogentisic acid, which turns black on alkali treatment or exposure to oxygen. In&#xD;
      the body, homogentisic acid forms a characteristic blue color in the cartilage of the ear and&#xD;
      brown color in the sclera of the eye. The gene for homogentisic acid oxidase was isolated in&#xD;
      1996, and scores of different mutations have been defined. Only symptomatic treatment is&#xD;
      available. We propose to investigate up to 200 alkaptonuric patients, particularly adults,&#xD;
      during 5-day admissions, to define the disorder using current medical techniques. We will use&#xD;
      our expertise in this disease to advise the population in terms of prognosis and therapy.&#xD;
      Mutation analysis with correlation of genotype and phenotype, will be performed as a&#xD;
      secondary goal. Finally, we will use this protocol to recruit patients into protocol&#xD;
      05-HG-0076. &quot;Long-term Clinical Trial of Nitisinone in Alkaptonuria.&quot; Nitisinone is a very&#xD;
      promising drug which inhibits the formation of homogentisic acid. The present protocol does&#xD;
      not include treatment with nitisinone. Instead, we will examine patients, measure baseline&#xD;
      excretion of homogentisic acid on repeated 24-hour urines, and characterize the signs and&#xD;
      symptoms of alkaptonuria at different ages.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 21, 2000</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To delineate the clinical and laboratory findings of alkaptonuria, using state-of-the-art medical technology such as cardiac CT, MRI, and echocardiograms.</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>To delineate the clinical and laboratory findings of alkaptonuria, using state-of-the-art medical technology such as cardiac CT, MRI, and echocardiograms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To understand the natural history and rates of progression to identify suitable outcome measures for future studies.</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>To understand the natural history and rates of progression to identify suitable outcome measures for future studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Alkaptonuria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alkaptonuria</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with confirmed or suspected alkaptonuria</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with confirmed or suspected alkaptonuria@@@&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        All patients entering this study will carry the diagnosis of alkaptonuria, although we will&#xD;
        confirm this diagnosis during the admission.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients will be excluded if they cannot travel to the NIH due to their medical condition,&#xD;
        are less than two years old, or are in imminent danger of death due to, e.g., cardiac&#xD;
        involvement.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wendy J Introne, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wendy J Introne, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-8879</phone>
    <email>wi2p@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2000-HG-0141.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 18, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 14, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Homogentisic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Ochronosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Inborn Error of Metabolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Enzyme Defect</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <keyword>Alkaptonuria</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alkaptonuria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ochronosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>.This data will be deidentified.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>While the study is open.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>All data sharing will be approved by the NHGRI Tech Transfer Office.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

