<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005749</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5061</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R18HL052704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005749</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Project Andale--Increasing Exercise in Hispanic Women</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>San Diego State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>San Diego State University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the differential effectiveness of a culturally tailored program to shape and&#xD;
      maintain moderate intensity physical activity and to improve cardiorespiratory fitness among&#xD;
      low SES sedentary Latino women.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Latino women are at high risk for cardiovascular (CVD) and other chronic diseases, in part,&#xD;
      due to sedentary lifestyle, obesity, and poor fitness. Few studies assess long-term physical&#xD;
      activity, fewer observe maintenance and none have demonstrated effective procedures for&#xD;
      sustaining exercise. Only one study has demonstrated increased moderate exercise and none has&#xD;
      demonstrated maintenance of physical activity among Latino women. Theoretically-based&#xD;
      procedures (shaping, contingency management, relapse prevention, and social reinforcement)&#xD;
      hypothesized as necessary to maintain physical activity had not yet been tested&#xD;
      experimentally.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The 210 Latinas were assigned at random to one of three groups: one six month physical&#xD;
      activity intervention, one physical activity plus maintenance intervention, and one safety&#xD;
      education control. Exercise training emphasized walking. Bilingual exercise leaders, aided by&#xD;
      peer models from the community, used shaping procedures to establish daily walking in&#xD;
      participants. In the maintenance program, family incentives reinforced transfer to community&#xD;
      exercise and were used to establish positive feedback loops to promote activity within the&#xD;
      family. Peer led community exercise sessions, and community activism were also used to&#xD;
      establish social networks which reinforced sustained physical activity.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Program support was faded out as naturally occurring social support for Community exercise&#xD;
      was established. Four (baseline, post-intervention, post-maintenance, follow-up), repeated&#xD;
      measures over 24 months assessed fitness (VO2max), physical activity (PAR), and CVD risk&#xD;
      factors. Theoretically important mediating variables, such as self-efficacy, social support,&#xD;
      stage of change for exercise, decisional balance, and home exercise environment were&#xD;
      explored. Repeated measures analyses were used to determine significant differences among&#xD;
      groups, time and group by time main effects. This study was the first to attempt to engineer&#xD;
      maintenance of physical activity among minority women. Results will provide a model to be&#xD;
      used to sustain physical activity and reduce the risk of cardiovascular and other diseases.&#xD;
      If effective, this analysis will also serve as a model for designing programs to sustain&#xD;
      physical activity in the increasingly sedentary general population.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study was renewed in January 2000 to continue through December 2001.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1996</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2002</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melbourne Hovell</last_name>
    <affiliation>San Diego State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>August 2004</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 11, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 11, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 12, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

