<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001457</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>950199</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>95-DK-0199</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001457</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lamivudine for Chronic Hepatitis B</brief_title>
  <official_title>Lamivudine for Chronic Hepatitis B</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic hepatitis B is a disease of the liver caused by the hepatitis B virus. It affects&#xD;
      nearly 1 million Americans. Approximately 25% of patients with chronic hepatitis B will&#xD;
      develop liver cirrhosis and 5% of patients will develop liver cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Presently, two medications have been shown effective in the treatment of hepatitis B:&#xD;
      lamivudine and alpha interferon. Alpha interferon (an antiviral drug that acts through the&#xD;
      immune system) is given by injection once daily or three times a week for four to six months.&#xD;
      Lamivudine (also known as 3-thiacytidine: 3TC) is an antiviral medication given as a pill&#xD;
      once a day for twelve months. These treatments have been known to provide long-term&#xD;
      improvement in one third of patients receiving them.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In previous research, the drug lamivudine was shown to stop the growth of the hepatitis B&#xD;
      virus and to lead marked decreases in the levels of hepatitis B virus and to improvements in&#xD;
      the disease in 50 to 70% of patients. However, once lamivudine therapy was discontinued the&#xD;
      virus returned to levels noted before the therapy began. In those studies lamivudine was&#xD;
      given for 3 to 12 months then discontinued. This study will investigate the safety and&#xD;
      effectiveness of long-term therapy with lamivudine.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will select 60 patients diagnosed with hepatitis B. After a thorough medical&#xD;
      examination and liver biopsy, subjects will be given lamivudine. The drug will be taken by&#xD;
      mouth in tablet form (100 mg) once a day for up to 5 years. Subjects will undergo regular&#xD;
      check-ups and after 1 year of therapy be admitted to the Clinical Center for another medical&#xD;
      examination and liver biopsy to assess progress. Patients who have benefitted from the&#xD;
      therapy will continue taking the medication for up to 5 years. A third liver biopsy will be&#xD;
      done during the last year of treatment. The effectiveness of lamivudine will be determined by&#xD;
      whether levels of hepatitis B virus decrease in the blood, whether liver enzymes improve, and&#xD;
      whether inflammation and scarring decreases in the liver biopsies.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To assess the safety, antiviral activity and clinical benefit of lamivudine (3-thiacytidine:&#xD;
      3TC) in chronic hepatitis B, we will treat 60 patients with oral lamivudine in a dose of 100&#xD;
      mg daily for up to five years. Lamivudine is a nucleoside analogue which is used extensively&#xD;
      in patients with HIV infection and is being studied in controlled trials in chronic hepatitis&#xD;
      B. In this study, we will evaluate lamivudine in patients with four different forms of&#xD;
      chronic hepatitis B: (A) Atypical serology (HBeAg negative), (B) extra-hepatic&#xD;
      manifestations, (C) chronic delta hepatitis, (D) typical HBeAg- positive chronic hepatitis B.&#xD;
      After evaluation and liver biopsy, patients will receive lamivudine, 100 mg orally once daily&#xD;
      for 1 year, being monitored at regular intervals for symptoms of liver disease, side effects&#xD;
      of lamivudine, serum biochemical and hematologic indices, and serologic markers of hepatitis&#xD;
      B (and D) virus replication. At one year, patients will have a repeat medical evaluation and&#xD;
      liver biopsy. If there is virologic, biochemical or histologic evidence of benefit, therapy&#xD;
      will be continued thereafter for up to 5 years. Patients who develop viral resistance to&#xD;
      lamivudine may be offered therapy with higher doses of lamivudine (300 mg per day). The&#xD;
      activity of lamivudine will be assessed by changes in levels of HBV DNA or HDV RNA during&#xD;
      treatment and its efficacy by loss of viral markers and improvements in aminotransferases and&#xD;
      liver histology.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date>September 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>60</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Hepatitis B</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Hepatitis D</condition>
  <condition>Glomerulonephritis</condition>
  <condition>Polyarteritis Nodosa</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lamivudine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age 18 years or above, male or female.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Known presence of HBsAg in serum for at least 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Liver biopsy histology showing chronic hepatitis with or without cirrhosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Previous therapy with alpha interferon without a lasting effect or intolerance to alpha&#xD;
        interferon, due to side effects.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Written informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Group A: For patients with chronic hepatitis B with atypical serology: absence of HBeAg&#xD;
        from serum despite elevations in serum aminotransferases, such as that the average levels&#xD;
        are greater than 55 U/L (approximately 1.3 times the upper limit of the normal range) based&#xD;
        upon two determinations taken at least one month apart during the 6 months before entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Group B: For patients with glomerulonephritis: proteinuria of greater than 1 gm per 24&#xD;
        hours. For patients with polyarteritis, radiological proof of arteritis and involvement of&#xD;
        at least on organ system outside of the liver.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Group C: For patients with chronic delta hepatitis: anti-HDV in serum and HDV antigen in&#xD;
        liver biopsy or HDV RNA in serum and elevations in serum aminotransferases, such that the&#xD;
        average levels are greater than 55 U/L based upon two determinations taken at least one&#xD;
        month apart during the 6 months before entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Group D: For patients with chronic hepatitis B and typical serology: HBeAg and HBV DNA in&#xD;
        serum but ineligibility to enter the multicenter trial of lamivudine either because of&#xD;
        previous receipt of interferon and intolerable side effects, refusal to receive interferon&#xD;
        again, because of normal serum aminotransferases, or lack of availability of the trial.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnant or if capable of bearing or fathering children must practice adequate&#xD;
        contraception.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Significant systemic illnesses other than liver diseases, including congestive heart&#xD;
        failure, renal failure, chronic pancreatitis, diabetes mellitus with poor control.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pre-existing bone marrow compromise: hematocrit must be greater than 30%, white blood cell&#xD;
        count must be greater than 2000 mm(3), platelets must be greater than 70,000 mm(3).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Creatinine clearance must be greater than 50 cc/min.&#xD;
&#xD;
        A history of clinically apparent pancreatitis or evidence of subclinically pancreatitis as&#xD;
        shown by serum amylase values twice the upper limits of the normal range and abnormalities&#xD;
        of the pancreas on computerized tomography or other imaging studies of the abdomen.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Irreversibly severe cirrhosis as defined by Child's stage C.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of anti-HIV or anti-HCV with HCV RNA in serum.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Immunosuppressive therapy requiring use of more than 10 mg of prednisone (or its&#xD;
        equivalent) per day.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Other antiviral therapy for chronic hepatitis B within the previous 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Sensory or motor neuropathy apparent from medical history and physical examination.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoofnagle JH, di Bisceglie AM. The treatment of chronic viral hepatitis. N Engl J Med. 1997 Jan 30;336(5):347-56. doi: 10.1056/NEJM199701303360507. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>9011789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perrillo RP, Gelb L, Campbell C, Wellinghoff W, Ellis FR, Overby L, Aach RD. Hepatitis B e antigen, DNA polymerase activity, and infection of household contacts with hepatitis B virus. Gastroenterology. 1979 Jun;76(6):1319-25.</citation>
    <PMID>437428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beasley RP, Hwang LY, Lin CC, Chien CS. Hepatocellular carcinoma and hepatitis B virus. A prospective study of 22 707 men in Taiwan. Lancet. 1981 Nov 21;2(8256):1129-33. doi: 10.1016/s0140-6736(81)90585-7. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>6118576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2005</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Nucleoside Analogues</keyword>
  <keyword>Delta Hepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Glomerulonephritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Polyarteritis Nodosa</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis Mutants</keyword>
  <keyword>3TC</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Hepatitis B</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Hepatitis D</keyword>
  <keyword>Cirrhosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Lamivudine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis D, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulonephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polyarteritis Nodosa</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lamivudine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

