<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000619</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>122</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000619</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation Study of Congestive Heart Failure and Pulmonary Artery Catheterization Effectiveness (ESCAPE)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare the efficacy of Pulmonary Artery Catheterization (PAC)-directed treatment strategy&#xD;
      to a non-invasive treatment strategy on morbidity and mortality in patients with severe,&#xD;
      class IV New York Heart Association (NYHA) congestive heart failure. A secondary objective&#xD;
      was to determine costs and resource utilization of PAC-directed treatment strategy compared&#xD;
      to non-invasive treatment strategy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Congestive heart failure constitutes one of the major categories of morbidity, particularly&#xD;
      in the elderly, and is responsible for the utilization of significant resources, including a&#xD;
      large number of hospitalizations (estimated at 800,000 to 2.3 million per year) and related&#xD;
      health care costs. In 1993, 4.7 million Americans carried the diagnosis of CHF, and about&#xD;
      400,000 new cases are diagnosed every year. It is estimated that there are 800,000 to 1.2&#xD;
      million CHF patients with NYHA class III-IV symptoms. The diagnosis and treatment of CHF and&#xD;
      its episodes of decompensation can be facilitated by pulmonary artery catheter use, but its&#xD;
      efficacy is highly dependent on the physician's experience in the treatment of such patients.&#xD;
      Recently, concern has been raised about the benefits of PAC, also known as Swan-Ganz&#xD;
      catheterization.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In response to concerns about the benefits and safety of PAC, the NHLBI and the Food and Drug&#xD;
      Administration (FDA) co-sponsored a workshop in August 1997 entitiled &quot;Pulmonary Artery&#xD;
      Catheterization and Clinical Outcomes (PACCO)&quot;. The purpose of the workshop was to provide an&#xD;
      objective assessment of the state-of-the-science of PAC and its various uses. Experts in&#xD;
      critical care, pulmonary medicine, cardiovascular medicine, surgery, pediatric cardiology,&#xD;
      nursing, biostatistics, ethics, and medical economics identified several important clinical&#xD;
      areas as priorities for clinical trials; persistent/refractory congestive heart failure (NYHA&#xD;
      class IV) received top priority to test whether a PAC-directed treatment strategy achieves a&#xD;
      better and less costly long-term outcome compared to a non-invasive treatment strategy. In&#xD;
      addition to providing data on outcome, hospital utilization, and costs, the study would have&#xD;
      additional benefits. For example, it would provide a clear benchmark for testing other&#xD;
      technologies, now in developmental stages, that could supplant PAC in the future. Finally,&#xD;
      the study would provide the basis for developing competency requirements for physicians,&#xD;
      nurses, and others who insert and use pulmonary artery catheters, which was a strong&#xD;
      recommendation of the PACCO Workshop.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients were randomized into two treatment arms: A total of 218 patients were assigned into&#xD;
      a treatment strategy without PAC hemodynamic monitoring (Usual Group) and 215 patients into a&#xD;
      treatment strategy guided by PAC (Hemodynamic Group). The primary endpoint was the combined&#xD;
      endpoint of rehospitalization and death.&#xD;
&#xD;
      For all patients randomized, therapy was tailored to the ultimate goal of discharge on an&#xD;
      oral medical regimen to provide better relief of CHF symptoms, to reduce filling pressures&#xD;
      and to maintain adequate perfusion. These goals were the same for both groups, but in the&#xD;
      Usual Group therapy was adjusted according to clinical assessment alone, while in the&#xD;
      PAC-directed group, actual measurement of hemodynamics was used to supplement clinical&#xD;
      assessment. The oral medical regimen for discharge was designed by the attending heart&#xD;
      failure physician based on the standard available medications of angiotensin converting&#xD;
      enzyme inhibitors (ACEI), nitrates, hydralazine, furosemide and other diuretic agents.&#xD;
      Intravenous diuretics were used when major diuresis was desired with subsequent change to&#xD;
      oral diuretics at least 48 hours before discharge. Physicians could also use low dose&#xD;
      infusions of dopamine or dobutamine to facilitate diuresis. Intravenous nitroprusside could&#xD;
      be used in either group.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the Usual Group, therapy was tailored to the following goals: a) absence of evidence of&#xD;
      elevated intracardiac filling pressures; relief of orthopnea; relief of abdominal discomfort&#xD;
      attributed to hepatosplenchnic congestion; resolution of peripheral edema, ascites, and&#xD;
      rales; reduction of jugular venous distension to 5 cm or less above sternal angle; and b)&#xD;
      adequate peripheral perfusion; warm extremities, if they could be achieved, and pulse&#xD;
      pressure 25 percent or more , or, if less, the greatest which could be achieved. Either&#xD;
      during or after hemodynamic monitoring, therapy could be adjusted to achieve the clinical&#xD;
      goals above and further adjusted, if necessary to maintain adequate blood pressure and renal&#xD;
      function for all patients. Patients for whom therapy was adjusted without hemodynamic&#xD;
      monitoring could crossover for hemodynamic monitoring at any time they reached certain&#xD;
      criteria. The criteria for crossover included: need to add intravenous inotropic agents above&#xD;
      3 mcg/kg/minute to prevent symptomatic hypotension; repeated inability to discontinue&#xD;
      low-dose inotropic agents; or renal insufficiency.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the PAC-directed hemodynamic arm, therapy was adjusted to achieve specific hemodynamic&#xD;
      goals in addition to the clinical goals in the Usual Group. These goals could include:&#xD;
      pulmonary capillary wedge pressure (PCWP) 15 mm Hg or less; right atrial pressure 8mm Hg or&#xD;
      less unless PCWP is 15 mm Hg or less; maintenance of systolic blood pressure of 80 or above,&#xD;
      except for occasional transient decreases to lower levels after oral medications.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Regardless of the goals by which therapy was adjusted in the hospital, the following&#xD;
      conditions were met prior to discharge: 24 hours on oral medications alone without major&#xD;
      medication change except for anticoagulation, and 48 hours after discontinuation of any&#xD;
      intravenous inotropic medications; stable fluid balance; patient education; and home services&#xD;
      and follow-up appointment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Post-discharge management was the same for both groups, according to standard practice.&#xD;
      Patients were followed for adjustment of CHF medications in their heart failure clinics at&#xD;
      one to two weeks, four weeks, three months, and six months and more often if clinically&#xD;
      indicated. There was a minimum of six months of follow-up.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Data collection included: blood pressure and weight at each visit; electrocardiogram at&#xD;
      pre-randomization visit and at each hospitalization; serum electrolytes; echocardiogram at&#xD;
      randomization, at hospitalization discharge, and at six month follow-up; exercise stress&#xD;
      tests during index hospitalization and six month follow-up; natriuretic hormone profile at&#xD;
      randomization, discharge, and six month follow-up; medical history, endpoints, side effects,&#xD;
      hospitalizations and quality of life; and compliance with protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study consisted of a Clinical Coordinating Center which included a network of 26 clinical&#xD;
      units, and an echocardiographic core laboratory. The Protocol developed extended for six&#xD;
      months, patient recruitment extended for 48 months, follow-up for six months, and data&#xD;
      analysis for six months.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The NHLBI has awarded R01HL67691 in April 2001 as an ancillary study. The study entitled&#xD;
      &quot;ESCAPE Mechanistic Substudies&quot; has its own site on this database.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2006</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Failure, Congestive</condition>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>catheterization, Swan-Ganz</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients ages over 16, with class IV congestive heart failure (CHF). Patients had current&#xD;
        hospitalization for CHF, one previous hospitalization for CHF within the past six months,&#xD;
        left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;35 percent for at least three months, and attempted&#xD;
        therapy with angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEI) and digoxin and/or diuretics&#xD;
        in the past. Patients had NYHA class IV with clinical evidence of elevated filling&#xD;
        pressures at rest, that is, (a) evidence of elevated intracardiac filling pressures:&#xD;
        orthopnea, abdominal discomfort attributed to hepato-splenic congestion, peripheral edema,&#xD;
        ascites, rales, and jugular venous distension to 5 cm or less above sternal angle; and (b)&#xD;
        inadequate peripheral perfusion, that is, cool extremities. Exclusions included patients&#xD;
        with acute CHF requiring PAC as a part of the management and factors suggesting inability&#xD;
        to comply with the protocol.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah MR, O'Connor CM, Sopko G, Hasselblad V, Califf RM, Stevenson LW. Evaluation Study of Congestive Heart Failure and Pulmonary Artery Catheterization Effectiveness (ESCAPE): design and rationale. Am Heart J. 2001 Apr;141(4):528-35. doi: 10.1067/mhj.2001.113995.</citation>
    <PMID>11275915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Binanay C, Califf RM, Hasselblad V, O'Connor CM, Shah MR, Sopko G, Stevenson LW, Francis GS, Leier CV, Miller LW; ESCAPE Investigators and ESCAPE Study Coordinators. Evaluation study of congestive heart failure and pulmonary artery catheterization effectiveness: the ESCAPE trial. JAMA. 2005 Oct 5;294(13):1625-33. doi: 10.1001/jama.294.13.1625.</citation>
    <PMID>16204662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2008</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 27, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>ESCAPE</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Individual Participant Data Set</doc_type>
      <doc_url>http://biolincc.nhlbi.nih.gov/studies/escape/</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>NHLBI provides controlled access to IPD through BioLINCC. Access requires registration, evidence of local IRB approval or certification of exemption from IRB review, and completion of a data use agreement.</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_type>Study Protocol</doc_type>
      <doc_url>http://biolincc.nhlbi.nih.gov/studies/escape/</doc_url>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_type>Study Forms</doc_type>
      <doc_url>http://biolincc.nhlbi.nih.gov/studies/escape/</doc_url>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

