<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000759</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG 188</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000759</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurodevelopmental and Neurological Study of Infants and Children With HIV-1 Infection and AIDS in Clinical Trials</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neurodevelopmental and Neurological Study of Infants and Children With HIV-1 Infection and AIDS in Clinical Trials</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      AS PER AMENDMENT 10/24/96: To develop a domain/construct-driven neuropsychological and&#xD;
      neurological battery. Scaling of instruments to allow measurement of functions from infancy&#xD;
      to early adulthood; establish reliability and validity of the new instruments developed for&#xD;
      the NIMH Neurodevelopmental Battery. Downward extension of cognitive domains into infancy and&#xD;
      early childhood. To describe and compare outcomes when assessing level of development versus&#xD;
      rate of change. Describe and compare the outcomes from a global assessment of&#xD;
      neurodevelopment (e.g., a standardized I.Q. score) versus discrete assessments (e.g.,&#xD;
      functional domains such as motor or language skills). Develop guidelines for multicultural&#xD;
      neuropsychological and neurological assessment within a clinical trials design. Describe the&#xD;
      nature of impaired developmental abilities and course of the disease in infants and children.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The assessment of children who sustain central nervous system (CNS) insult requires&#xD;
      approaches that differ in several ways from adult-based assessment. The rapid changes that&#xD;
      occur in the developing CNS as well as in behavior reflect underlying processes of growth and&#xD;
      development.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The assessment of children who sustain central nervous system (CNS) insult requires&#xD;
      approaches that differ in several ways from adult-based assessment. The rapid changes that&#xD;
      occur in the developing CNS as well as in behavior reflect underlying processes of growth and&#xD;
      development.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will be conducted as a nested substudy within ACTG 152. AS PER AMENDMENT 10/24/97:&#xD;
      ACTG 188 was originally a nested study within ACTG 152, a three-arm clinical drug trial, but,&#xD;
      due to recruitment limitations, expanded to include other protocol and non-protocol children&#xD;
      with HIV-1 infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      It will include 225 HIV-infected patients from ACTG 152, as well as an additional 450&#xD;
      non-infected participants recruited for two comparison groups, one consisting of seronegative&#xD;
      infants and children with perinatal exposure to HIV and a second group without perinatal&#xD;
      exposure to HIV. AS PER AMENDMENT 10/24/96: Patients in the HIV-unexposed and uninfected&#xD;
      group are discontinued from the study and remaining patients are reassigned to two new age&#xD;
      groups: 3 months to 41 months and 30 days or 42 months to 9 years, 11 months, 30 days.&#xD;
      Patients 33 months or older but less than 42 months are discontinued from the study, those&#xD;
      patients less than 33 months at the time of enrollment are graduated from the study at the&#xD;
      age of 42 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A neurological assessment battery will evaluate the following domains: growth, sensory, tone,&#xD;
      motor, posture, locomotion, hand use, deep tendon reflexes, abnormal movements, language, and&#xD;
      behavior. Participants will be asked to do different kinds of activities such as talking,&#xD;
      listening, and drawing, and to play games that involve walking, jumping, concentration, and&#xD;
      memory. All participants will be assessed at clinic visits and followed for 72 weeks. AS PER&#xD;
      AMENDMENT 10/23/97: A modified version of the neurological battery will be discontinued from&#xD;
      interim follow-up evaluations and will be administered one last time as part of the exit&#xD;
      evaluation.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Natural History</observational_model>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>675</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participants must have:&#xD;
&#xD;
        AS PER AMENDMENT 10/24/96:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Signed, informed consent from a parent or legal guardian for patients under 18 years&#xD;
             of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        HIV-Infected Group: Documentation of HIV infection from a state-licensed lab as follows:&#xD;
        Children &gt; one month of age:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Documentation of current or prior enrollment in an investigational drug therapy or&#xD;
             other research protocol in which the protocol inclusion criteria specify HIV infection&#xD;
             OR laboratory evidence of vertically transmitted HIV infection as demonstrated on two&#xD;
             separate peripheral blood samples by either a positive viral culture (blood or&#xD;
             cerebrospinal fluid) OR detectably serum p24 antigen OR positive HIV-DNA PCR.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Children &gt;= 18 months of age:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Fulfillment of above criteria OR &gt;= 2 positive tests for HIV antibody (two different&#xD;
             specimens) determined by a federally-licensed test kit for detection of antibody,&#xD;
             confirmed by an independent supplemental test.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Documentation of presumption of maternal HIV infection at or prior to the birth of the&#xD;
             child.&#xD;
&#xD;
        HIV-Exposed, Uninfected Group: Children &lt; 18 months of age:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  At least two negative tests for direct detection of HIV (viral culture and/or antigen&#xD;
             detection and/or PCR assay and normal immunologic function.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Children &gt;= 18 months of age:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Negative serological test by an FDA-licensed test kit for detection of HIV antibody&#xD;
             performed on a specimen obtained at &gt;= 18 months of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Documentation of presence of maternal HIV infection at or prior to the birth of the&#xD;
             child.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Co-existing Condition:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with the following conditions are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
        AS PER AMENDMENT 10/24/96:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Central nervous system (CNS) disorders including poorly controlled seizure disorder&#xD;
             while on anticonvulsant therapy, evidence of neuroimaging abnormality resulting from a&#xD;
             traumatic brain injury or major congenital malformations associated with CNS&#xD;
             dysfunction.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Genetic diseases including:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  inborn errors of metabolism, inherited genetic diseases that would compromise CNS&#xD;
             function, chromosomal disorder that would compromise CNS function, cystic fibrosis,&#xD;
             muscular dystrophy, sickle cell anemia.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Juvenile onset diabetes.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Organ transplant recipients.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Deafness or blindness.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Intrathecal or intraventricular chemotherapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Treatment:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cranial or spinal radiation therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with the following prior conditions are excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Traumatic brain injury with loss of consciousness of &gt; 24 hours and/or skull fracture.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Prematurity including:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  intraventricular hemorrhage &gt; grade 2, requirement for mechanical ventilation for &gt; 28&#xD;
             days, seizures or another perinatal brain injury history including history of&#xD;
             hydrocephaly.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Intrathecal or intraventricular chemotherapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Treatment:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cranial or spinal radiation therapy.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>8 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wilson B</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fletcher J</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Belman A</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Med Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 1998</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Central Nervous System Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS-Related Complex</keyword>
  <keyword>Peripheral Nervous System Diseases</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

