<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005227</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1107</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL041514</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005227</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AIDS-Associated Cardiomyopathy</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To define the incidence and prevalence of AIDS-associated cardiomyopathy. Also, to conduct&#xD;
      immunopathology and serologic studies in endomyocardial biopsies and autopsy tissues.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      In 1988, the leading cause of death in AIDS patients was respiratory mechanisms might have&#xD;
      played a significant role in its pathogenesis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The project was part of an Institute-initiated study on AIDS-Associated Heart Disease in&#xD;
      Adults. The concept was approved by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Advisory Council in&#xD;
      September 1987. The Request for Applications was also released in September 1987. Awards were&#xD;
      made in July 1988.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The prevalence study was one of three subprojects with the common failure due to chronic&#xD;
      opportunistic pulmonary infection, primarily Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia. Drugs such as&#xD;
      azidothymidine (AZT) and trimetrexate showed some effectiveness in prolonging the lives of&#xD;
      some AIDS patients. With increased survival, it was believed that cardiac diseases might well&#xD;
      become an important complication of AIDs. Reports described a syndrome of rapidly progressive&#xD;
      cardiomyopathy associated with AIDS. The etiology of AIDS-associated cardiomyopathy was yet&#xD;
      unknown although immunologic theme of the immunopathogenesis of AIDS-associated&#xD;
      cardiomyopathy. The other two subprojects dealt with immunopathology studies in&#xD;
      endomyocardial biopsies and autopsy tissues and serologic studies. The AIDS Clinical Research&#xD;
      Center at Johns Hopkins Hospital served as the source of patients. All patients underwent&#xD;
      serologic testing and echocardiography at time of entry and at six and twelve months. The&#xD;
      screening electrocardiogram identified 40 to 50 patients per year with AIDS-associated&#xD;
      cardiomyopathy. Approximately 30 patients per year had no contraindications for&#xD;
      endomyocardial biopsy. Comprehensive tissue studies and cellular immune studies were&#xD;
      performed on the cohort and autopsies, if possible. Immunohistochemical techniques and in&#xD;
      situ hybridization of biopsy and autopsy material were used to determine if AIDS-associated&#xD;
      cardiomyopathy was associated with HIV infection of the heart or with some other viral or&#xD;
      opportunistic non-viral infection. Indirect immunofluorescence and a Western immunoblotting&#xD;
      assay using patient sera determined the prevalence of heart autoimmunity.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in&#xD;
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1988</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1993</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Diseases</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ahvie Herskowitz</last_name>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beschorner WE, Baughman K, Turnicky RP, Hutchins GM, Rowe SA, Kavanaugh-McHugh AL, Suresch DL, Herskowitz A. HIV-associated myocarditis. Pathology and immunopathology. Am J Pathol. 1990 Dec;137(6):1365-71.</citation>
    <PMID>2260626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turnicky RP, Goodin J, Smialek JE, Herskowitz A, Beschorner WE. Incidental myocarditis with intravenous drug abuse: the pathology, immunopathology, and potential implications for human immunodeficiency virus-associated myocarditis. Hum Pathol. 1992 Feb;23(2):138-43. doi: 10.1016/0046-8177(92)90234-t.</citation>
    <PMID>1740298</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu TC, Pizzorno MC, Hayward GS, Willoughby S, Neumann DA, Rose NR, Ansari AA, Beschorner WE, Baughman KL, Herskowitz A. In situ detection of human cytomegalovirus immediate-early gene transcripts within cardiac myocytes of patients with HIV-associated cardiomyopathy. AIDS. 1992 Aug;6(8):777-85. doi: 10.1097/00002030-199208000-00002.</citation>
    <PMID>1329847</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herskowitz A, Willoughby SB, Baughman KL, Schulman SP, Bartlett JD. Cardiomyopathy associated with antiretroviral therapy in patients with HIV infection: a report of six cases. Ann Intern Med. 1992 Feb 15;116(4):311-3. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-116-4-311. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>1733387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaudin PB, Hruban RH, Beschorner WE, Kasper EK, Olson JL, Baughman KL, Hutchins GM. Myocarditis associated with doxorubicin cardiotoxicity. Am J Clin Pathol. 1993 Aug;100(2):158-63. doi: 10.1093/ajcp/100.2.158.</citation>
    <PMID>8356947</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herskowitz A, Wu TC, Willoughby SB, Vlahov D, Ansari AA, Beschorner WE, Baughman KL. Myocarditis and cardiotropic viral infection associated with severe left ventricular dysfunction in late-stage infection with human immunodeficiency virus. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1994 Oct;24(4):1025-32. doi: 10.1016/0735-1097(94)90865-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7930193</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herskowitz A, Vlahov D, Willoughby S, Chaisson RE, Schulman SP, Neumann DA, Baughman KL. Prevalence and incidence of left ventricular dysfunction in patients with human immunodeficiency virus infection. Am J Cardiol. 1993 Apr 15;71(11):955-8. doi: 10.1016/0002-9149(93)90913-w.</citation>
    <PMID>8465788</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Willoughby SB, Vlahov D, Herskowitz A. Frequency of left ventricular dysfunction and other echocardiographic abnormalities in human immunodeficiency virus seronegative intravenous drug users. Am J Cardiol. 1993 Feb 15;71(5):446-7. doi: 10.1016/0002-9149(93)90451-h. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>8430637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herskowitz A, Willoughby SB, Vlahov D, Baughman KL, Ansari AA. Dilated heart muscle disease associated with HIV infection. Eur Heart J. 1995 Dec;16 Suppl O:50-5. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/16.suppl_o.50.</citation>
    <PMID>8682102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2005</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

