<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005712</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4921</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL045279</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005712</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Self Management Education Asthma</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of New Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of New Mexico</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the effects of a new statewide program to enhance identification, referral and&#xD;
      provision of care to rural families of Hispanic children with moderately severe to severe&#xD;
      asthma. Specifically, to determine if comprehensive medical care (CMC) plus an educational&#xD;
      self-management program for rural Hispanic children and their families had an impact on&#xD;
      asthma morbidity, as well as on cost and family adaptation.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Because of New Mexico's large rural and heavily Hispanic population, it was an ideal setting&#xD;
      to determine effective methods for case management, self-management educational programs and&#xD;
      effective tertiary to primary care delivery collaboration.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study was part of a demonstration and education initiative &quot;Interventions for Control of&#xD;
      Asthma Among Black and Hispanic Children&quot; which was released by the NHLBI in June 1989.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      A randomized block design was used with random assignment of subjects by county to treatment&#xD;
      groups of 1. comprehensive medical care or standard tertiary care and education, or 2.&#xD;
      CMC-Plus adding a structured self-management program--Open Airways/Respiro Abierto (developed&#xD;
      and tested with support of NHLBI). CMC-Plus also received in home education and intervention&#xD;
      from community based Hispanic family educators trained in an empowerment model of family&#xD;
      intervention, in-home support, and education. Case management was provided by CMS; CMC and&#xD;
      CMC-Plus were provided at the UNM-PPP in close collaboration with and transfer of care to the&#xD;
      primary physician. Additional educational contact with primary care providers and emergency&#xD;
      rooms were provided through the UNM Department of Family, Community &amp; Emergency Medicine&#xD;
      which utilized the National Institutes of Health National Asthma Education Program's&#xD;
      Guidelines for Step-Wise Care of Asthma. Asthma morbidity, cost of care, family adaptation&#xD;
      and family satisfaction were evaluated using standardized instruments.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1990</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 1996</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <condition>Lung Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark D, Gollub R, Green WF, Harvey N, Murphy SJ, Samet JM. Asthma in Jemez Pueblo schoolchildren. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1995 May;151(5):1625-7. doi: 10.1164/ajrccm.151.5.7735623.</citation>
    <PMID>7735623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 14, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 14, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

