<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001248</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>890045</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>89-N-0045</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001248</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) to Evaluate Activity of Multiple Sclerosis (MS)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Progression in Multiple Sclerosis by Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Studies performed under 89-N-0045 are designed to examine the natural history of multiple&#xD;
      sclerosis (MS) using MRI and immunological measures. In addition to studying the natural&#xD;
      history of untreated patients, the natural history of patients receiving approved&#xD;
      disease-modifying therapies of MS will be examined. In both cohorts of patients levels of&#xD;
      disease activity on MRI will be compared with immunological characteristics in order to help&#xD;
      identify disease mechanism. Patients with either definite MS (based either on clinical or&#xD;
      combined clinical and MRI criteria) or with an initial presentation of neurological&#xD;
      dysfunction consistent with MS will be studied longitudinally by MRI. Disease activity on MRI&#xD;
      will be assessed using several MRI measures of disease activity including the number of&#xD;
      contrast enhancing lesions, the overall burden of disease, brain atrophy and measures to&#xD;
      assess axonal damage. Patients will be assessed clinically and correlations between&#xD;
      immunological and genetic factors and disease activity as seen clinically or by MRI will be&#xD;
      studied.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A second cohort of patients starting the use of approved therapy will also be examined.&#xD;
      Patients referred to NIH prior to beginning approved therapy will be assessed with a series&#xD;
      of three monthly MRIs to determine the level of pretreatment disease activity. After&#xD;
      beginning approved therapy under the direction of their private physician, patients will be&#xD;
      followed similarly to the natural history cohort. Immunological and genetic findings will be&#xD;
      accessed before and during therapy in order to help establish the mechanisms of action of the&#xD;
      therapies and to identify mechanisms accounting for either a response or lack of response to&#xD;
      therapy. Part of the collected samples willl be cryopreserved to provide respository for&#xD;
      further studies focusing on detection of biomarkers indicative of disease state, disease&#xD;
      stage or repsonse to therapies.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Additionally, a cohort of normal volunteers will be studied. The studies in the normal&#xD;
      volunteers will be used to establish the most appropriate imaging sequences for studying&#xD;
      normal white matter in MS patients using magnetization transfer (MT) imaging sequences for&#xD;
      studying normal white matter in MS patients using magnetization transfer (MT) imaging and to&#xD;
      provide normative immunological measures.&#xD;
&#xD;
      ...&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Studies performed under 89-N-0045 are primarily designed to examine the evolving natural&#xD;
      history of multiple sclerosis (MS) and its mimickers, viewed through the window of&#xD;
      neuroimaging (especially magnetic resonance imaging or MRI). The protocol has four other&#xD;
      important objectives: (1) Screening prospective participants for selected NINDS&#xD;
      Neuroimmunology Clinic trials; (2) Performing studies to help define the mechanism of action&#xD;
      and cause of side effects of disease modifying therapies (DMT); (3) Studying healthy&#xD;
      volunteers for comparison with patients and for development of new experimental technologies;&#xD;
      and (4) Comparing MS to other neurological diseases that share imaging features.&#xD;
&#xD;
      To the extent possible, scheduled testing performed under this protocol will coincide with&#xD;
      standard-of-care evaluations for diagnosis and longitudinal clinical management, thereby&#xD;
      reducing the burden of research participation by participants. Such testing may involve&#xD;
      state-of-the-art research methods. Additional pure-research visits may be scheduled to&#xD;
      further investigate findings observed on scheduled visits and/or outside studies.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Disease activity on MRI will be assessed using several MRI measures, including the detection&#xD;
      of new on-study lesions, quantification of contrast-enhancing lesions, the total number&#xD;
      and/or volume of MRI-visible lesions, brain volume and brain volume change, and more advanced&#xD;
      MRI measures of tissue damage, such as quantitative magnetic relaxation mapping,&#xD;
      diffusion-weighted imaging (DWI), magnetization transfer imaging (MTI), and MR spectroscopy&#xD;
      (MRS). Participants may be assessed with other imaging modalities, including optical&#xD;
      coherence tomography (OCT), and they will be asked to provide research samples (generally&#xD;
      blood, but also saliva and cerebrospinal fluid) and be studied clinically.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In order to obtain comparative data for proper interpretation of the results in MS, two&#xD;
      control cohorts one consisting of patients, the other of healthy volunteers will be studied.&#xD;
      The patient control cohort will include patients with other CNS diseases that may share&#xD;
      pathophysiological processes with MS patients (e.g. other inflammatory conditions of the&#xD;
      central nervous system, mitochondrial disorders, leukodystrophies, neurodegenerative diseases&#xD;
      that may cause axonal loss or oxidative stress, or cerebral small vessel disease). Enrollment&#xD;
      of these control patient populations will help to answer the question of whether the&#xD;
      identified MRI findings and/or pathophysiological mechanisms are MS-specific or&#xD;
      generalizable.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 23, 1992</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the rate of change in the number of new white matter lesions per participant</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline vs. follow up visits</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome, which is designed to determine how MS disease activity has changed with the advent of ever-more-effective disease-modifying therapy, is the rate of change in the number of new white matter lesions per participant, indexed by the date of baseline evaluation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2500</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy volunteers for technique development and comparison with the patient populations.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MS/CIS/RIS population</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with a diagnosis of MS or who have typical imaging abnormalities associated with MS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-MS comparison population</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with disorders of the CNS, to include patients with diseases that share mechanisms of tissue damage with MS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        -MS/CIS/RIS population-Patients with a diagnosis of MS or who have typical imaging&#xD;
        abnormalities associated with MS.-Non-MS comparison populations-Patients with disorders of&#xD;
        the CNS, to include patients with diseases that share mechanisms of tissue damage with MS,&#xD;
        such as mitochondrial disorders, leukodystrophies, neurodegenerative diseases that may&#xD;
        cause axonal loss or oxidative stress, and chronic small vessel disease.-Healthy&#xD;
        volunteers-Healthy volunteers for technique development and comparison with the patient&#xD;
        populations.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  One of the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Diagnosis of MS or clinically isolated syndrome based on currently accepted&#xD;
                  diagnostic criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Presentation with neuroimaging features consistent with MS.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Diagnosis of another disease of the CNS&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Healthy volunteer.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age greater than or equal to 18.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Able to give informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        NIH employees are eligible to participate.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Contraindication to MRI.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unwilling to allow coded samples to be processed offsite or unwilling to have coded&#xD;
             samples used in other studies.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel S Reich, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jenifer E Dwyer</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-3825</phone>
    <email>jenifer.dwyer@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Daniel S Reich, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-1801</phone>
    <email>reichds@ninds.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY dial 711</phone_ext>
      <email>ccopr@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1989-N-0045.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tresley RM, Stone LA, Fields N, Maloni H, McFarland H, Frank JA. Clinical safety of serial monthly administrations of gadopentetate dimeglumine in patients with multiple sclerosis: implications for natural history and early-phase treatment trials. Neurology. 1997 Apr;48(4):832-5. doi: 10.1212/wnl.48.4.832.</citation>
    <PMID>9109864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calabresi PA, Stone LA, Bash CN, Frank JA, McFarland HF. Interferon beta results in immediate reduction of contrast-enhanced MRI lesions in multiple sclerosis patients followed by weekly MRI. Neurology. 1997 May;48(5):1446-8. doi: 10.1212/wnl.48.5.1446.</citation>
    <PMID>9153489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calabresi PA, Tranquill LR, Dambrosia JM, Stone LA, Maloni H, Bash CN, Frank JA, McFarland HF. Increases in soluble VCAM-1 correlate with a decrease in MRI lesions in multiple sclerosis treated with interferon beta-1b. Ann Neurol. 1997 May;41(5):669-74. doi: 10.1002/ana.410410517.</citation>
    <PMID>9153530</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 27, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI (Magnetic Resonance Imaging)</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>.This is a natural history, not a clinical trial, therefore we are not obligated to provide a data sharing statement.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

