<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001357</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>930205</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>93-I-0205</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001357</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Subcutaneously Administered Interleukin-2 Therapy in HIV-Infected Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Subcutaneously Administered Interleukin-2 Therapy in HIV-Infected Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I dose-escalating safety study aimed at identifying the maximum tolerated&#xD;
      dose (MTD) for an outpatient regimen while exposing the minimum number of patients to a dose&#xD;
      less than MTD. The anticipated accrual will be approximately 15 patients and the study will&#xD;
      take one year to complete. Patients will receive Proleukin速 (Registered Trademark)&#xD;
      subcutaneously at their assigned dose level once per day for 5 days approximately every eight&#xD;
      weeks for a total of 6 months. A cycle of therapy is defined as 5 days of Proleukin速&#xD;
      (Registered Trademark) plus antiviral therapy followed by 7 weeks of antiviral therapy alone.&#xD;
      If tolerated, each patient will receive 3 cycles of therapy and, following completion of&#xD;
      three cycles, will be eligible for extended treatment. IL-2 injections will be delivered by&#xD;
      study personnel on an outpatient basis for at least the first cycle of therapy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I dose-escalating safety study aimed at identifying the maximum tolerated&#xD;
      dose (MTD) for an outpatient regimen while exposing the minimum number of patients to a dose&#xD;
      less than MTD. The anticipated accrual will be approximately 15 patients and the study will&#xD;
      take one year to complete. Patients will receive Proleukin速 (Registered Trademark)&#xD;
      subcutaneously at their assigned dose level once per day for 5 days approximately every eight&#xD;
      weeks for a total of 6 months. A cycle of therapy is defined as 5 days of Proleukin速&#xD;
      (Registered Trademark) plus antiviral therapy followed by 7 weeks of antiviral therapy alone.&#xD;
      If tolerated, each patient will receive 3 cycles of therapy and, following completion of&#xD;
      three cycles, will be eligible for extended treatment. IL-2 injections will be delivered by&#xD;
      study personnel on an outpatient basis for at least the first cycle of therapy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1993</start_date>
  <completion_date>April 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>80</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infection</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interleukin-2</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        18 years of age or older with positive HIV-1 ELISA and Western blot.&#xD;
&#xD;
        CD4+ cell counts greater than or equal to 350 cells/mm(3).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No prior IL-2 therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No antiretroviral therapy for 6 weeks prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Willingness to remain off antiretrovirals for 12 months or until a protocol defined&#xD;
        recommendation or required change is determined.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No therapy with systemic corticosteroids, chemotherapy, or experimental therapy in the 4&#xD;
        weeks prior to entry on study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        SGOT less than or equal to 150 microliter/l; Hgb greater than 10 gm/dl; Granulocyte count&#xD;
        less than or equal to 1,000/mm(3); T. bilirubin less than or equal to 2.0 mg/dl; Serum&#xD;
        creatinine less than or equal to 2.0 mg/dl; Proteinuria less than or equal to 1+; platelet&#xD;
        count greater than 75,000.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No history of AIDS-defining opportunistic infection, or malignancy other than mucocutaneous&#xD;
        Kaposi sarcoma.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No significant cardiac, pulmonary, kidney, rheumatologic, gastrointestinal, psychiatric, or&#xD;
        neurological disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No pregnancy or breastfeeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No avascular necrosis of the bone.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patient must be fully informed of the known benefits of antiretroviral therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        HOME PATIENTS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patient must be enrolled and in good standing on a current NIAID protocol involving the use&#xD;
        of IL-2 therapy. The patient must already have undergone at least one year of treatment on&#xD;
        the protocol during which IL-2 therapy has been given, including at least 2 well-tolerated&#xD;
        outpatient cycles of scIL-2 at a stable dose.&#xD;
&#xD;
        The patient must have a history of generally tolerable side effects while receiving IL-2&#xD;
        that did not require frequent medical interventions, intravenous fluid replacement, and/or&#xD;
        IL-2 dose reductions. Conditions generally not suitable for home scIL-2 administration&#xD;
        would include (but are not limited to) an unusually heavy requirement for narcotic usage&#xD;
        during a cycle, significant urticaria (hives) or other allergic conditions, and any history&#xD;
        of possible airway compromise due to throat swelling.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patient must not have experienced any serious (grade 3 or higher) clinical or laboratory&#xD;
        abnormalities of medical significance during days 0-5 of the last 2 outpatient scIL-2&#xD;
        cycles.&#xD;
&#xD;
        The patient must have a strong relationship with a private physician or health-care&#xD;
        provider at home who has demonstrated close involvement in the patient's care to date and&#xD;
        who would be willing to help supervise a patient's care during each home scIL-2 cycle.&#xD;
        Because of the need to identify a single health-care provider at home who will agree to be&#xD;
        available to render care (if needed) during a patient's scIL-2 cycle, patients who&#xD;
        currently receive their home care from rotating staff members in a general clinic setting&#xD;
        may not be eligible for home scIL-2 administration. A signed written statement&#xD;
        acknowledging willingness to participate in monitoring must be received by the clinic 8&#xD;
        study team from the private physician or health-care provider prior to the first home&#xD;
        scIL-2 cycle. In addition, communication must occur between your clinic 8-study team and&#xD;
        the designated physician or health-care provider prior to each subsequent cycle to confirm&#xD;
        that individual's continued willingness to serve as on-site provider for any serious&#xD;
        medical conditions that might develop during a cycle.&#xD;
&#xD;
        The patient must live at a home address with easy access to a telephone and must have&#xD;
        demonstrated reliability in responding to telephone calls from clinic 8 staff members. The&#xD;
        patient must also be able to provide the study team with reliable contact information for a&#xD;
        close family member or friend who will agree to serve in the capacity of a &quot;care-giver&quot;&#xD;
        during each cycle: i.e., someone who will be able to render non-medical assistance to the&#xD;
        patient and be able to check on their condition daily in the event that emergency medical&#xD;
        assistance needs to be summoned. It will become the patient's responsibility to ensure that&#xD;
        the local &quot;care-giver&quot; communicates their willingness to serve in this capacity by&#xD;
        telephoning the clinic 8-study team prior to each cycle.&#xD;
&#xD;
        The patient must have &quot;reasonable&quot; (i.e., rapid and close) access at home to emergency&#xD;
        medical services and a nearby medical facility in the event of a medical crisis. The&#xD;
        suitability of the at-home situation will be assessed on a case-by-case basis by the clinic&#xD;
        8-study team.&#xD;
&#xD;
        The patient must have demonstrated reliability and consistency in sterile technique, the&#xD;
        reconstitution of IL-2 vials, and the preparation and administration of scIL-2 injections.&#xD;
&#xD;
        The patient must be receiving outpatient scIL-2 cycles at least once every 6 months as part&#xD;
        of their normal protocol participation, except at the discretion of the study team.&#xD;
&#xD;
        The patient must have access to a reliable home weight scale and be able to weigh&#xD;
        themselves accurately on a daily basis for the purposes of safety monitoring.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lissoni P, Barni S, Ardizzoia A, Crispino S, Paolorossi F, Archili C, Vaghi M, Tancini G. Second line therapy with low-dose subcutaneous interleukin-2 alone in advanced renal cancer patients resistant to interferon-alpha. Eur J Cancer. 1992;28(1):92-6. doi: 10.1016/0959-8049(92)90393-g.</citation>
    <PMID>1567700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lotze MT, Matory YL, Rayner AA, Ettinghausen SE, Vetto JT, Seipp CA, Rosenberg SA. Clinical effects and toxicity of interleukin-2 in patients with cancer. Cancer. 1986 Dec 15;58(12):2764-72. doi: 10.1002/1097-0142(19861215)58:123.0.co;2-z.</citation>
    <PMID>3490903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McElrath MJ, Kaplan G, Burkhardt RA, Cohn ZA. Cutaneous response to recombinant interleukin 2 in human immunodeficiency virus 1-seropositive individuals. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1990 Aug;87(15):5783-7. doi: 10.1073/pnas.87.15.5783.</citation>
    <PMID>2143021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2002</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Cytokines</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunoregulation</keyword>
  <keyword>CD4 Cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

