<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001864</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990110</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-EI-0110</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001864</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Amblyopia (Lazy Eye) Treatment Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Amblyopia Treatment Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the results of two standard treatments for amblyopia&#xD;
      in order to find out if one is more effective than the other. Amblyopia, which develops in&#xD;
      childhood, is also called &quot;lazy eye,&quot; because one eye is not being used properly. The brain&#xD;
      favors the other eye for some reason, such as crossing or turning out of the eyes, and vision&#xD;
      in the weak eye is reduced.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Amblyopia is treated by forcing the child to use the weak eye. There are two ways to do this:&#xD;
      1) a patch placed over the &quot;good&quot; eye forces the child to use the weak eye; or 2) an eye drop&#xD;
      placed in the &quot;good&quot; eye once a day to blur vision in that eye makes the child rely on the&#xD;
      weak eye. The success rates with both of these methods have been reported to be about the&#xD;
      same; this study will try to identify if one is more effective than the other.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Children will be randomly assigned by computer to one of the following two treatment methods:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patch&#xD;
&#xD;
      The child initially will wear a patch over the &quot;good&quot; eye for 8 to 12 hours every day. If&#xD;
      vision in the weak eye improves, the patching time will be decreased. If vision remains good&#xD;
      after 3 months, the patching will be stopped, unless the child's doctor believes treatment&#xD;
      should continue. If vision in the weak eye does not improve, the patching time will be&#xD;
      increased.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Eye Drops&#xD;
&#xD;
      The child will be given one drop per day of atropine in the &quot;good&quot; eye. If vision in the weak&#xD;
      eye improves, the drops will be given less often. If the vision remains good after 3 months,&#xD;
      the drops will be stopped, unless the child's doctor believes treatment should continue. If&#xD;
      the initial daily drop does not improve the vision in the weak eye, the child's eyeglasses&#xD;
      may be changed to try to further blur the vision in the &quot;good&quot; eye.&#xD;
&#xD;
      After 6 months, treatment may be stopped if it has not been successful. If treatment has been&#xD;
      successful after 6 months, it may be continued at a reduced amount or stopped.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Follow-up visits will be scheduled every 4 weeks for the first 6 months and every 2 to 4&#xD;
      months after that until the end of the 2-year study. During each visit the eyes will be&#xD;
      examined for eye movements and vision, and the pupils will be dilated to examine the inside&#xD;
      of the eye.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Amblyopia Treatment Study (ATS) has been designed as a randomized, controlled&#xD;
      single-masked multi-center clinical trial with the following objectives:&#xD;
&#xD;
      To determine whether the success rate with atropine treatment of amblyopia due to strabismus&#xD;
      or anisometropia in patients less than 7 years old is equivalent to the success rate with&#xD;
      occlusion (patching) therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      To develop more precise estimates of the success rates of amblyopia treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      To identify factors that may be associated with successful treatment of amblyopia.&#xD;
&#xD;
      To collect data on the clinical course of treated amblyopia to provide more precise estimates&#xD;
      of treatment kinetics than now available.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>November 2001</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>20</enrollment>
  <condition>Amblyopia</condition>
  <condition>Anisometropia</condition>
  <condition>Strabismus</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atropine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patch</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Age less than 7 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Able to measure surrounded single optotype visual acuity using the ATS BVAT protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Amblyopia associated with strabismus (comitant or incomitant), anisometropia, or both.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No more than 2 months of amblyopia therapy in the past 2 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No current vision therapy or orthoptics.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Visual acuity in the sound eye greater than or equal to 20/40.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Visual acuity in the amblyopic eye less than or equal to 20/40 and greater than or equal to&#xD;
        20/100.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Inter-eye acuity difference (IAD) greater than or equal to 3 LogMAR lines.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No ocular cause for reduced visual acuity.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Cycloplegic refraction and ocular examination within 2 months of enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No myopia.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Hyperopic/astigmatic refractive error, if present, corrected for at least 4 weeks.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No prior intraocular surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Downs Syndrome not present.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No known skin reactions to patch or bandage adhesives.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No known allergy to atropine or other cycloplegics.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Availability for at least 6 months of follow-up, has a home phone (or access to phone), and&#xD;
        willing to be contacted by Jaeb Center staff.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Eye Institute (NEI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woodruff G, Hiscox F, Thompson JR, Smith LK. Factors affecting the outcome of children treated for amblyopia. Eye (Lond). 1994;8 ( Pt 6):627-31. doi: 10.1038/eye.1994.157.</citation>
    <PMID>7867817</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaw DE, Fielder AR, Minshull C, Rosenthal AR. Amblyopia--factors influencing age of presentation. Lancet. 1988 Jul 23;2(8604):207-9. doi: 10.1016/s0140-6736(88)92301-x.</citation>
    <PMID>2899674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simons K. Preschool vision screening: rationale, methodology and outcome. Surv Ophthalmol. 1996 Jul-Aug;41(1):3-30. doi: 10.1016/s0039-6257(97)81990-x.</citation>
    <PMID>8827927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2001</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Lazy Eye</keyword>
  <keyword>Atropine Penalization</keyword>
  <keyword>Patching</keyword>
  <keyword>Vision Loss</keyword>
  <keyword>Amblyopia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amblyopia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Strabismus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anisometropia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atropine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

