<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000985</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG 095</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11070</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000985</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Foscarnet Versus Vidarabine in the Treatment of Herpes Infection in Patients With AIDS Who Have Not Had Success With Acyclovir</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Acyclovir-Resistant Mucocutaneous Herpes Simplex Infection in Patients With the Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome: A Randomized Multicenter Study of Foscarnet Versus Vidarabine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare the safety and effectiveness of foscarnet and vidarabine treatments for AIDS&#xD;
      patients who have herpes simplex virus infections that are resistant to standard treatment&#xD;
      with acyclovir.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Foscarnet is a drug that inhibits viruses and has been shown to be effective against&#xD;
      infection with Cytomegalovirus and also against infection with the Herpes simplex virus in&#xD;
      several patients with AIDS. Vidarabine has been shown to have activity against the Herpes&#xD;
      simplex virus in patients who do not have AIDS, but it has not been studied in patients who&#xD;
      do have AIDS. This study compares foscarnet and vidarabine treatments for AIDS patients who&#xD;
      have herpes simplex infection that has not responded to therapy with acyclovir in the hope&#xD;
      that one of these two drugs will help to stop further progression of the herpes simplex&#xD;
      infection and may have fewer side effects.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Foscarnet is a drug that inhibits viruses and has been shown to be effective against&#xD;
      infection with Cytomegalovirus and also against infection with the Herpes simplex virus in&#xD;
      several patients with AIDS. Vidarabine has been shown to have activity against the Herpes&#xD;
      simplex virus in patients who do not have AIDS, but it has not been studied in patients who&#xD;
      do have AIDS. This study compares foscarnet and vidarabine treatments for AIDS patients who&#xD;
      have herpes simplex infection that has not responded to therapy with acyclovir in the hope&#xD;
      that one of these two drugs will help to stop further progression of the herpes simplex&#xD;
      infection and may have fewer side effects.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Following evaluation studies, patients receive at least 10 days of intravenous (IV) therapy&#xD;
      with acyclovir. During this therapy, patients have two serum concentration levels of&#xD;
      acyclovir drawn to make sure there are adequate levels of medication in their blood. If skin&#xD;
      lesions do not heal after a total of 10 days of therapy with acyclovir, lesions are swabbed&#xD;
      for viral culture to test the susceptibility of the virus to therapy with acyclovir,&#xD;
      foscarnet, and vidarabine. If the test confirms that the herpes lesions are resistant to&#xD;
      acyclovir, patients may choose to participate in the next phase of the study. Following&#xD;
      additional evaluation studies, patients are randomized to one of two groups, each of which&#xD;
      receives 10-21 days of IV treatment with one of the two alternative medications, foscarnet or&#xD;
      vidarabine. Foscarnet is given by IV infusion every 8 hours, and each infusion lasts 1 hour.&#xD;
      Vidarabine is given by IV infusion once a day, and each infusion lasts 12 hours. While&#xD;
      receiving therapy with either foscarnet or vidarabine, blood tests are done every 3 days for&#xD;
      routine lab tests and once a week to determine foscarnet or vidarabine blood levels. Skin&#xD;
      lesions are cultured for herpes virus every 5 days. At the end of 10 days of therapy,&#xD;
      improvement is evaluated, and the patients can continue to receive therapy if indicated.&#xD;
      There is a provision for cross-over treatment if patients show a poor response.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 1990</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>26</enrollment>
  <condition>Herpes Simplex</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vidarabine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acyclovir</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Foscarnet sodium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed for phase B:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Aerosolized pentamidine prophylaxis for Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia (PCP).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allowed for phase A:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ganciclovir. Patients receiving this drug at the time of study enrollment must&#xD;
             discontinue the drug at the time of enrollment and for the duration of the study&#xD;
             period.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Co-existing Condition:&#xD;
&#xD;
        For phase A, patients with pre-existing severe neurologic impairment such as seizure&#xD;
        disorder or marked or incapacitating ataxia are excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded upon entry into phase B:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ganciclovir.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Immunomodulators.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Probenecid.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ciprofloxacin.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Allopurinol.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Zidovudine (AZT).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Antiretrovirals.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other investigational agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acyclovir for another labeled indication.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Potentially nephrotoxic agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients will be excluded from the study for the following reasons:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Phase A:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Previous hypersensitivity reaction to foscarnet or vidarabine. Patients who have a&#xD;
             documented history of vidarabine intolerance may be eligible for the foscarnet on the&#xD;
             non-randomized arm of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Phase B:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Clinical response to therapy with acyclovir in phase A described as &quot;healed&quot; or&#xD;
             &quot;good.&quot;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Medication:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded within 14 days of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Immunomodulators or biologic response modifiers.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Phase A:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Excluded within 30 days of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Foscarnet.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Phase B:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded within 7 days of study entry into phase B:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any potentially nephrotoxic agent, except acyclovir.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior Treatment:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Excluded for phase A within 14 days of study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Lymphocyte replacement therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must demonstrate the following clinical and laboratory findings:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Phase A:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  HIV positive by federally licensed ELISA test confirmed by Western blot, p24 serum&#xD;
             antigen, or a positive HIV culture; or a prior diagnosis of AIDS as defined by Centers&#xD;
             for Disease Control criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Mucocutaneous herpes simplex virus (HSV) infection confirmed by viral culture&#xD;
             persisting for a minimum of 2 weeks which is clinically resistant to therapy with&#xD;
             acyclovir in the opinion of the patient's physician.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Phase B:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Persistent shedding of HSV at the completion of or within 1 week after completion of&#xD;
             phase A acyclovir therapy as confirmed by viral culture.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Documented in vitro resistance of the virus to acyclovir.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  All strains must be referred to the Diagnostic Virology Laboratories at either San&#xD;
             Francisco General Hospital or Beth Israel Hospital, Boston, for susceptibility&#xD;
             testing.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Two serum acyclovir levels drawn during phase A. Results may be pending at time of&#xD;
             entry into phase B.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  All eligibility evaluations must be performed within 7 days prior to study entry for&#xD;
             phase A or B.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>S Safrin</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush Univ. Med. Ctr. ACTG CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess - East Campus A0102 CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ. of Rochester ACTG CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington AIDS CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Safrin S, Crumpacker C, Chatis P, Davis R, Hafner R, Rush J, Kessler HA, Landry B, Mills J. A controlled trial comparing foscarnet with vidarabine for acyclovir-resistant mucocutaneous herpes simplex in the acquired immunodeficiency syndrome. The AIDS Clinical Trials Group. N Engl J Med. 1991 Aug 22;325(8):551-5. doi: 10.1056/NEJM199108223250805.</citation>
    <PMID>1649971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Safrin S, Crumpacker C, Chatis P, Davis R, Hafner R, Rush J, Kessler H, Landry B, Mills J. ACTG 095: a randomized comparison of foscarnet (FOS) vs. Vidarabine (ARA-A) for treatment of acyclovir (ACV)-resistant mucocutaneous herpes simplex virus (HSV) infection in patients with AIDS. Int Conf AIDS. 1991 Jun 16-21;7(1):44 (abstract no MB85)</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2021</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 28, 2021</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 28, 2021</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 4, 2021</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vidarabine</keyword>
  <keyword>Phosphonoacetic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Herpes Simplex</keyword>
  <keyword>Foscarnet</keyword>
  <keyword>Acyclovir</keyword>
  <keyword>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Herpes Simplex</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acyclovir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foscarnet</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Phosphonoacetic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

