<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001813</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990099</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-C-0099</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001813</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00004044</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Examination of Clinical and Laboratory Abnormalities in Patients With Defective DNA Repair: Xeroderma Pigmentosum, Cockayne Syndrome, or Trichothiodystrophy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Examination of Clinical and Laboratory Abnormalities in Patients With Defective DNA Repair: Xeroderma Pigmentosum, Cockayne Syndrome, or Trichothiodystrophy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Four rare genetic diseases, xeroderma pigmentosum (XP), Cockayne syndrome (CS), the XP/CS&#xD;
      complex and trichothiodystrophy (TTD) have defective DNA excision repair although only XP has&#xD;
      increased cancer susceptibility. We plan to perform careful clinical examination of selected&#xD;
      patients with XP, XP/CS, CS, or TTD and follow their clinical course. We will obtain tissue&#xD;
      (skin, blood, hair, buccal swabs) for laboratory examination of DNA repair and for genetic&#xD;
      analysis. We hope to be able to correlate these laboratory abnormalities with the clinical&#xD;
      features to better understand the mechanism of cancer prevention by DNA repair. Patients will&#xD;
      be offered counseling and education for cancer control.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Three rare genetic diseases, xeroderma pigmentosum (XP), Cockayne syndrome (CS), and&#xD;
      trichothiodystrophy (TTD) have defective DNA excision repair although only XP has increased&#xD;
      cancer susceptibility. We plan to perform careful clinical examination of selected patients&#xD;
      with XP, CS, TTD, or overlap syndromes to follow their clinical course. We will obtain tissue&#xD;
      (skin, blood, hair, or buccal cells) for laboratory examination of DNA repair and for&#xD;
      histologic, protein, biochemical, and genetic analysis. We hope to be able to correlate these&#xD;
      laboratory abnormalities with the clinical features to better understand the mechanism of&#xD;
      cancer prevention by DNA repair. Patients will be offered counseling and education for cancer&#xD;
      control.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 10, 1999</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify patients with genetic diseases</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with three rare genetic diseases; xeroderma pigmentosum (XP), Cockayne syndrome (CS), and trichothiodystrophy (TTD)and overlap syndromes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnosis confirmation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 days</time_frame>
    <description>-To confirm suspected cases of XP, CS, TTD, XP/TTD or overlap syndrome patients by review of clinical records, by clinical examination and by laboratory testing -To document presence (or absence) of cancers (skin, eye, tongue, or internal) in XP, XP/CS, CS, TTD, XP/TTD and other overlap syndrome patients-To document atypical clinical features or unusual environmental exposures of patients with XP, XP/CS, CS, TTD, XP/TTD and otheroverlap syndromes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tissue collection</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 days</time_frame>
    <description>obtain tissue (skin, blood, hair or buccal cells) from XP, CS, TTD, XP/TTD or overlap syndrome patients, their first-degree relatives and healthy volunteers for establishment of cell cultures and for examination of DNA repair and genetic analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>identify molecular defects</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 days</time_frame>
    <description>identify molecular defects in the DNA repair or other genes in cells from patients with XP, CS, TTD, XP/TTD or overlap syndromes and toattempt to correlate the defects with the clinical features</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>yearly</time_frame>
    <description>follow the clinical course of selected patients with XP, CS, TTD, XP/TTD or overlap syndromes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">750</enrollment>
  <condition>Cockayne Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Skin Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Xeroderma Pigmentosum</condition>
  <condition>Trichothiodystrophy Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Genodermatosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects with clinical and/or laboratory documentation of typical features or suggestiveclinical features of XP, CS, TTD, or overlap syndromes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Family members of patients with XP, CS, TTD, or overlap syndromes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy volunteers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients will be sought by contacting professional organizations (such as the American&#xD;
        Academy of Dermatology-XP Task Force), lay support groups (such as the XP Society and the&#xD;
        Share and Care CS Support Network) or by direct referral.@@@Healthy volunteers or NIH staff&#xD;
        will be recruited through the Program for Healthy Volunteers (CRVP@mail.cc.nih.gov),&#xD;
        through the Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov), or as a&#xD;
        self-referral through the clinicaltrials.gov web site (http://clinicaltrials.gov). Healthy&#xD;
        volunteers may also be approached by a member of the LCBG, NCI regarding interest in&#xD;
        participating on this protocol.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects age 6 weeks and above:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  with clinical and/or laboratory documentation of typical features or suggestive&#xD;
                  clinical features of XP, CS, TTD, or overlap syndromes or&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  that are first degree relatives or other family members of participants with XP,&#xD;
                  CS, TTD, or overlap syndromes&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Healthy volunteers of age 1 year and above (including NIH employees) willing to donate&#xD;
             blood, skin, buccal cells, or hair.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients or legally authorized representatives must provide informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -Inability or unwillingness to provide tissue (skin, blood, buccal cells or hair) for&#xD;
        laboratory studies.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kenneth H Kraemer, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Deborah E Tamura, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 760-7355</phone>
    <email>dt220a@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kenneth H Kraemer, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 760-6139</phone>
    <email>kraemerk@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1999-C-0099.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barrett SF, Robbins JH, Tarone RE, Kraemer KH. Evidence for defective repair of cyclobutane pyrimidine dimers with normal repair of other DNA photoproducts in a transcriptionally active gene transfected into Cockayne syndrome cells. Mutat Res. 1991 Nov;255(3):281-91. doi: 10.1016/0921-8777(91)90032-k.</citation>
    <PMID>1719400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boltshauser E, Yalcinkaya C, Wichmann W, Reutter F, Prader A, Valavanis A. MRI in Cockayne syndrome type I. Neuroradiology. 1989;31(3):276-7. doi: 10.1007/BF00344359.</citation>
    <PMID>2779780</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 19, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Xeroderma Pigmentosum</keyword>
  <keyword>Trichothiodystrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>Cockayne Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Skin Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>DNA Repair</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Skin Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Xeroderma Pigmentosum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cockayne Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ichthyosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trichothiodystrophy Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>.All IPD recorded in the medical record will be shared with intramural investigators upon request. @@@@@@In addition, all large scale genomic sequencing data will be shared with subscribers to dbGaP.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>-Clinical data available during the study and indefinitely.@@@@@@-Genomic data are available once genomic data are uploaded per protocol GDS plan for as long as database is active</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>-Clinical data will be made available and with the permission of the study PI.@@@@@@-Genomic data are made available via dbGaP through requests to the data custodians.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

