<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001893</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990140</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-H-0140</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001893</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of TNFR:Fc (Enbrel) in the Treatment of Asthma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Clinical Trial of TNFR:Fc in a Segmental Allergen Challenge Model of Asthma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study is a phase II clinical trial of TNFR:Fc therapy in a segmental allergen&#xD;
      bronchoprovocation model of atopic asthma. The goal of this study is to assess whether&#xD;
      inhibition of tumor necrosis factor (TNF) bioactivity can attenuate airway inflammation in&#xD;
      mild-to-moderate allergic asthmatics. This protocol will utilize a randomized, double-blind,&#xD;
      placebo-controlled trial design. TNF bioactivity will be inhibited via systemic&#xD;
      administration (e.g., subcutaneous injection) of a dimeric fusion protein consisting of the&#xD;
      extracellular ligand binding domain of the 75-kilodalton TNF receptor linked to the Fc&#xD;
      portion of human IgG1 (TNFR:Fc, Immunex). The data generated by this study will address the&#xD;
      utility of anti-TNF therapy for patients with asthma.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study is a phase II clinical trial of TNFR:Fc therapy in a segmental allergen&#xD;
      bronchoprovocation model of atopic asthma. The goal of this study is to assess whether&#xD;
      inhibition of tumor necrosis factor (TNF) bioactivity can attenuate airway inflammation in&#xD;
      mild-to-moderate allergic asthmatics. This protocol will utilize a randomized, double-blind,&#xD;
      placebo-controlled trial design. TNF bioactivity will be inhibited via systemic&#xD;
      administration (e.g., subcutaneous injection) of a dimeric fusion protein consisting of the&#xD;
      extracellular ligand- binding domain of the 75-kilodalton TNF receptor linked to the Fc&#xD;
      portion of human IgG1 (TNFR:Fc, Immunex). The data generated by this study will address the&#xD;
      utility of anti-TNF therapy for patients with asthma.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 17, 1999</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2002</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Whether subcutaneous administration of TNFR:Fc alters TNF bioactivity in brochoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) samples.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment>150</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TNFR:Fc</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients will be between 18 and 65 years of age, male or female, and must be at least 5&#xD;
        feet in height.&#xD;
&#xD;
        The diagnosis of asthma requires a history of intermittent, reversible expiratory flow&#xD;
        limitation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients will have mild-to-moderate allergic asthma as defined by a baseline forced&#xD;
        expiratory flow in one second (FEV(1)) greater than 70% of predicted (at least 6 hours&#xD;
        after bronchodilator use) and therapy limited to inhaled beta-agonists.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must be without evidence of an asthma exacerbation or a viral upper respiratory&#xD;
        tract infection for 6 weeks prior to entry into the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Positive skin prick-puncture test to one or more common aeroallergens.&#xD;
&#xD;
        A positive inhaled methacholine challenge as defined by a decrease in FEV(1) of at least&#xD;
        20% (PC20) in response to inhalation of less than 25 mg/ml of methacholine.&#xD;
&#xD;
        A decrease in FEV(1) of at least 20% in response to inhalation of up to 10,000&#xD;
        bioequivalency allergy units (BAU) or allergy units (AU) per ml of a selected common&#xD;
        aeroallergen (house dust mite, cat hair or grasses) or up to 150 Antigen E units per ml of&#xD;
        short ragweed. Asthmatic patients must also demonstrate a late asthmatic response (defined&#xD;
        as a 20% fall from the baseline established following completion of the early asthmatic&#xD;
        response).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Normal complete blood count, PT, PTT, and serum electrolytes, mineral and hepatic panels&#xD;
        (less than 30 ml of blood will be drawn), normal EKG and chest radiograph without acute&#xD;
        pulmonary infiltrates.&#xD;
&#xD;
        For women of childbearing potential, negative pregnancy test with 2 weeks prior to study&#xD;
        and willingness to adhere to reliable birth control methods during the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Hypersensitivity to TNFR:Fc&#xD;
&#xD;
        Women who are breast-feeding infants will be excluded because the risk of a serious adverse&#xD;
        reaction in the infants to TNFR:Fc is unknown.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Diagnosis of a pulmonary disorder other than asthma (e.g., chronic bronchitis, cystic&#xD;
        fibrosis, bronchiectasis, HIV-related lymphocytic airway inflammation).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Respiratory tract infection or asthma exacerbation within 4 weeks of screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Presence of an active infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Use of theophylline, oral or inhaled corticosteroid, nedocromil sodium, cromolyn sodium,&#xD;
        zilueton, leukotriene receptor antagonists (e.g., zafirlukast or montelukast), or&#xD;
        anti-cholinergic agents within the prior 3 months. In addition, patients requiring ongoing&#xD;
        therapy with anti-histamines, hydroxyzine, and tricyclic anti-depressants will be excluded.&#xD;
        Research subjects can continue therapy with inhaled beta-agonists during the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of anaphylaxis or severe allergic response.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of adverse reactions to lidocaine or other local anesthetics.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Use of aspirin within 2 weeks of the bronchoscopic study or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory&#xD;
        agents within 2 days of the bronchoscopic study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of cigarette smoking within the past 3 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of allergy immunotherapy within the past year.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allergy to methacholine.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Positive test for human immunodeficiency virus (to exclude patients with HIV-related&#xD;
        lymphocytic airway inflammation).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Positive test for hepatitis viruses (to exclude patients with hepatitis-related lung&#xD;
        disease, such as pleural effusions, interstitial pneumonitis and fibrosis).&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of Crohn's disease (to exclude patients with inflammatory bowel disease-related&#xD;
        alveolar lymphocytosis).&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of diseases associated with impaired host defenses, such as diabetes mellitus or&#xD;
        congestive heart failure. Patients with impaired host defenses also include individuals&#xD;
        with either acquired or congenital, quantitative or qualitative defects in neutrophil,&#xD;
        lymphocyte, monocyte/macrophage or complement function. Similarly, patients requiring&#xD;
        immunosuppressive therapies, such as a chronic corticosteroid utilization for more than 6&#xD;
        months or cytoxic chemotherapeutic agents will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of chronic heart failure or coronary artery disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of central nervous system demyelinating disorders, such as multiple sclerosis,&#xD;
        myelitis or optic neuritis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of hematologic disorders, such as anemia (other than iron deficiency anemia),&#xD;
        thrombocytopenia or leukopenia.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of renal disease, such as chronic renal failure or renal artery stenosis with renal&#xD;
        artery stent placement.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of psoriasis.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broide DH, Lotz M, Cuomo AJ, Coburn DA, Federman EC, Wasserman SI. Cytokines in symptomatic asthma airways. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 1992 May;89(5):958-67. doi: 10.1016/0091-6749(92)90218-q.</citation>
    <PMID>1374772</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 13, 2008</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Steward Levine, M.D./National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute</name_title>
    <organization>National Institutes of Health</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bronchoprovocation</keyword>
  <keyword>Airway Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumor Necrosis Factor</keyword>
  <keyword>Bronchoalveolar Lavage</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Function Test</keyword>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etanercept</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

