<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001867</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990179</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-EI-0179</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001867</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Pregnancy on Uveitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Pregnancy on Uveitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to gain information about the course of uveitis (a type of eye&#xD;
      inflammation) during pregnancy and the postpartum period (six months after delivery). Some&#xD;
      reports have indicated the condition may improve or disappear without treatment during&#xD;
      pregnancy and recur postpartum, requiring treatment. No systematic studies have been done,&#xD;
      however, to examine a link between pregnancy and disease suppression.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All medicines for uveitis have side effects-particularly for pregnant women, their unborn&#xD;
      babies, and breast-feeding mothers. The information gained may help guide treatment decisions&#xD;
      for these patients in the future.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Women who are between 2 and 20 weeks pregnant and have had uveitis within 2 years of becoming&#xD;
      pregnant will be followed monthly with an eye examination and blood tests until six months&#xD;
      after giving birth. The eye examination will include dilation of the pupils to look at the&#xD;
      back of the eye. Photos of the eye will be taken to record changes that occur due to uveitis.&#xD;
      The blood tests will assess immune function and try to determine whether levels of hormones&#xD;
      and cytokines are related to uveitis disease activity. Patients who develop an inflammation&#xD;
      and significant vision loss may require treatment, possibly with eye drops or injections near&#xD;
      the eye. Treatment will be decided in consultation with the patient's obstetrician.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pregnancy is thought to be associated with the remediation of some disease and exacerbation&#xD;
      of other conditions. Anecdotal case reports suggest that uveitis may remit or improve during&#xD;
      pregnancy and recur in the postpartum period. This observation is supported by findings in an&#xD;
      experimental autoimmune uveitis model in mice. We propose to study the natural history of&#xD;
      ocular inflammation in a series of pregnant women who have had ocular inflammation (uveitis)&#xD;
      in the two year period prior to becoming pregnant. Women will be enrolled between 2 and 20&#xD;
      completed weeks of gestation at which time they will receive a complete ophthalmologic&#xD;
      examination and will have blood drawn for cytokine and hormone evaluation. These procedures&#xD;
      will be repeated at monthly intervals until 6 months postpartum. Treatment of uveitis will&#xD;
      ensue as medically indicated and in consultation with the woman's obstetric care provider.&#xD;
      The goal of this investigation is to determine whether cytokine levels are correlated with&#xD;
      disease expression. Such information may be useful to inform decisions about how to best&#xD;
      manage pregnant and postpartum uveitis patients in the future.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>September 2000</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>10</enrollment>
  <condition>Postpartum Period</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <condition>Uveitis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Females with a history of unilateral or bilateral immune-mediated, non-infectious&#xD;
        inflammatory ocular disease that required topical and/or systemic immunosuppresive&#xD;
        medications at least once in the past two years or who are currently under treatment for&#xD;
        unilateral or bilateral non-infectious ocular inflammation and having diagnosed uveitis,&#xD;
        scleritis, or autoimmune corneal disorders in the past two years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        First and second trimester pregnancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Informed consent from the patient.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No pregnancy complications which require medical treatment and special obstetric care.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No hematolgical disorder that would preclude blood draws for investigational purposes.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No current ocular or systemic infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No current malignancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No current endocrine disorders.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Eye Institute (NEI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wegmann TG, Lin H, Guilbert L, Mosmann TR. Bidirectional cytokine interactions in the maternal-fetal relationship: is successful pregnancy a TH2 phenomenon? Immunol Today. 1993 Jul;14(7):353-6. doi: 10.1016/0167-5699(93)90235-D.</citation>
    <PMID>8363725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raghupathy R. Th1-type immunity is incompatible with successful pregnancy. Immunol Today. 1997 Oct;18(10):478-82. doi: 10.1016/s0167-5699(97)01127-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9357139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raghupathy R. Maternal anti-placental cell-mediated reactivity and spontaneous abortions. Am J Reprod Immunol. 1997 Jun;37(6):478-84. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0897.1997.tb00263.x.</citation>
    <PMID>9228305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 1999</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Cytokine</keyword>
  <keyword>Gestation</keyword>
  <keyword>Postpartum</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Th 1 Lymphocyte</keyword>
  <keyword>Th 2 Lymphocyte</keyword>
  <keyword>Uveitis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uveitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

