<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001826</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990134</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-C-0134</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001826</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Observation of HIV-Infected Children Receiving Protease Inhibitor and Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitor</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Long-Term Observational Study of Immunologic Reconstitution in HIV-1 Infected Children Who Are Receiving Combination Protease Inhibitor and Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will continue to follow children who participated in an earlier National Cancer&#xD;
      Institute trial of HIV treatment with a protease inhibitor. Children in this study will&#xD;
      receive a combination of at least three drugs that include at least one protease inhibitor&#xD;
      and one reverse transcriptase inhibitor.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study will examine to what extent these drugs can restore immune function in HIV-infected&#xD;
      children and over what length of time. It will look at changes in the amounts of virus and&#xD;
      the specific types of immune cells in the body over the 96-week trial period. It will also&#xD;
      examine patients' immune system response to influenza and tetanus vaccinations.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The children will either continue to receive the anti-HIV drugs they have been taking, or&#xD;
      their medicines will be changed to a different combination of protease inhibitor and reverse&#xD;
      transcriptase inhibitor. Before and during the study, patients will undergo various tests,&#xD;
      including a physical examination, blood tests and chest X ray, immune response tests, CT&#xD;
      scan, eye examination, electrocardiogram and echocardiogram. A procedure called apheresis may&#xD;
      be done to collect white blood cells. In this procedure, whole blood is drawn similar to&#xD;
      donating blood, the white cells are separated out by a machine, and the red cells are&#xD;
      returned to the body.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the extent of immunoreconstitution in children receiving combination&#xD;
      antiretroviral therapy that includes a protease inhibitor and reverse transcriptase&#xD;
      inhibitors. The children who will be evaluated and followed in this study are those who have&#xD;
      previously been studied on other protease inhibitor-containing anti-HIV protocols within the&#xD;
      HIV and AIDS Malignancy Branch. This study will provide a mechanism to assess the long-term&#xD;
      immunologic changes of potent combination therapy in this unique population and to relate&#xD;
      this to the virologic changes. A total of 50 HIV-1 infected children will be studied. The&#xD;
      children enrolled in this protocol will either continue their current combination of protease&#xD;
      inhibitor and reverse transcriptase therapy or, if deemed clinically appropriate, will be&#xD;
      changed to a new, best available combination of protease inhibitor and reverse transcriptase&#xD;
      inhibitors. Long-term immunoreconstitution, defined as the repopulation of naive CD4+T&#xD;
      lymphocytes, will be studied by determining the presence and extent of production of new&#xD;
      naive (thymic derived) CD4+T cells and by the ability of patients to mount new helper T cell&#xD;
      responses after immunization with influenza and tetanus toxoid. Expansion of T cell receptor&#xD;
      will also be explored in subsets of enrolled patients. In addition, unforeseen toxicities&#xD;
      attributable to the use of combination antiretroviral therapy have been recognized and&#xD;
      described in adult patients. This study will evaluate abnormalities in lipid and glucose&#xD;
      metabolism, changes in the distribution of body fat, and surrogate markers of cardiovascular&#xD;
      disease risk in this cohort of pediatric patients.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>May 2006</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>50</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infection</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age greater than 1 year and less than 21 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Diagnosis of HIV-1 infection as defined by the Centers for Disease Control (CDC).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Currently on at least a three drug combination that includes a protease inhibitor (PI) and&#xD;
        reverse transcriptase inhibitor (RTI) therapy for at least 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patient must have received initial protease inhibitor treatment in studies in the HIV and&#xD;
        AIDS Malignancy Branch but need not be enrolled on another NIH study to be eligible for&#xD;
        this protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Age-adjusted CD4+ T lymphocytes greater than 200 cells/ml.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Measurements of CD4+45RA+ and CD4+45RO+ T lymphocytes taken within 9 weeks of the time of&#xD;
        initiation of protease-inhibitor therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Availability of a parent or guardian to provide informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA&#xD;
&#xD;
        Critically ill or clinically unstable child.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients receiving treatment for an infection that requires prolonged treatment must have&#xD;
        been stable on therapy for at least 14 days prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Administration of chemotherapeutic agents or use of immunomodulating agents such as high&#xD;
        dose corticosteroids, interferons, pentoxifylline, G-CSF/GM-CSF, erythropoietin, growth&#xD;
        hormone and other growth factors within one month of enrollment. However, patients on&#xD;
        anti-inflammatory drugs or stable doses of immunoglobulins (including hyperimmune&#xD;
        immunoglobulin) will be eligible unless the latter are directed at a T-cell specific&#xD;
        antigen.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Sexually active post-menarchal female unwilling to use a barrier method of contraception or&#xD;
        unwilling to remain sexually abstinent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who, in the opinion of the Protocol Chairperson or Principal Investigator:&#xD;
&#xD;
        may not be likely to benefit from this study,&#xD;
&#xD;
        may be put at undue risk by participation in this study,&#xD;
&#xD;
        are unlikely to comply with the study requirements.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clerici M, Shearer GM. Correlates of protection in HIV infection and the progression of HIV infection to AIDS. Immunol Lett. 1996 Jun;51(1-2):69-73. doi: 10.1016/0165-2478(96)02557-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8811347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ho DD. Toward HIV eradication or remission: the tasks ahead. Science. 1998 Jun 19;280(5371):1866-7. doi: 10.1126/science.280.5371.1866. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>9669944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chun TW, Carruth L, Finzi D, Shen X, DiGiuseppe JA, Taylor H, Hermankova M, Chadwick K, Margolick J, Quinn TC, Kuo YH, Brookmeyer R, Zeiger MA, Barditch-Crovo P, Siliciano RF. Quantification of latent tissue reservoirs and total body viral load in HIV-1 infection. Nature. 1997 May 8;387(6629):183-8. doi: 10.1038/387183a0.</citation>
    <PMID>9144289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2006</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>CD-4-Naive T Cells</keyword>
  <keyword>CD-4-Memory T Cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiviral Activity</keyword>
  <keyword>VB Repertoire</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunizations</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Experienced</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

