<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000430</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N01 AR92237</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NIAMS-040</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000430</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Low-Dose Hormone Replacement Therapy and Alendronate for Osteoporosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Trial of Continuous Low-Dose Hormone Replacement Therapy Combined With Alendronate in Postmenopausal Women With Low Bone Density</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Osteoporosis, a condition in which bones are fragile and break easily, is a major health&#xD;
      problem for postmenopausal women. Research studies have shown that both estrogen/progestin&#xD;
      replacement therapy (hormone replacement therapy, or HRT) and alendronate are effective in&#xD;
      preventing and treating osteoporosis. However, because these drugs work in somewhat different&#xD;
      ways, a combination of the two drugs might protect women from osteoporosis better than either&#xD;
      drug alone. In this study we will test whether HRT and alendronate given together for 3.5&#xD;
      years to postmenopausal women with low bone mass will have a greater effect on bone than&#xD;
      either HRT or alendronate given alone. We will also give every participant in this study&#xD;
      calcium and vitamin D supplements.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Clinical trials of estrogen/progestin replacement therapy (HRT) and a bisphosphonate,&#xD;
      alendronate (ALN), have demonstrated that both are effective in causing gains in bone mass&#xD;
      and preventing bone loss and fractures in postmenopausal women. The FDA has approved both&#xD;
      these drugs for prevention and treatment of fractures, and both are widely used in clinical&#xD;
      practice. Because both are approved and effective, and they work by different mechanisms,&#xD;
      many patients and their physicians ask whether both should be taken in combination,&#xD;
      particularly in cases of severe disease. The question is asked frequently because of the high&#xD;
      incidence of osteoporosis among women and the need for long-term prevention and treatments&#xD;
      that often last decades.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Indeed, physicians are using ALN and HRT together without adequate scientific support for the&#xD;
      assumption that the combination is more effective than either given alone.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Clinical trials are now underway to test conventional doses of HRT given as conjugated equine&#xD;
      estrogens (CEE), 0.625 mg/day or its equivalent, combined with ALN, 10 mg/day. However,&#xD;
      researchers are not studying the bone-sparing effectiveness of the combined administration of&#xD;
      ALN and low-dose continuous HRT given as CEE, 0.3 mg/d, along with medroxyprogesterone, 2.5&#xD;
      mg/d (MP). This low-dose continuous HRT regimen is attractive because of better convenience,&#xD;
      better patient tolerance, and reduced risk of breast cancer and other safety concerns&#xD;
      associated with conventional higher doses. Further, we have recently demonstrated that the&#xD;
      bone-sparing effect of this regimen is comparable to that of higher doses.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The long-term objective of this study is to test the hypothesis that the combined therapy&#xD;
      shows a greater bone effect than does either treatment given alone. Our specific aim is to&#xD;
      conduct a 3.5 year, randomized, double-blind, controlled trial of low-dose, continuous HRT&#xD;
      combined with alendronate, 10 mg/d (ALN), in three groups (72 people per group) of&#xD;
      estrogen-deprived postmenopausal women over age 60. We will give Group 1 low-dose HRT, Group&#xD;
      2 ALN, and Group 3 both low-dose HRT and ALN. We will give calcium and vitamin D supplements&#xD;
      to people in all three groups.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The primary outcome measures will be spine bone mineral density (SpBMD) and total hip bone&#xD;
      mineral density (HipBMD) measured by dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA). Secondary&#xD;
      outcome measures will be total body bone mineral content and forearm bone mineral content. In&#xD;
      addition, we will perform studies to characterize the mechanism of the effects of these&#xD;
      regimens. These studies will consist of measurements of urinary bone resorption markers,&#xD;
      serum bone formation markers, calcium excretion, calcium absorption, and application of a&#xD;
      model developed in our laboratory to estimate and compare the magnitudes of the anabolic&#xD;
      effects (if any) of all three interventions on SpBMD and HipBMD.&#xD;
&#xD;
      We have reported data showing that both agents have an anabolic effect on bone in humans,&#xD;
      meaning that they cause an increase in bone mass beyond that explained by a remodeling&#xD;
      transient brought about by reduction in bone remodeling rates. Further, research has shown&#xD;
      that HRT and ALN affect bone by different mechanisms. Thus, this combination may have an&#xD;
      additive effect on bone resulting in bone gain beyond that previously seen with other&#xD;
      interventions. This project will provide much-needed information to physicians and their&#xD;
      patients on the benefits and safety of this combination regimen so that they can make&#xD;
      &quot;evidence-based&quot; decisions on the choice of interventions to prevent and treat osteoporosis.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>September 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>240</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteopenia</condition>
  <condition>Osteoporosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alendronate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Estrogen/progestin therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Women at least 60 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Good general health.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willingness to participate in this 3.5 year study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ability to give informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ability to live independently and travel to the research center for visits (we will&#xD;
             provide transportation on a limited basis).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Spine bone mineral density (BMD) (L1-4) T-score between -1.0 and -2.5, or a hip&#xD;
             T-score between -1.0 and -2.5. A T-score of -1.0 is equal to a bone mass of one&#xD;
             standard deviation below the mean peak bone mass in healthy young adult women.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any history of cancer except the following: (a) superficial basal or squamous cell&#xD;
             carcinoma of the skin which has been completely resected or resolved by a topical&#xD;
             chemotherapeutic agent, and (b) other malignancies treated curatively at least 10&#xD;
             years previously, without any evidence of recurrence.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Abnormal transvaginal ultrasound that has not been investigated and cleared by&#xD;
             endometrial biopsy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of low-trauma hip or spine fracture previously diagnosed.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Serious residuals from cerebral vascular disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diabetes mellitus, except for easily controlled, non-insulin dependent or insulin&#xD;
             dependent diabetes mellitus without significant microvascular or neuropathic disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Serum creatinine &gt;1.9 mg/dl.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chronic liver disease or alcoholism.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Treatment with bone active agents such as fluoride or bisphosphonates within the&#xD;
             previous 2 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Treatment with calcitonin, estrogen, or a selective estrogen receptor modulator within&#xD;
             the previous 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Systemic corticosteroid therapy at pharmacologic levels for more than 6 months&#xD;
             duration.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any corticosteroid therapy within the previous 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Treatment with anticonvulsant therapy within the previous year.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Clinically significant abnormalities on pre-study laboratory or clinical screens.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Treatment with thyroid hormone is accepted, provided the patient is euthyroid at the&#xD;
             time of entry, and the serum TSH by ultrasensitive assay is normal.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Uncontrolled hypertension.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unstable angina.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Myocardial infarction within 1 year prior to entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Evidence of metabolic bone disease, e.g. hyper- or hypoparathyroidism, Paget's&#xD;
             disease, osteomalacia, osteogenesis imperfecta, or others.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active rheumatoid arthritis or collagen disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Recent major gastrointestinal disease (within the past year) such as peptic ulcer,&#xD;
             malabsorption, chronic ulcerative colitis, regional enteritis, or any significant&#xD;
             chronic diarrhea state.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Tobacco use at a level of more than 10 cigarettes per day.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert R. Recker, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Creighton University Osteoporosis Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joan M. Lappe, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Creighton University Osteoporosis Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Creighton University Osteoporosis Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68131</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2004</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 19, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 2, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 2, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 4, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Osteoporosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteopenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Postmenopausal women</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormone replacement therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Alendronate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases, Metabolic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alendronate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estrogens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Progestins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

