<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005631</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>99-092</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000067785</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-G00-1774</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005631</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rituximab and Combination Chemotherapy in Treating Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Large Cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cytoreduction and Stem Cell Mobilization With Rituximab and ICE for Patients With Refractory or Relapsed CD20+ B-Cell IGL Eligible for ASCT: The RICE Protocol</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Monoclonal antibodies such as rituximab can locate cancer cells and either kill&#xD;
      them or deliver cancer-killing substances to them without harming normal cells. Drugs used in&#xD;
      chemotherapy use different ways to stop cancer cells from dividing so they stop growing or&#xD;
      die. Combining combination chemotherapy with monoclonal antibody therapy may kill more cancer&#xD;
      cells.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PURPOSE: Phase II trial to study the effectiveness of rituximab and combination chemotherapy&#xD;
      in treating patients who have relapsed or refractory large cell lymphoma.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine the complete response rate in patients with relapsed or refractory&#xD;
      CD20-positive diffuse large cell, immunoblastic, or anaplastic large cell lymphoma treated&#xD;
      with cytoreduction and mobilization with rituximab, ifosfamide, carboplatin, and etoposide&#xD;
      (RICE). II. Assess the ability of this regimen to deplete the stem cell harvest of B-cells&#xD;
      and tumor cells in these patients. III. Assess the efficacy of this regimen to mobilize&#xD;
      peripheral blood progenitor cells in these patients. IV. Assess the safety and toxicity of&#xD;
      this regimen in these patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      OUTLINE: Cytoreduction and mobilization: Patients receive ifosfamide IV over 24 hours and&#xD;
      carboplatin IV on day 4 and etoposide IV over 1 hour on days 3-5. Chemotherapy repeats every&#xD;
      2 weeks for 3 courses. Patients receive rituximab IV on day -2 before initiation of&#xD;
      chemotherapy and on day 1 of each course of chemotherapy. Patients receive filgrastim (G-CSF)&#xD;
      subcutaneously (SC) daily on days 7-14 of each course of chemotherapy. Patients with complete&#xD;
      or partial response after completion of course 3 continue to receive G-CSF SC daily until&#xD;
      peripheral blood stem cells (PBSC) are harvested. When blood counts recover, PBSC are&#xD;
      harvested and selected for CD34+ cells. If sufficient numbers of CD34+ cells are not&#xD;
      obtained, patients undergo bone marrow harvest.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 36 patients will be accrued for this study within 2 years.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2002</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2002</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>filgrastim</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rituximab</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carboplatin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>etoposide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ifosfamide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically proven non-Hodgkin's lymphoma that is in first&#xD;
        relapse or refractory to primary therapy Eligible types: Diffuse large cell Immunoblastic&#xD;
        Anaplastic large cell Eligible for autologous peripheral blood stem cell transplantation&#xD;
        CD20-positive disease Measurable disease No brain parenchyma involvement&#xD;
&#xD;
        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 to 72 Performance status: Not specified Life expectancy:&#xD;
        Not specified Hematopoietic: Absolute neutrophil count greater than 1,000/mm3 Platelet&#xD;
        count greater than 50,000/mm3 Hepatic: Bilirubin no greater than 2.0 mg/dL unless due to&#xD;
        Gilbert's disease No chronic or persistent hepatitis Hepatitis B surface antigen negative&#xD;
        Renal: Creatinine no greater than 1.5 mg/dL OR Creatinine clearance greater than 60 mL/min&#xD;
        No chronic renal insufficiency Cardiovascular: Normal baseline cardiac function Ejection&#xD;
        fraction at least 50% by echocardiogram or MUGA scan No myocardial infarction within the&#xD;
        past 6 months No unstable angina No cardiac arrhythmias except chronic atrial fibrillation&#xD;
        Other: Not pregnant or nursing Negative pregnancy test Fertile patients must use effective&#xD;
        barrier contraception HIV negative No other malignancy within the past 5 years except basal&#xD;
        cell or squamous cell skin cancer or carcinoma in situ of the cervix No uncontrolled&#xD;
        infection&#xD;
&#xD;
        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: See Disease Characteristics Prior rituximab&#xD;
        allowed Chemotherapy: No prior carboplatin or cisplatin Endocrine therapy: Not specified&#xD;
        Radiotherapy: Not specified Surgery: Not specified&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>72 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig Moskowitz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kewalramani T, Zelenetz AD, Nimer SD, Portlock C, Straus D, Noy A, O'Connor O, Filippa DA, Teruya-Feldstein J, Gencarelli A, Qin J, Waxman A, Yahalom J, Moskowitz CH. Rituximab and ICE as second-line therapy before autologous stem cell transplantation for relapsed or primary refractory diffuse large B-cell lymphoma. Blood. 2004 May 15;103(10):3684-8. doi: 10.1182/blood-2003-11-3911. Epub 2004 Jan 22.</citation>
    <PMID>14739217</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 16, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 18, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 18, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 19, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>recurrent adult diffuse large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult immunoblastic large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>anaplastic large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ifosfamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

