<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005231</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1111</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01HL041335</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005231</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development, Testing, and Validation of A Protocol To Assess Cardiovascular Reactivity in Human Populations</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To develop a comprehensive protocol for assessing cardiovascular reactivity to stressors, for&#xD;
      use in epidemiological and clinical investigations of cardiovascular diseases in healthy&#xD;
      populations.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Cardiovascular reactivity (CVR) is the change in a cardiovascular parameter in response to a&#xD;
      discrete environmental stimulus. A leading theory linking behavior to cardiovascular diseases&#xD;
      such as atherosclerosis and hypertension proposed that an exaggerated physiological response&#xD;
      to a psychological challenge increased the risk for development of disease. Such a link had&#xD;
      not been established conclusively in 1988. To a considerable extent, this might have been due&#xD;
      to the fact that numerous approaches were devised to elicit and measure CVR. Furthermore, no&#xD;
      single test or combination of tests was available which would be suitable for administering&#xD;
      to large numbers of individuals who differed in age, gender, cultural or ethnic background,&#xD;
      and socioeconomic status, as would be required for definitive prospective studies of&#xD;
      reactivity and cardiovascular disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A conference sponsored by the NHLBI and the University of Pittsburgh in 1984 comprehensively&#xD;
      reviewed the concept of reactivity, its measurement, and its hypothesized relationship to a&#xD;
      disease process. The value of CVR is that it provides an estimation of the changes in&#xD;
      cardiovascular function in response to the challenges of daily life, and thus may serve as a&#xD;
      better marker or predictor of cardiovascular disease risk than the usual 'casual'&#xD;
      measurements. Essential hypertension appears to be a multi-factorially determined disorder,&#xD;
      whose etiology encompasses different elements for different individuals. Physiological&#xD;
      changes induced by excessive cardiovascular reactivity are among the mechanisms suggested to&#xD;
      account for the transition from borderline to established hypertension. In this model,&#xD;
      episodic cardiovascular activation elicited by behavioral challenges leads to autoregulatory&#xD;
      adjustments culminating in elevated blood pressure. An alternative interpretation is that&#xD;
      both elevated CVR and elevated blood pressure are reflections of underlying nervous system&#xD;
      pathology. Prospective studies, using appropriate behavioral designs and a standardized&#xD;
      protocol to assess cardiovascular reactivity could distinguish between these alternatives.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The possible role of cardiovascular reactivity in coronary heart disease was supported by&#xD;
      evidence from both basic and clinical studies. The hemodynamic forces resulting from&#xD;
      turbulence and shear stress at curves and bifurcations of the coronary arteries had been&#xD;
      cited as responsible for the greater degree of atherosclerosis in high heart rate, as opposed&#xD;
      to low heart rate animals. Monkeys with large elevations of heart rate in response to&#xD;
      psychological arousal developed significantly more atherosclerosis. Although the above&#xD;
      findings had not been confirmed in humans as of 1988, a substantial majority of studies&#xD;
      reported greater reactivity of Type A subjects during stress.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Although the evidence was suggestive and the mechanism plausible, stress-induced&#xD;
      cardiovascular reactivity had not been investigated as a risk factor for cardiovascular&#xD;
      disease. In addition to basic research to determine the parameters and physiological&#xD;
      determinants of reactivity, clinical and epidemiological studies were needed to establish&#xD;
      whether this association was reliable. Especially needed were prospective, longitudinal&#xD;
      studies of the association between reactivity and disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The Clinical Applications and Prevention Advisory Committee of the National Heart, Lung, and&#xD;
      Blood Institute recommended the development of this study in February 1987. The National&#xD;
      Heart, Lung, and Blood Advisory Council approved the concept in May 1987. A Request for&#xD;
      Applications was released in August 1987 and awards made in July 1988.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Investigators at the University of Miami evaluated cardiovascular and hormonal functions at&#xD;
      rest and after standardized manipulations designed to evoke autonomic nervous system arousal.&#xD;
      Two hundred and fifty-six subjects were enrolled into a 2 (male, female) x 2 (Black, white) x&#xD;
      2 (25-44 years, 55-64 years) x 2 (Miami, Durham) design. Subjects were compared across a&#xD;
      broad range of socioeconomic status. Each subject was scheduled for three laboratory&#xD;
      sessions. Sessions 1 and 2 were two weeks apart. Session 3 was six months later. During the&#xD;
      sessions, individuals were subjected to a forehead cold pressor stimulus, a video game, and&#xD;
      an evaluative speech stressor. Noninvasive cardiovascular measures assessed included heart&#xD;
      rate, cardiac output, peripheral resistance, Heather Index, pre-ejection period, left&#xD;
      ventricular ejection period, and diastolic, systolic, and mean arterial blood pressure. On&#xD;
      the same day as the laboratory session, subjects wore an ambulatory impedance and&#xD;
      electrocardiogram monitor at work and at home. The following day subjects wore an ambulatory&#xD;
      blood pressure monitor at work and at home. Data were analyzed in terms of stability of&#xD;
      baseline values, differences in laboratory reactivity between groups, differences in&#xD;
      reactivity between tasks, reliability of responses to tasks across sessions, differences in&#xD;
      reactivity as an individual difference variable, and generalizability of reactivity in the&#xD;
      laboratory to cardiovascular function observed in more naturalistic settings. Improved&#xD;
      procedures were developed for monitoring impedance cardiographic and electrocardiographic&#xD;
      activity.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Investigators at the University of Pittsburgh developed a battery of tests to elicit&#xD;
      differential vascular, cardiac inotropic and chronotropic responses. Each task was based on a&#xD;
      computer-driven video game which permitted a standardized task presentation and multiple&#xD;
      response measurement. During the initial prototyping year, items were selected to maximize&#xD;
      reliability, validity, and applicability to diverse demographic groups. Circadian ambulatory&#xD;
      studies in this year established optimal baselines for reactivity assessment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in&#xD;
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1988</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1991</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Neil Schneiderman</last_name>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagel JH, Shyu LY, Reddy SP, Hurwitz BE, McCabe PM, Schneiderman N. New signal processing techniques for improved precision of noninvasive impedance cardiography. Ann Biomed Eng. 1989;17(5):517-34. doi: 10.1007/BF02368071.</citation>
    <PMID>2610423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson NB, McNeilly M, Myers H. Autonomic reactivity and hypertension in blacks: a review and proposed model. Ethn Dis. 1991 Spring;1(2):154-70.</citation>
    <PMID>1842532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peckerman A, Saab PG, McCabe PM, Skyler JS, Winters RW, Llabre MM, Schneiderman N. Blood pressure reactivity and perception of pain during the forehead cold pressor test. Psychophysiology. 1991 Sep;28(5):485-95. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8986.1991.tb01985.x.</citation>
    <PMID>1758926</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jennings JR, Kamarck T, Stewart C, Eddy M, Johnson P. Alternate cardiovascular baseline assessment techniques: vanilla or resting baseline. Psychophysiology. 1992 Nov;29(6):742-50. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8986.1992.tb02052.x.</citation>
    <PMID>1461961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kamarck TW. Recent developments in the study of cardiovascular reactivity: contributions from psychometric theory and social psychology. Psychophysiology. 1992 Sep;29(5):491-503. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8986.1992.tb02023.x.</citation>
    <PMID>1410179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kamarck TW, Jennings JR, Debski TT, Glickman-Weiss E, Johnson PS, Eddy MJ, Manuck SB. Reliable measures of behaviorally-evoked cardiovascular reactivity from a PC-based test battery: results from student and community samples. Psychophysiology. 1992 Jan;29(1):17-28. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8986.1992.tb02006.x.</citation>
    <PMID>1609024</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kamarck TW, Jennings JR, Pogue-Geile M, Manuck SB. A multidimensional measurement model for cardiovascular reactivity: stability and cross-validation in two adult samples. Health Psychol. 1994 Nov;13(6):471-8. doi: 10.1037//0278-6133.13.6.471.</citation>
    <PMID>7889901</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kamarck TW, Jennings JR, Stewart CJ, Eddy MJ. Reliable responses to a cardiovascular reactivity protocol: a replication study in a biracial female sample. Psychophysiology. 1993 Nov;30(6):627-34. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8986.1993.tb02088.x.</citation>
    <PMID>8248454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Debski TT, Zhang Y, Jennings JR, Kamarck TW. Stability of cardiac impedance measures: aortic opening (B-point) detection and scoring. Biol Psychol. 1993 Aug;36(1-2):63-74. doi: 10.1016/0301-0511(93)90081-i.</citation>
    <PMID>8218625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2000</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 13, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

