<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001646</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>970164</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>97-I-0164</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001646</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Voriconazole vs. Amphotericin B in the Treatment of Invasive Aspergillosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Voriconazole vs. Amphotericin B in the Treatment of Invasive Aspergillosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Invasive aspergillosis is a fungal disease which is increasing in incidence with the increase&#xD;
      in immunocompromised persons in our population. Persons with prolonged neutropenia secondary&#xD;
      to cytotoxic chemotherapies are at the highest risk for acute aspergillosis. Patients&#xD;
      undergoing bone marrow transplantation, receiving prolonged corticosteroid or other&#xD;
      immunosuppressive therapies, and persons with HIV infection and AIDS are also at risk. Even&#xD;
      with antifungal therapy, aspergillosis in its acute invasive forms has a high mortality. In&#xD;
      bone marrow transplantation patients and in those whose infection involves the brain, this&#xD;
      mortality is greater than 90%. Amphotericin B in its conventional form, is the current&#xD;
      standard treatment for this disease. Response to therapy with amphotericin B usually ranges&#xD;
      between 20-60% in most studies. The higher response rates are usually seen in those patients&#xD;
      who can tolerate this agent for at least 14 days. Because of its nephrotoxicity and other&#xD;
      adverse effects, alternatives to conventional amphotericin B have been sought. These&#xD;
      currently include liposomal forms of amphotericin B and itraconazole. Although these forms&#xD;
      show a decrease in adverse effects, the efficacy of these drugs has not been shown to be&#xD;
      equivalent to conventional amphotericin B.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Voriconazole is an investigational antifungal drug currently being brought to phase III&#xD;
      trials in the US. This azole has been shown active against Aspergillus spp. in vitro, and in&#xD;
      animal models and early human trials to be effective against aspergillosis. It has been shown&#xD;
      to be well-tolerated and is available in an intravenous and oral formulation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will evaluate the efficacy, safety, and toleration of voriconazole compared to&#xD;
      conventional therapy with amphotericin B as primary treatment of acute invasive aspergillosis&#xD;
      in immunocompromised patients. Patients will be randomized to open-labelled therapy with&#xD;
      voriconazole or amphotericin B in a one-to-one ratio.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Invasive aspergillosis is a fungal disease which is increasing in incidence with the increase&#xD;
      in immunocompromised persons in our population. Persons with prolonged neutropenia secondary&#xD;
      to cytotoxic chemotherapies are at the highest risk for acute aspergillosis. Patients&#xD;
      undergoing bone marrow transplantation, receiving prolonged corticosteroid or other&#xD;
      immunosuppressive therapies, and persons with HIV infection and AIDS are also at risk. Even&#xD;
      with antifungal therapy, aspergillosis in its acute invasive forms has a high mortality. In&#xD;
      bone marrow transplantation patients and in those whose infection involves the brain, this&#xD;
      mortality is greater than 90%. Amphotericin B, in its conventional form, is the current&#xD;
      standard treatment for this disease. Response to therapy with amphotericin B usually ranges&#xD;
      between 20-60% in most studies. The higher response rates are usually seen in those patients&#xD;
      who can tolerate this agent for at least 14 days. Because of its nephrotoxicity and other&#xD;
      adverse effects, alternatives to conventional amphotericin B have been sought. These&#xD;
      currently include liposomal forms of amphotericin B and itraconazole. Although these forms&#xD;
      show a decrease in adverse effects, the efficacy of these drugs has not been shown to be&#xD;
      equivalent to conventional amphotericin B.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Voriconazole is an investigational antifungal drug currently being brought to phase III&#xD;
      trials in the U.S. This azole has been shown active against Aspergillus sp. in vitro, and in&#xD;
      animal models and early human trials to be effective against aspergillosis. It has been shown&#xD;
      to be well-tolerated and is available in an intravenous and oral formulation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will evaluate the efficacy, safety, and toleration of voriconazole compared to&#xD;
      conventional therapy with amphotericin B as primary treatment of acute invasive aspergillosis&#xD;
      in immunocompromised patients. Although the original protocol allows enrollment of subjects&#xD;
      older than 12 years old we do not expect to enroll patients younger than 18 years old.&#xD;
      Patients will be randomized to open-labelled therapy with voriconazole or amphotericin B in a&#xD;
      one-to-one ratio.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date>August 2000</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>10</enrollment>
  <condition>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Aspergillosis</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Neutropenia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Voriconazole</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amphotericin B</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Males and females of greater than 12 years of age with any of the following conditions:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Allogeneic or autologous bone marrow/ peripheral stem cell transplant.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Hematological malignancy (including lymphoma).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Aplastic anemia and myelodysplastic syndromes (currently on immunosuppressive treatment).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Solid organ transplantation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Solid organ malignancy (after cytotoxic chemotherapy).&#xD;
&#xD;
        HIV infection/AIDS.&#xD;
&#xD;
        High dose prolonged corticosteroid therapy (greater than or equal to 20 mg daily of&#xD;
        prednisone or equivalent for greater than 3 weeks) or prolonged therapy with other&#xD;
        immunosuppressive agents (e.g., azathioprine, methotrexate).&#xD;
&#xD;
        WITH a diagnosis of definite or probable acute invasive aspergillosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        The fungal infection at baseline should represent a new episode of acute invasive&#xD;
        aspergillosis. Any course of systemic treatment with amphotericin B (conventional or lipid&#xD;
        formulation) or itraconazole should have been completed at least 8 weeks prior to study&#xD;
        entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Signed informed consent must be obtained prior to study participation (patient, relative or&#xD;
        legal representative). For patients aged 12-17 years, the written informed consent of the&#xD;
        parents or legal guardian must also be obtained.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Women of child bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at entry and must&#xD;
        agree to use barrier methods of contraception throughout the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with sarcoidosis, aspergilloma or allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with chronic invasive aspergillosis with a duration of symptoms or radiological&#xD;
        findings for more than 4 weeks prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients that have received systemic antifungal therapy at doses greater than 0.5&#xD;
        mg/kg/day for conventional or lipid formulations of amphotericin B or greater than 200&#xD;
        mg/day of itraconazole, for more than 96 hours during the two week period prior to study&#xD;
        entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with a diagnosis of CMV pneumonia.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No pregnant or lactating females.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with a history of hypersensitivity or intolerance to azole antifungal agents&#xD;
        including miconazole, ketoconazole, fluconazole, or itraconazole.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with a history of hypersensitivity or severe intolerance (despite supportive&#xD;
        therapy) to conventional or a lipid formulation of amphotericin B.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No subjects who are receiving and cannot discontinue the following drugs at least 24 hours&#xD;
        prior to randomization: Terfenadine, cisapride and astemizole (due to the possibility of&#xD;
        QTc prolongation); Sulphonylureas (as these compounds have a narrow therapeutic window and&#xD;
        an increase in plasma levels may lead to hypoglycemia).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No subjects who have received the following drugs within 14 days prior to randomization:&#xD;
        Rifampin, carbamazepine and barbiturates as these are potent inducers of hepatic enzymes&#xD;
        and will result in undetectable levels of voriconazole.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients who are receiving or are likely to received any investigational drug (any&#xD;
        unlicensed new chemical entity), except one of the following classes of medications: cancer&#xD;
        chemotherapeutic agents, antiretrovirals, therapies for HIV/AIDS-related opportunistic&#xD;
        infections.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients who are receiving the following medications or treatments during the study&#xD;
        period: G-CSF or GM-CSF (for other than of granulocytopenia) any systemic antifungal&#xD;
        medication active against Aspergillus white blood cell transfusions.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with the following abnormalities of liver function tests: AST, ALT greater than&#xD;
        5x ULN (upper limit normal); alkaline phosphatase, total bilirubin greater than 5x ULN.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with renal insufficiency that would contraindicate treatment with initial&#xD;
        randomized therapy (serum creatinine greater than 2.5 mg/dl).&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with a life expectancy of less than 72 hours.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients on artificial ventilation, unlikely to be extubated within 24 hours of study&#xD;
        entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients for whom written informed consent cannot be obtained.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients that have already participated in this trial.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with any condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, could affect&#xD;
        patient safety, preclude evaluation of response, or render it unlikely that the&#xD;
        contemplated course of therapy can be completed.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pocock SJ, Simon R. Sequential treatment assignment with balancing for prognostic factors in the controlled clinical trial. Biometrics. 1975 Mar;31(1):103-15.</citation>
    <PMID>1100130</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 1999</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Aspergillus</keyword>
  <keyword>Azole</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunocompromise</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aspergillosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neutropenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Voriconazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amphotericin B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposomal amphotericin B</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

