<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001888</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990076</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-H-0076</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001888</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sample Collections From the Airways of Asthmatic Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Asthma Sample Collection Protocol</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fiberoptic bronchoscopy is a procedure which involves passing a pencil-thin tube into the&#xD;
      lung in order to collect fluid and cells from the airways. Fiberoptic bronchoscopy can&#xD;
      collect cells from the walls of airways by gently brushing them (bronchial brushing). In&#xD;
      addition, squirting small amounts of sterile water in to the airway and gently suctioning it&#xD;
      back into the bronchoscope (bronchoalveolar lavage) collects cells.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In this study, researchers plan to perform these tests on patients with asthma and normal&#xD;
      volunteers. This research may help to improve the understanding of the processes involved in&#xD;
      airway inflammation and asthma.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This tissue procurement protocol proposes to perform bronchoscopy with bronchoalveolar&#xD;
      lavage, bronchial brushings, and bronchial wall biopsies as well as to collect samples of&#xD;
      sputum, exhaled breath condensates and blood, in order to evaluate the molecular mechanisms&#xD;
      underlying the pathogenesis of airway inflammation, airway hyperresponsiveness, and airway&#xD;
      remodeling in asthmatic subjects.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2, 1999</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the role of apolipoprotein and lipid pathways in asthmatic and non-asthmatic subjects.</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>These studies will increase the understanding of the pathogenic mechanisms underlying asthmatic airway inflammation and may identify novel therapeutic targets.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the role of exosome-associated proteins and receptors in the regulation of airway inflammatory responses</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>These studies will increase the understanding of the pathogenic mechanisms underlying asthmatic airway inflammation and may identify novel therapeutic targets.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the expression, regulation, and function of differentially expressed proteins and genes in human airway structural and inflammatory cell populations in asthma</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>These studies will increase the understanding of the pathogenic mechanisms underlying asthmatic airway inflammation and may identify novel therapeutic targets.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the relative contribution of specific soluble pro-inflammatory cytokines and receptors in asthmatic bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) in mediating airway structural and inflammatory cell responses</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>These studies will increase the understanding of the pathogenic mechanisms underlying asthmatic airway inflammation and may identify novel therapeutic targets.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the expression, regulation, and function of proteins regulating the release of soluble receptors and mediators from asthmatic inflammatory and structural cell populations</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>These studies will increase the understanding of the pathogenic mechanisms underlying asthmatic airway inflammation and may identify novel therapeutic targets.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Asthmatics</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Research Volunteers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Any individual between the ages of 18 and 75 with asthma will be accepted into the study.&#xD;
        Since asthma has a roughly equivalent prevalence in groups differing in race and gender,&#xD;
        recruitment of study participants will be aimed at selecting a study population which&#xD;
        reflect this diversity. Asthmatic or research volunteers with HIV infection will be&#xD;
        excluded from the study so as not to include patients with HIV-related lymphocytic airway&#xD;
        inflammation. Volunteers will be obtained through the NIH Clinical Research Volunteer&#xD;
        Program or other standard channels at NIH.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        ASTHMATICS:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Patients undergoing a research bronchoscopy will be between 18 and 75 years of age,&#xD;
             male or female. The diagnosis of asthma requires a history of intermittent, reversible&#xD;
             expiratory flow limitation. In addition, patients will have demonstrated evidence of&#xD;
             either an abnormal methacholine challenge or reversible airway obstruction. An&#xD;
             abnormal methacholine challenge will be defined as a decrease in FEV1 of at least 20%&#xD;
             at a PD20 dose &lt; 200 microgram. Reversible airway obstruction will be defined as an&#xD;
             improvement of at least 10% in either the FEV1 or FVC following bronchodilator&#xD;
             treatment. Methacholine challenge testing will not be performed if the subject has a&#xD;
             history of allergy to methacholine. Results of testing performed by the subject s&#xD;
             primary care provider may be accepted as evidence of reversible airflow obstruction.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. For women of childbearing potential, negative pregnancy test and willingness to adhere&#xD;
             to reliable birth control methods prior to&#xD;
&#xD;
             bronchoscopy or sputum induction.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Asthmatic research subjects who will only be providing research blood specimens, nasal&#xD;
             epithelial lining fluid, spontaneously expectorated sputum, or exhaled breath&#xD;
             condensate, and will not be undergoing a research bronchoscopy or sputum induction,&#xD;
             may participate in the protocol by providing a clinical history that they have asthma&#xD;
             and are not pregnant. Documentation of an abnormal methacholine challenge or&#xD;
             reversible airflow obstruction or a negative pregnancy test, for women of childbearing&#xD;
             age, will not be required for donation of research blood specimens, or other&#xD;
             non-invasive samples, such as nasal epithelial lining fluid, sputum, or exhaled breath&#xD;
             condensate.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        ASTHMATICS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Diagnosis of a pulmonary disorder other than asthma (e.g., chronic bronchitis, cystic&#xD;
        fibrosis, HIV-related lymphocytic airway inflammation).&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of drug or alcohol abuse within the past year.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Positive test for human immunodeficiency virus (to exclude patients with HIV-related&#xD;
        lymphocytic airway inflammation) or hepatitis virus.&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA - RESEARCH VOLUNTEERS:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Research volunteers undergoing a research bronchoscopy will be between 18 and 75 years&#xD;
             of age, male or female.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. A negative inhalational methacholine challenge as defined by the absence of a 20%&#xD;
             decrease in FEV1 at a PD20 dose of &gt; 400 microgram (normal bronchial&#xD;
             hyperresponsiveness). Methacholine challenge testing will not be performed if the&#xD;
             subject has a history of allergy to methacholine. Results of testing performed by the&#xD;
             subject s primary care provider may be accepted as evidence of a negative methacholine&#xD;
             challenge.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. For women of childbearing potential, negative pregnancy test within 2 weeks prior to&#xD;
             bronchoscopy and willingness to adhere to reliable birth control methods prior to&#xD;
             bronchoscopy or sputum induction.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Research volunteers who will only be providing research blood specimens, nasal&#xD;
             epithelial lining fluid, sputum, spontaneously expectorated sputum, or exhaled breath&#xD;
             condensate, and will not be undergoing a research bronchoscopy or sputum induction,&#xD;
             may be included in the protocol without documentation of a negative inhalational&#xD;
             methacholine challenge or a negative pregnancy test if they provide a history that&#xD;
             they do not have asthma and that they are not currently pregnant, for women of&#xD;
             childbearing&#xD;
&#xD;
        age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA - RESEARCH VOLUNTEERS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Same as the asthmatic exclusion criteria plus a history of asthma.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stewart J Levine, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kamah Howard, C.R.N.P.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-1878</phone>
    <email>kamahh@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stewart J Levine, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-1553</phone>
    <email>levines@nhlbi.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY dial 711</phone_ext>
      <email>ccopr@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1999-H-0076.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 18, 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 21, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 21, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Induced Sputum</keyword>
  <keyword>Exhaled Breath Condensate</keyword>
  <keyword>Fiberoptic Bronchoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Bronchoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>mRNA</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

