<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001698</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>980118</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>98-C-0118</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001698</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized, Double Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Phase IIB Trial of Ketorolac Mouth Rinse Evaluating the Effect of Cyclooxygenase Inhibition on Oropharyngeal Leukoplakia: Collaborative Study of the NCI, NIDCD and the NIDCR</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Double Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Phase IIB Trial of Ketorolac Mouth Rinse Evaluating the Effect of Cyclooxygenase Inhibition on Oropharyngeal Leukoplakia: Collaborative Study of the NCI, NIDCD and the NIDCR</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In Phase II trials, treatment with ketorolac tromethamine oral rinse has been shown to block&#xD;
      periodontal disease progression even in the absence of standard clinical intervention such as&#xD;
      scaling and root planing which is routinely done to reduce the periodontal pathogen load that&#xD;
      is driving the local destructive host inflammatory response. Resolution of periodontal&#xD;
      disease has a favorable effect on normalizing the cellular and biochemical indices of&#xD;
      inflammation as reflected by histological changes as well as the levels of prostaglandin E2&#xD;
      (PGE2) and interleukin I beta (IL-1beta). In this trial, we will prospectively evaluate if&#xD;
      eliminating the inflammatory process (via inhibition of PGE2 biosynthesis) in the oral cavity&#xD;
      has a favorable impact on reversing oropharyngeal leukoplakia. To test this hypothesis, up to&#xD;
      57 prospectively identified individuals with objective findings of oropharyngeal leukoplakia&#xD;
      will be randomized to receive either a mouth rinse containing ketorolac or placebo. Ketorolac&#xD;
      is a 7-fold selective inhibitor of cyclooxygenase-2 (Cox-2), which has been designed for&#xD;
      local delivery to maximize the drug exposure to critical oral target tissues while minimizing&#xD;
      gastric and systemic exposure to the drug. All responses will be determined at the three&#xD;
      month completion of trial using the response criteria developed at MD Anderson Cancer Center.&#xD;
      The drug will be given for three months and then all the patients will be followed for one&#xD;
      additional month off all oral treatment to observe for late side effects. Based on the&#xD;
      analysis of oral exam and photographically documented change in the pretreatment area of&#xD;
      leukoplakia, the response of all patients will be determined.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The evaluation of the outcome will include a measurable secondary endpoint consisting of an&#xD;
      assessment of histological change as determined by serial punch biopsies of the oral cavity.&#xD;
      In addition, a panel of carcinogenesis and inflammatory markers will be serially measured at&#xD;
      baseline, at one month follow up or at study conclusion. In the residual tissue, other&#xD;
      bioassays will be evaluated to determine their suitability as intermediate endpoint markers.&#xD;
      The purpose of this study is a preliminary evaluation of the effectiveness of ketorolac as a&#xD;
      potential chemoprevention agent for oropharyngeal cancer. If ketorolac administration in this&#xD;
      preliminary Phase IIB trial is associated with reversal of leukoplakia, then a definitive&#xD;
      Phase III chemoprevention trial with a cancer reduction endpoint (most likely in a&#xD;
      cooperative group-type setting) may be the next validation step.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In Phase II trials, treatment with ketorolac tromethamine oral rinse has been shown to block&#xD;
      periodontal disease progression even in the absence of standard clinical intervention such as&#xD;
      scaling and root planing which is routinely done to reduce the periodontal pathogen load that&#xD;
      is driving the local destructive host inflammatory response. Resolution of periodontal&#xD;
      disease has a favorable effect on normalizing the cellular and biochemical indices of&#xD;
      inflammation as reflected by histological changes as well as the levels of prostaglandin E2&#xD;
      (PGE2) and interleukin I beta (IL-1beta). In this trial, we will prospectively evaluate if&#xD;
      eliminating the inflammatory process (via inhibition of PGE2 biosynthesis) in the oral cavity&#xD;
      has a favorable impact on reversing oropharyngeal leukoplakia. To test this hypothesis, up to&#xD;
      57 prospectively identified individuals with objective findings of oropharyngeal leukoplakia&#xD;
      will be randomized to receive either a mouth rinse containing ketorolac or placebo. Ketorolac&#xD;
      is a 7-fold selective inhibitor of cyclooxygenase-2 (Cox-2), which has been designed for&#xD;
      local delivery to maximize the drug exposure to critical oral target tissues while minimizing&#xD;
      gastric and systemic exposure to the drug. All responses will be determined at the three&#xD;
      month completion of trial using the response criteria developed at MD Anderson Cancer Center.&#xD;
      The drug will be given for three months and then all the patients will be followed for one&#xD;
      additional month off all oral treatment to observe for late side effects. Based on the&#xD;
      analysis of oral exam and photographically documented change in the pretreatment area of&#xD;
      leukoplakia, the response of all patients will be determined.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The evaluation of the outcome will include a measurable secondary endpoint consisting of an&#xD;
      assessment of histological change as determined by serial punch biopsies of the oral cavity.&#xD;
      In addition, a panel of carcinogenesis and inflammatory markers will be serially measured at&#xD;
      baseline, at one month follow up or at study conclusion. In the residual tissue, other&#xD;
      bioassays will be evaluated to determine their suitability as intermediate endpoint markers.&#xD;
      The purpose of this study is a preliminary evaluation of the effectiveness of ketorolac as a&#xD;
      potential chemoprevention agent for oropharyngeal cancer. If ketorolac administration in this&#xD;
      preliminary Phase IIB trial is associated with reversal of leukoplakia, then a definitive&#xD;
      Phase III chemoprevention trial with a cancer reduction endpoint (most likely in a&#xD;
      cooperative group-type setting) may be the next validation step.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>57</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukoplakia</condition>
  <condition>Periodontal Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketorolac Rinse</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must have objective evidence of oral leukoplakia. This includes subjects who have&#xD;
        had a previous diagnosis of head and neck or oral cancer, who are currently free of&#xD;
        evidence of known cancer for at least three months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must have bidimensionally measurable lesions.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must consent to serial photography and biopsy to document response to treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        All patients old enough to give their own informed consent (greater than or equal to 18&#xD;
        years old) are eligible.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects must be excellent performance status (Performance Status 0-1).&#xD;
&#xD;
        In addition, they must be otherwise medically fit in the opinion of the PI with no other&#xD;
        uncontrolled medical conditions.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with a hypersensitivity to aspirin, lidocaine or non-steroid anti-inflammatory&#xD;
        agents or retinoids will be ineligible.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients using antibiotics, steroids, NSAID, aspirin, probenecid or antihistamines for an&#xD;
        extended regimen of at least 10 or more consecutive days, or any immunosuppressants,&#xD;
        anticoagulants, dilantin, lithium, methotrexate, phenothiazines, investigational drugs with&#xD;
        pharmacological activity that could compromise the test product safety during the 30 days&#xD;
        immediately preceding the first treatment visit.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with serious or debilitating oral conditions that require extensive dental&#xD;
        procedures in order to safely participate in this trial. This trial does not envision the&#xD;
        need to do dental procedures (such as root canal or gingival procedure) in order to allow a&#xD;
        potential participant to enroll on this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Individuals with a social or psychiatric situation interfering with study compliance or an&#xD;
        unwillingness to undergo the serial oral biopsies will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with compromised respiratory function manifested by shortness of breath with mild&#xD;
        exertion or dependency on supplemental oxygen.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with compromised cardiovascular status including poorly controlled angina or&#xD;
        congestive heart failure.&#xD;
&#xD;
        ELIGIBILITY FOR ORAL IMAGING SUBSTUDY:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participation in this substudy requires that patients be enrolled in the parent trial.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects must have given their consent and signed supplemental informed consent for the&#xD;
        pilot study involving oral imaging.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cavanaugh PF Jr, Meredith MP, Buchanan W, Doyle MJ, Reddy MS, Jeffcoat MK. Coordinate production of PGE2 and IL-1 beta in the gingival crevicular fluid of adults with periodontitis: its relationship to alveolar bone loss and disruption by twice daily treatment with ketorolac tromethamine oral rinse. J Periodontal Res. 1998 Feb;33(2):75-82. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0765.1998.tb02295.x.</citation>
    <PMID>9553866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong WK, Sporn MB. Recent advances in chemoprevention of cancer. Science. 1997 Nov 7;278(5340):1073-7. doi: 10.1126/science.278.5340.1073.</citation>
    <PMID>9353183</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Potter M. Experimental plasmacytomagenesis in mice. Hematol Oncol Clin North Am. 1997 Apr;11(2):323-47. doi: 10.1016/s0889-8588(05)70434-2.</citation>
    <PMID>9137973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2004</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Chemoprevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Direct Epithelial Delivery</keyword>
  <keyword>Tobacco-induced Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Field Cancerization</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukoplakia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Periodontal Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketorolac</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

