<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001901</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990040</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-I-0040</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001901</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Etanercept to Treat Wegener's Granulomatosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Trial of TNFR:Fc (Etanercept) in Patients With Wegener's Granulomatosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the use of etanercept (also called Enbrel or TNFR:Fc) in patients&#xD;
      with Wegener's granulomatosis, a type of vasculitis (blood vessel inflammation). Wegener's&#xD;
      granulomatosis may affect many parts of the body, including the brain, nerves, eyes, sinuses,&#xD;
      lungs, kidneys, intestinal tract, skin, joints, heart, and other sites. Generally, the&#xD;
      greater the disease involvement, the more life-threatening it is. Standard treatment is a&#xD;
      combination of prednisone and a cytotoxic agent-usually cyclophosphamide or methotrexate.&#xD;
      However, many patients treated with this regimen have a disease relapse, and others cannot&#xD;
      take these drugs because of severe side effects. This study will evaluate etanercept's safety&#xD;
      and effectiveness, and particularly its value in reducing the need for prednisone and&#xD;
      preventing disease relapse.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The Food and Drug Administration has approved etanercept for treating rheumatoid arthritis,&#xD;
      another inflammatory disease. The drug works by blocking the activity of TNF-a protein made&#xD;
      by white blood cells that is involved in the inflammatory process. Since prednisone also&#xD;
      affects inflammatory proteins and lowers TNF production, the use of etanercept may reduce the&#xD;
      need for prednisone in patients with Wegener's granulomatosis, and thus the risk of its side&#xD;
      effects.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients between 10 and 70 years of age with Wegener's granulomatosis who have never taken&#xD;
      prednisone, methotrexate or cyclophosphamide, or have taken these drugs for less than 3 weeks&#xD;
      may be eligible for this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants will have a medical history review and physical examination, including&#xD;
      laboratory studies. If medically indicated, X-rays, consultations and biopsies (surgical&#xD;
      removal of a small tissue sample) of affected organs will also be done. All patients will&#xD;
      begin treatment with prednisone, methotrexate and etanercept. Those who improve on this&#xD;
      regimen will stop prednisone gradually over 3 months. Those who achieve disease remission at&#xD;
      the end of another 3 months will be randomly assigned to either continue taking etanercept&#xD;
      and methotrexate for another 12 months or to stop etanercept and continue only methotrexate&#xD;
      for the next 12 months (after which methotrexate will gradually be stopped). Patients who are&#xD;
      not in remission by the 6-month point will continue taking etanercept until they go into&#xD;
      remission, when they will be assigned to stop or not stop etanercept, as described above.&#xD;
      Patients who do not achieve remission within 12 months of beginning treatment will be taken&#xD;
      off the study. Patients who have a disease relapse while on the study will likely be switched&#xD;
      to treatment with prednisone and either methotrexate or cyclophosphamide. Patients randomized&#xD;
      to stop etanercept and who have a relapse within a year of stopping the drug may be offered&#xD;
      re-treatment on this protocol, but with continuing etanercept for a full year after&#xD;
      remission.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will be evaluated in the outpatient clinic every 2 to 4 weeks for the first 4 months&#xD;
      and every 1 to 3 months after that. Patients whose disease is in remission and who stop all&#xD;
      medications will be followed every 3 to 6 months for 2 years. Follow-up evaluations include a&#xD;
      physical examination, blood draws and, if medically indicated, X-rays. The total study&#xD;
      duration is 60 to 70 months.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to assess the safety, pharmacokinetics, and immunologic effects&#xD;
      of a recombinant fusion protein that consists of the soluble tumor necrosis factor receptor&#xD;
      linked to the Fc portion of human IgG1 (TNFR:Fc) in patients with Wegener's granulomatosis. A&#xD;
      secondary objective is to determine if TNFR:Fc demonstrates anti-inflammatory activity in the&#xD;
      treatment of Wegener's granulomatosis. Specifically, we will seek to examine whether TNFR:Fc&#xD;
      is able to reduce the need for glucocorticoid treatment and lower relapse rates. Patients&#xD;
      will be eligible to participate in this protocol when there is evidence that the disease is&#xD;
      active but is not immediately life-threatening. In this study, patients will receive TNFR:Fc&#xD;
      (25mg subcutaneously twice weekly) together with methotrexate and prednisone. In all patients&#xD;
      the prednisone will be tapered over a 3 month schedule. At the end of 6 months, patients in&#xD;
      remission will be randomized to either continue TNFR:Fc for another 12 months or stop. All&#xD;
      patients will continue methotrexate for 1 year after they enter remission after which time it&#xD;
      will be tapered and discontinued.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>60</enrollment>
  <condition>Vasculitis</condition>
  <condition>Wegener's Granulomatosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etanercept</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Documentation of Wegener's granulomatosis based on clinical characteristics and&#xD;
        histopathologic and/or angiographic evidence of vasculitis. In the absence of&#xD;
        histopathologic and/or angiographic evidence of vasculitis, patients who meet one of the&#xD;
        following criteria and in whom infectious and autoimmune diseases that may mimic Wegener's&#xD;
        granulomatosis or a related systemic vasculitides have been excluded will also be eligible:&#xD;
        a) a positive assay for anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic autoantibodies (C- or P-ANCA) and the&#xD;
        presence of glomerulonephritis defined by red blood cell casts and proteinuria or renal&#xD;
        biopsy showing necrotizing glomerulonephritis in the absence of immune deposits; b) a&#xD;
        positive assay for anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic autoantibodies (C- or P-ANCA) and the&#xD;
        presence of granulomatous inflammation on biopsy plus abnormal chest radiograph (defined as&#xD;
        the presence of nodules, fixed infiltrates, or cavities) plus nasal/oral inflammation on&#xD;
        clinical examination.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects must be between the ages of 10 - 70 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subject must have evidence of active major organ disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who have never been previously seen at the NIH will be eligible if the above&#xD;
        conditions are met and they either: are not receiving treatment; have been receiving&#xD;
        prednisone at induction doses and MTX for less than 3 weeks; have been receiving prednisone&#xD;
        at induction doses and CYC for less than 3 weeks but did not have severe disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with evidence of bacterial sepsis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with evidence of other active systemic infection which in the judgment of the&#xD;
        investigator, is of greater danger to the patient than the underlying vasculitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnant or subjects who are nursing infants.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Fertile women must have a negative pregnancy test within one week prior to study entry and&#xD;
        all participants must be using effective means of birth control.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with one or more of the following: serum creatinine greater than 2.5 mg/dl or&#xD;
        creatinine clearance less than 35 ml/min; pulmonary disease resulting in a pO(2) less than&#xD;
        70 mmHg, or FVC, FEV(1) or DLCO less than 70% of predicted; any Wegener's&#xD;
        granulomatosis-related disease manifestation that, in the judgment of the investigators, is&#xD;
        immediately life-threatening.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Hemocytopenia: platelet count less than 80,000/mm(3), leukocyte count less than&#xD;
        3,000/mm(3), hematocrit less than 20% (in the absence of gastrointestinal bleeding or&#xD;
        hemolytic anemia).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Liver function test abnormalities greater than three times upper limits of normal (either&#xD;
        serum GOT, GPT, alkaline phosphatase, and/or bilirubin).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Processes associated with an increased risk of MTX toxicity: acute or chronic liver&#xD;
        disease, past history of alcohol abuse (greater than 14 oz. of 100 proof liquor or&#xD;
        equivalent per week), ongoing alcohol use of any volume that cannot be discontinued upon&#xD;
        entry into the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Serological evidence of infection with human immunodeficiency virus, hepatitis C, or a&#xD;
        positive hepatitis B surface antigen. A serological determination will be performed within&#xD;
        two weeks of beginning study participation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Treatment with any investigational drug within 30 days.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Known allergy to TNFR:Fc.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Individuals with a history of psychiatric illness that in the opinion of the principal&#xD;
        investigator (PI) would preclude entrance into the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of multiple sclerosis or other demyelinating disease.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fauci AS, Wolff SM. Wegener's granulomatosis: studies in eighteen patients and a review of the literature. Medicine (Baltimore). 1973 Nov;52(6):535-61. doi: 10.1097/00005792-197311000-00002. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>4748591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fauci AS, Haynes BF, Katz P, Wolff SM. Wegener's granulomatosis: prospective clinical and therapeutic experience with 85 patients for 21 years. Ann Intern Med. 1983 Jan;98(1):76-85. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-98-1-76.</citation>
    <PMID>6336643</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoffman GS, Kerr GS, Leavitt RY, Hallahan CW, Lebovics RS, Travis WD, Rottem M, Fauci AS. Wegener granulomatosis: an analysis of 158 patients. Ann Intern Med. 1992 Mar 15;116(6):488-98. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-116-6-488.</citation>
    <PMID>1739240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2005</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Vasculitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Prednisone-sparing</keyword>
  <keyword>Methotrexate</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumor Necrosis Factor</keyword>
  <keyword>Remission</keyword>
  <keyword>Wegener's Granulomatosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Granulomatosis with Polyangiitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vasculitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etanercept</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

