<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001865</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990135</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-EI-0135</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001865</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HAT in Eye Complications of Behcet's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Investigate the Safety and Efficacy of HAT to Treat the Ocular Complications Related to Behcet's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the safety and effectiveness of Zenapax in controlling recurrent eye&#xD;
      inflammations associated with Behcet's disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Behcet's disease is usually treated with corticosteroids to suppress inflammation. Other&#xD;
      medicines such as methotrexate, cyclophosphamide, or azathioprine may also be used. These&#xD;
      drugs all can have serious side effects, including liver or kidney damage. Zenapax is a&#xD;
      monoclonal antibody that binds to certain proteins (receptors) on white blood cells,&#xD;
      preventing them from interacting with a chemical called interleukin-2. Blocking this&#xD;
      interaction prevents inflammation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will include 20 patients who had unacceptable side effects from other medicines&#xD;
      used to treat their disease; did not benefit from standard treatment; and refused standard&#xD;
      treatment because of possible side effects of the medicines.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All patients in the study will continue to take their current medicines at the start of the&#xD;
      study. In addition, one group of patients will receive Zenapax and a second group will&#xD;
      receive a placebo. The drug or placebo will be infused into the vein at the start of the&#xD;
      study and every two weeks for the next six weeks, and then every four weeks for the rest of&#xD;
      the study period (24 months). Each infusion lasts about 15 minutes. Patients will have eye&#xD;
      examinations at the time of every treatment, and medicines will be added if needed to control&#xD;
      eye disease. Drugs will be tapered after six months in patients whose eye disease is quiet,&#xD;
      and readjusted as necessary. Neither the doctors nor the patients will know who is receiving&#xD;
      placebo and who is receiving Zenapax until the study ends.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will be given a physical examination, medical history, eye examination, fluorescein&#xD;
      angiography (special photographs of the retina to evaluate the blood vessels in the eye), and&#xD;
      blood tests.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Zenapax was previously studied in 10 patients with uveitis with positive results. The&#xD;
      patients were able to reduce the other medicines they were taking with minimal side effects.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The development of an ideal therapy to immunosuppress patients with Behcet's disease, a cause&#xD;
      of endogenous uveitis and a major cause of acquired blindness in adults, is an important&#xD;
      research goal. Corticosteroids remain the mainstay of therapy for intraocular inflammation;&#xD;
      however, many patients are intolerant or resistant to corticosteroid therapy. Although the&#xD;
      etiology of Behcet's disease is unknown, evidence suggests that an interleukin-2 receptor&#xD;
      bearing auto-aggressive cells may play an important role in this disorder. Zenapax, a&#xD;
      humanized anti-TAC (T-cell activated antigen) monoclonal antibody (HAT), has been utilized in&#xD;
      Protocol # 96-EI-0096, a pilot Phase I/II study, to evaluate Zenapax administration in the&#xD;
      treatment of patients with endogenous sight-threatening uveitis. Long-term results&#xD;
      demonstrate a positive therapeutic trend in this trial. We propose a randomized masked pilot&#xD;
      trial of Zenapax versus placebo. Twenty patients who are 18 years of age or older with&#xD;
      Behcet's disease will be randomly assigned to receive either Zenapax or placebo in addition&#xD;
      to their standard immunosuppressive therapy. After six months of quiescent disease, patients&#xD;
      will be eligible to taper their standard immunosuppressive therapy. The primary purpose of&#xD;
      the study is to investigate the safety and efficacy of Zenapax in controlling the recurrent,&#xD;
      explosive nature of ocular manifestations in patients with Behcet's disease. Because this&#xD;
      study is a Phase I/II study examining both efficacy and safety, primary outcomes for each are&#xD;
      defined. The primary safety endpoint is one of the following: a) development of a life&#xD;
      threatening complication, namely an exacerbation of systemic or neurological disease, or b)&#xD;
      the development of a severe opportunistic infection. The primary efficacy outcomes of this&#xD;
      study are based on the number of ocular attacks experienced and the amount of&#xD;
      immunosuppressive medications over the 2 year study period, including the ability to taper&#xD;
      the standard immunosuppressive therapy. Secondary efficacy outcomes include the level of&#xD;
      inflammation as measured by vitreous haze and anterior chamber cells and flare, the presence&#xD;
      or absence of cystoid macular edema, the change from baseline in visual acuity, and quality&#xD;
      of life issues as measured through questionnaires.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>26</enrollment>
  <condition>Behcet's Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Retinal Disease</condition>
  <condition>Uveitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Daclizumab</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must be 18 years of age or older for the primary randomized cohort.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Up to six additional patients under 18 but more than 6 years of age may enroll in a&#xD;
        separate stratum.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients has ocular complications of Behcet's disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients is currently taking a minimum of 15 mg of prednisone, or cyclosporine, or&#xD;
        anti-metabolites, or any combination of these for the treatment of their intraocular&#xD;
        inflammatory disease and retinal vasculitis for at least the past 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients must have had at least two documented ocular attacks due to their Behcet's disease&#xD;
        involving the posterior segment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients has normal renal or liver function or evidence of only mild abnormalities as&#xD;
        defined by the WHO criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients has a neutrophil count above 750.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients agrees to use acceptable birth control methods throughout the course of the study&#xD;
        and for 6 months after completion of treatment if assigned to Zenapax. If patient is&#xD;
        assigned to placebo and has been unmasked, the patient need not practice birth control.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients is able to understand and sign a consent form before entering into the study.&#xD;
        Minor patients will be required to sign an assent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients has received previous treatment with an IL-2 directed monoclonal antibody or any&#xD;
        other investigational agent that would interfere with the ability to evaluate the safety,&#xD;
        efficacy, or pharmacokinetics of Zenapax.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients has significant active infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients has a history of cancer (other than non-melanoma skin cancer) within the past 5&#xD;
        years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patient is pregnant or lactating.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients with significant symptomatic neurological disease which complicates evaluation of&#xD;
        neurological sequelae of Behcet's disease. This would include multiple sclerosis, stroke,&#xD;
        and other neurodegenerative disease are not eligible. Neuro-Behcet's disease would be&#xD;
        permitted.&#xD;
&#xD;
        In the opinion of the treating physicians the ocular disease is end-stage, and there would&#xD;
        be no reasonable hope for an improvement in visual acuity.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patient has used Latanoprost within two weeks prior to enrollment, or has a current or&#xD;
        likely need for Latanaprost during the course of the study.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Eye Institute (NEI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reed MH, Shapiro ME, Strom TB, Milford EL, Carpenter CB, Weinberg DS, Reimann KA, Letvin NL, Waldmann TA, Kirkman RL. Prolongation of primate renal allograft survival by anti-Tac, an anti-human IL-2 receptor monoclonal antibody. Transplantation. 1989 Jan;47(1):55-9. doi: 10.1097/00007890-198901000-00013.</citation>
    <PMID>2643232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown PS Jr, Parenteau GL, Dirbas FM, Garsia RJ, Goldman CK, Bukowski MA, Junghans RP, Queen C, Hakimi J, Benjamin WR, et al. Anti-Tac-H, a humanized antibody to the interleukin 2 receptor, prolongs primate cardiac allograft survival. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1991 Apr 1;88(7):2663-7. doi: 10.1073/pnas.88.7.2663.</citation>
    <PMID>2011577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herve P, Wijdenes J, Bergerat JP, Bordigoni P, Milpied N, Cahn JY, Clement C, Beliard R, Morel-Fourrier B, Racadot E, et al. Treatment of corticosteroid resistant acute graft-versus-host disease by in vivo administration of anti-interleukin-2 receptor monoclonal antibody (B-B10). Blood. 1990 Feb 15;75(4):1017-23.</citation>
    <PMID>2136244</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2004</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Behcet's</keyword>
  <keyword>Monoclonal Antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>Uveitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin 2</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinal Vasculitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyopyon</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin 2 Receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>Bechet's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Ocular Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Behcet Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Daclizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

