<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001912</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990149</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-I-0149</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001912</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brain Tissue Swelling and Seizure Activity in Inactive Cysticercosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analysis of the Occurrence of Perilesional Edema and Seizures in Patients With Inactive Cysticercosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine what causes seizures in patients with cysticercosis (pork tapeworm&#xD;
      infection). A better understanding of this could lead to improved methods of controlling or&#xD;
      preventing seizures.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In humans, the pork tapeworm (Taenia solium) lives in the small intestine. The parasite's&#xD;
      microscopic eggs travel around the body-including to the brain-where they develop into cysts.&#xD;
      Usually, the cysts don't cause symptoms until they die. Then, they provoke an inflammatory&#xD;
      reaction that irritates the brain, causing seizures and other symptoms. The inflammation&#xD;
      eventually goes away, but the dead cysts remain. Calcium deposits often form where the cysts&#xD;
      are. Some of the calcified cysts develop swelling around them that seem to be associated with&#xD;
      the development of seizures.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will explore how and why these dead, calcified cysts continue to cause seizures.&#xD;
      In so doing, it will try to determine: 1) the best diagnostic imaging method for detecting&#xD;
      swelling around the cysts; 2) how often swelling occurs; and 3) what makes some cysts prone&#xD;
      to swelling and related seizure activity, while others are not.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with cysticercosis who have had seizures or who have known or possible swelling&#xD;
      around calcified cysts will be studied with various tests, including magnetic resonance&#xD;
      imaging (MRI), computed tomography (CT) scans, electroencephalography (EEG), blood tests, and&#xD;
      possibly lumbar puncture. Patients will be studied for two cycles of seizures (during active&#xD;
      and quiet periods) or a maximum 4 years.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Seizures are the most common clinical manifestation of cerebral cysticercosis and occur in&#xD;
      the presence of viable, dying, and calcified or non-calcified dead cysts. How calcified cysts&#xD;
      provoke seizures is not known but recent observations demonstrated edema around some&#xD;
      calcified lesions at the time of seizure activity and disappearance during periods when&#xD;
      seizures were not occurring. Edema associated with foci in idiopathic epilepsy is highly&#xD;
      unusual so that this observation suggests that the mechanism(s) associated with calcified&#xD;
      cysts is unique. Documenting and understanding this phenomenon is important for a number of&#xD;
      reasons. First, although by definition these lesions are inactive, e.g., not living larvae&#xD;
      and do not require anti-parasitic treatment, they are frequently mistaken for active lesions&#xD;
      and patients undergo unnecessary treatment. Second, a likely reason for perilesional edema is&#xD;
      intermittent antigen release and subsequent host immune response resulting in inflammation&#xD;
      and edema. If proved, then the treatment for this would not only involve suppression of&#xD;
      seizure activity with anti-seizure medication but also the use of anti-inflammatory&#xD;
      medications such as corticosteroids. The present protocol will systematically assess the&#xD;
      presence of edema associated with calcified lesions at the time of seizure activity and&#xD;
      attempt to determine why some calcified lesions in the same patient are foci of seizures&#xD;
      while others are clinically silent. There are three related but separate questions. 1) What&#xD;
      is the most sensitive MRI technique that can detect edema around calcified or inactive&#xD;
      lesions? It is essential to determine the most sensitive methods initially because the use of&#xD;
      insensitive techniques will lead to inaccurate assessments of which lesions are prone to lead&#xD;
      to seizure activity and how many patients are affected. 2) How common is perilesional edema&#xD;
      around calcified or inactive lesions associated with seizure activity? 3) What factors&#xD;
      determine which lesions are prone to cause seizure activity? 4) Can perilesional edema be&#xD;
      effectively treated or prevented? 5) Can perilesional edema be treated? We have reported from&#xD;
      long term longitudinal studies in a handful of patients that only some of many lesions seem&#xD;
      to be associated with seizure activity and edema.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 10, 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>April 4, 2012</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Cysticercosis</condition>
  <condition>Cysts</condition>
  <condition>Seizures</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
             18 years of age or older. If children are evaluated they can be seen under the general&#xD;
             protocol and they may be entered into the present protocol under an exception.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Likely diagnosis of inactive cysticercosis and present or past seizure activity. Requires&#xD;
        &quot;a&quot; and &quot;b&quot; plus any one of the remaining criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. History of seizures or present seizure activity;&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Previously treated or has inactive disease and declines treatment;&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Single calcified lesions and positive serology;&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Multiple calcified lesions;&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Multiple small enhancing nodular lesions;&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. History of cystic lesions responding to specific chemotherapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        If female, not pregnant and using effective birth control methods.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Less than 18 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Pregnant or unwilling to use effective birth control measures.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Refuse blood tests.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Unwilling or unable to undergo testing according to the schedule.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Unable to undergo MRI or CT examinations.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who require anesthesia to undergo imaging studies.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Henry Masur, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lima</city>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Peru</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>White AC Jr. Neurocysticercosis: a major cause of neurological disease worldwide. Clin Infect Dis. 1997 Feb;24(2):101-13; quiz 114-5. doi: 10.1093/clinids/24.2.101. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>9114131</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rajshekhar V, Chacko G, Haran RP, Chandy MJ, Chandi SM. Clinicoradiological and pathological correlations in patients with solitary cysticercus granuloma and epilepsy: focus on presence of the parasite and oedema formation. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 1995 Sep;59(3):284-6. doi: 10.1136/jnnp.59.3.284.</citation>
    <PMID>7673957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nash TE, Neva FA. Recent advances in the diagnosis and treatment of cerebral cysticercosis. N Engl J Med. 1984 Dec 6;311(23):1492-6. doi: 10.1056/NEJM198412063112307. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>6390196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 4, 2012</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Cysticercosis</keyword>
  <keyword>T. Solium</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Seizures</keyword>
  <keyword>Calcified Cysts</keyword>
  <keyword>Taenia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cysticercosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Taeniasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurocysticercosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Seizures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

