<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001543</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>960048</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>96-M-0048</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001543</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dynamics of Leptin and Endocrine Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dynamics of Leptin and Endocrine Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a study investigating the hormones and substances important to the stress response.&#xD;
      The hormone that is most directly responsible for stress response is called&#xD;
      corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH). CRH is produced in the hypothalamus of the brain and&#xD;
      causes the pituitary gland to produce another hormone called ACTH. The hormone ACTH then acts&#xD;
      on the adrenal glands causing them to produce the hormone cortisol.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Unfortunately, CRH levels are unable to be measured in simple blood samples. However,&#xD;
      substances like cortisol and leptin can provide information as to the activity of the&#xD;
      hypothalamus.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The hormone leptin is associated with the regulation of body weight and the normal&#xD;
      maintenance of bodily functions (homeostasis). It is found in fat cell (adipocyes) and&#xD;
      communicates the nutritional status of the body to the brain (central nervous system).&#xD;
      Research using animals has shown that defects in the communication between leptin and the&#xD;
      brain causes obesity (the state of being overweight). It has also been noted that obese&#xD;
      humans tend to have high levels of leptin.&#xD;
&#xD;
      By studying patients with abnormal genes responsible for leptin production, researchers have&#xD;
      found that a least one leptin gene must be intact for the normal secretion of hormones to&#xD;
      proceed. These results show that the hormone leptin is produced outside of the brain in fat&#xD;
      cells and acts directly on the function of the hypothalamus within the brain. Researchers&#xD;
      believe that leptin plays a key role in the normal release of hormones from the HPA axis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Researchers intend on continuing to study the role of leptin in fat distribution, and the&#xD;
      activity of the HPA axis in normal volunteers. In addition, this study will focus on the role&#xD;
      of leptin in depression, because depression is characterized by changes in food intake, body&#xD;
      weight, and neuroendocrine function. Data gathered from this study will provide a better&#xD;
      understanding of the causes and medical consequences of major depression.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our group has tested the hypothesis that the molecules involved in the neurobiology of the&#xD;
      stress response are key elements in the pathophysiology, treatment, and medical consequences&#xD;
      of major depressive disorder. Leptin is implicated in the regulation of adipose tissue, body&#xD;
      weight and homeostasis. In the first three years of this protocol we accomplished the&#xD;
      following: (1) discovered leptin pulsatility; (2) showed that is secreted in a highly&#xD;
      organized manner in men and women; (3) showed for the first time in humans an inverse&#xD;
      relation between rapid fluctuations in plasma leptin concentrations in healthy volunteers and&#xD;
      those of adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) and cortisol; (4) demonstrated a complex relation&#xD;
      between the minute-to-minute dynamics of leptin and those of luteinizing hormone and&#xD;
      estradiol; (5) showed a striking correlation between the 24-h dynamics of leptin and those of&#xD;
      TSH and GH; (6) demonstrated highly significant correlation between hourly fluctuations of&#xD;
      leptin levels and those of psychometric variables such as sadness, social withdrawal, and&#xD;
      carbohydrate craving, and (7) showed that women produce twice as much leptin per secretory&#xD;
      event than men. By studying patients with a leptin gene mutation we showed that at least one&#xD;
      intact copy of the leptin gene is required for the regulation of TSH function and GH&#xD;
      architecture in humans. These results indicate that leptin, a peripherally secreted molecule,&#xD;
      appears to modulate the secretion of hypothalamic hormones. We have therefore proposed that&#xD;
      hypothalamic neuroendocrine transduction, a key function of the CNS, may be regulated by&#xD;
      leptin, a peripheral pulsatile signal of nutritional status. We would like to continue and&#xD;
      expand our studies on the interactions of leptin, fat distribution, and the pituitary-adrenal&#xD;
      axis in normal volunteers and also in patients with depression, because depression is&#xD;
      characterized by alterations in food intake, body weight, and neuroendocrine function. Leptin&#xD;
      profoundly affects the regulation of these three parameters. Leptin also increases insulin&#xD;
      resistance, being therefore a risk factor for coronary artery disease, which is more&#xD;
      prevalent and associated with higher mortality in depressed patients than in the general&#xD;
      population. The data to be generated by this study will provide a better understanding of&#xD;
      pathophysiology and medical consequences of major depression.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 1996</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 2002</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>230</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Involutional Depression</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Depressed patients must have a history of past major depression of at least four months&#xD;
        duration, or a history of two or more briefer episodes. Must be overweight.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Must not need a hospital admission as part of their treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Overweight normal volunteers.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No subjects on chronic medication which cannot be washed out for one month.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No subjects with any serious medical illness.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No women who are pregnant, trying to become pregnant, or sexually active and not using&#xD;
        effective contraception.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No patients with HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
        No subjects who cannot discontinue use of alcohol/tobacco.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Behan DP, Linton EA, Lowry PJ. Isolation of the human plasma corticotrophin-releasing factor-binding protein. J Endocrinol. 1989 Jul;122(1):23-31. doi: 10.1677/joe.0.1220023.</citation>
    <PMID>2549150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campbell EA, Linton EA, Wolfe CD, Scraggs PR, Jones MT, Lowry PJ. Plasma corticotropin-releasing hormone concentrations during pregnancy and parturition. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1987 May;64(5):1054-9. doi: 10.1210/jcem-64-5-1054.</citation>
    <PMID>3494036</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gold PW, Goodwin FK, Chrousos GP. Clinical and biochemical manifestations of depression. Relation to the neurobiology of stress (1). N Engl J Med. 1988 Aug 11;319(6):348-53. doi: 10.1056/NEJM198808113190606. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>3292920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2002</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Major Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolic Clearance Rate</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulsatility</keyword>
  <keyword>Adrenocorticotropic Hormone</keyword>
  <keyword>Cortisol</keyword>
  <keyword>Corticotropin Releasing Hormone Binding Protein</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Half-Life</keyword>
  <keyword>Bioavailability</keyword>
  <keyword>Cushing's Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

