<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001934</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990169</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-N-0169</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001934</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zenapax to Treat Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of the Humanized Monoclonal Antibody Against the Interleukin-2 Receptor Alpha Subunit (IL-2R-Alpha; Zenapax(Registered Trademark)) on Inflammatory Activity in the CNS in MS in a Baseline-to-Treatment, Cross-Over, MRI-Controlled Single Center Phase I/II Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the safety and effectiveness of Zenapax (a laboratory-manufactured&#xD;
      antibody) in treating multiple sclerosis. Multiple sclerosis may be caused by an abnormal&#xD;
      immune response in which white blood cells called T lymphocytes attack the myelin sheath that&#xD;
      covers nerves and parts of the spinal cord. Zenapax binds to protein receptors on&#xD;
      lymphocytes, keeping them from interacting with interleukin-2, a substance necessary for&#xD;
      their growth.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients with multiple sclerosis who have had at least one relapse within 18 months of the&#xD;
      start of the study and in whom interferon-beta treatment has not been successful may be&#xD;
      considered for this study. There are two study phases: baseline and treatment. During the&#xD;
      baseline phase, patients will have three magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans over 2 months&#xD;
      to evaluate their disease activity. During treatment, patients will receive seven intravenous&#xD;
      (I.V.) infusions of Zenapax in the clinic. The first two infusions will be given 2 weeks&#xD;
      apart; the next five will be given once a month.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will have MRI scans before each infusion. The MRIs will be done using the standard&#xD;
      procedure and again using a contrast agent, gadolinium, injected into a vein. Gadolinium&#xD;
      helps identify new multiple sclerosis lesions in the brain. Blood and urine samples will be&#xD;
      taken during each clinic visit. In addition, patients will have skin tests, similar to a&#xD;
      tuberculin test, to evaluate immune status, and will be asked to undergo two lumbar punctures&#xD;
      (spinal tap; these will be optional)-one before the treatment phase begins, and another when&#xD;
      treatment is completed. Lymphocytes will also be collected from patients before, during and&#xD;
      after treatment. The lymphocytes are obtained by a procedure called apheresis: about a pint&#xD;
      of whole blood is drawn through a needle in the arm, the lymphocytes are separated out and&#xD;
      removed by a machine, and the rest of the blood is returned through a needle in the other&#xD;
      arm. These studies will hopefully allow conclusions about the safety of Zenapax in MS, but&#xD;
      also address its effectiveness with respect to modifying the inflammatory activity in the&#xD;
      brain of MS patients and inhibit autoimmune T lymphocytes that are involved in the disease&#xD;
      process.&#xD;
&#xD;
      ...&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Multiple sclerosis (MS) is an inflammatory and demyelinating disease of the central nervous&#xD;
      system (CNS) that preferentially affects young adults. While its etiology is unknown, current&#xD;
      concepts assume that CD4+ helper T cells with specificity for components of the myelin sheath&#xD;
      initiate the pathogenetic process. The activation and expansion of such autoreactive T cells&#xD;
      involves the secretion of autocrine growth factors, particularly interleukin-2 (IL-2), and&#xD;
      the concomitant expression of its receptor, IL-2R, on the surface of T cells. Since only&#xD;
      activated T lymphocytes can migrate through the blood brain barrier into the CNS and induce&#xD;
      the inflammatory process, blocking the IL-2R should have an impact on disease activity in MS.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In this trial , a humanized antibody against the IL-2Ra subunit (Zenapax(Registered&#xD;
      Trademark)) will be used to inhibit T cell activation in MS patients who have failed&#xD;
      conventional therapy by interferon-b. We will focus on the latter group of patients, since a&#xD;
      substantial number of patients on conventional therapy respond only partially or completely&#xD;
      fail treatment after longer periods of time. Up to 10 patients fulfilling these criteria will&#xD;
      be enrolled in this baseline-to-treatment, cross-over, MRI-controlled single-center phase&#xD;
      I/II trial to assess the safety of Zenapax(Registered Trademark) treatment and, at the same&#xD;
      time, examine the clinical course and particularly the inflammatory activity in the CNS by&#xD;
      monthly magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). Furthermore, immunological studies will be&#xD;
      performed in parallel to the trial in order to a) identify the impact of Zenapax(Registered&#xD;
      Trademark) treatment on immune parameters that should be affected by the blocking of the&#xD;
      IL-2R, and b) to improve our understanding of the relevance of activated autoreactive T&#xD;
      lymphocytes in MS.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in contrast-enhancing lesions on brain MRI.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zenapax</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA&#xD;
&#xD;
        Between the ages of 18 and 65 years, inclusive.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Subjects with relapsing-remitting or secondary progressive Multiple Sclerosis who have had&#xD;
        more than 1 relapse within 18 months preceding study enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EDSS score between 1 - 6.5, inclusive.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Give written informed consent prior to any testing under this protocol, including&#xD;
        screening/pre-treatment tests and evaluations that are not considered part of the subject's&#xD;
        routine care.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who have failed standard IFN-beta therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        To be eligible to proceed to the treatment phase of the study, subjects must have at least&#xD;
        2 Gd-enhancing lesions or greater in the 3 pre-treatment MRI scans (an average of at least&#xD;
        0.67 Gd-enhancing lesions per scan).&#xD;
&#xD;
        In patients with high inflammatory activity and high relapse rates it has been our&#xD;
        experience that the requirement of steroid therapy for the treatment of relapses may&#xD;
        prolong the baseline phase. In patients with high disease activity who require steroid&#xD;
        therapy and quickly afterwards demonstrate disease activity again, the investigator retains&#xD;
        the option to enroll patients with less than the stipulated baseline months in order to&#xD;
        initiate daclizumab therapy as quickly as possible. Since treatment escalation would&#xD;
        otherwise require therapy with mitoxantrone or cyclophosphamide, which both have&#xD;
        substantial toxicity, this step is in the best interest of the patient.&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Diagnosis of primary progressive MS, defined as gradual progression of disability from the&#xD;
        onset without relapses.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Abnormal screening/pre-treatment blood tests exceeding any of the limits defined below:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Alanine transaminase (ALT) or aspartate transaminase (AST) greater than two times the upper&#xD;
        limit of normal;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Total white blood cell count less than 3,000/mm(3);&#xD;
&#xD;
        CD4+ count less than 320/mm(3);&#xD;
&#xD;
        Platelet count less than 80,000/mm(3);&#xD;
&#xD;
        Creatinine greater than 2.0 mg/dL.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Concurrent, clinically significant (as determined by the investigator) cardiac,&#xD;
        immunologic, pulmonary, neurologic, renal, and/or other major disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Any contraindication to monoclonal antibody therapies.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients who are HIV+ since the effects of anti-Tac are not defined in these patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        If prior treatment was received, the subject must have been off treatment for the required&#xD;
        period prior to enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Prior treatment with any other investigational drug or procedure for MS.&#xD;
&#xD;
        History of alcohol or drug abuse within the 5 years prior to enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Male and female subjects not practicing adequate contraception.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Female subjects who are not post-menopausal or surgically sterile must be using an&#xD;
        acceptable method of contraception. Acceptability of various methods of contraception will&#xD;
        be at the discretion of the investigator. Written documentation that the subject is&#xD;
        post-menopausal or surgically sterile must be available prior to study start.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Unwillingness or inability to comply with the requirements of this protocol including the&#xD;
        presence of any condition (physical, mental, or social) that is likely to affect the&#xD;
        subject's returning for follow-up visits on schedule.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Previous participation in this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Breastfeeding patients.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/detail/B_1999-N-0169.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin R, McFarland HF, McFarlin DE. Immunological aspects of demyelinating diseases. Annu Rev Immunol. 1992;10:153-87. doi: 10.1146/annurev.iy.10.040192.001101.</citation>
    <PMID>1375472</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wucherpfennig KW, Strominger JL. Molecular mimicry in T cell-mediated autoimmunity: viral peptides activate human T cell clones specific for myelin basic protein. Cell. 1995 Mar 10;80(5):695-705. doi: 10.1016/0092-8674(95)90348-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7534214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gran B, Hemmer B, Vergelli M, McFarland HF, Martin R. Molecular mimicry and multiple sclerosis: degenerate T-cell recognition and the induction of autoimmunity. Ann Neurol. 1999 May;45(5):559-67. doi: 10.1002/1531-8249(199905)45:53.0.co;2-q.</citation>
    <PMID>10319877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2011</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 4, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 4, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Bibiana Bielekova, M.D./National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke</name_title>
    <organization>National Institutes of Health</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Daclizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

