<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001319</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>920256</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>92-I-0256</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001319</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of HIV-Negative Patients With Low CD4+ T Lymphocyte Counts</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Epidemiology, Clinical Manifestations, Etiologies, and Immunology of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) Negative CD4 T Lymphocyte Deficient Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate HIV-negative patients with unusually low levels of CD4+ T&#xD;
      lymphocytes (a type of white blood cell) to learn more about the clinical symptoms, cause,&#xD;
      immunology, and biology of this problem. CD4+ T lymphocytes play an important role in immune&#xD;
      function, and low counts may leave people susceptible to unusual infections. CD4+ T cell&#xD;
      deficiencies are most often associated with HIV infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients 8 years of age and older with CD4+ T cell counts below 300 cells/mm3 who test&#xD;
      negative for HIV infection by standard blood tests may be eligible for this study. Patients'&#xD;
      family members and partners may also be enrolled to investigate the possible role of a&#xD;
      genetic factor or exposure to some agent in this problem.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will be evaluated at the NIH Clinical Center at least once, and generally two or&#xD;
      more times. The evaluations, which may be done on an inpatient or outpatient basis, will&#xD;
      include some or all of the following tests and procedures:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Complete physical examination.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Medical history, including questions about sexual contacts, intravenous drug use,&#xD;
           travel, blood transfusions, previous illnesses, including sexually transmitted diseases,&#xD;
           and health of family members.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Urine test.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Blood tests for routine and research purposes, including tests for HIV, hepatitis,&#xD;
           syphilis and other infections, evaluation of immune function, and culture for viruses in&#xD;
           the HIV family. No more than 1 pint of blood will be drawn every 6 weeks.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Pregnancy test for women of childbearing potential.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Skin tests for tuberculosis and immune function. These tests involve injecting a small&#xD;
           amount of the substance to be tested just under the skin and looking for a raised area 1&#xD;
           to 2 days later.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Apheresis. Whole blood is collected through an arm vein (similar to donating blood), and&#xD;
           circulated through a cell separator machine, where it is spun to separate the&#xD;
           components. The red cells are then returned to the patient either through the same&#xD;
           needle or through a needle in the other arm, and the plasma and white cells are&#xD;
           extracted for study. The procedure, which takes 1 to 2 hours, may be repeated up to 3&#xD;
           times.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Family members will have 60 cc (4 tablespoons) of blood drawn to determine CD4+ T cell&#xD;
      counts.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Low CD4+ T-cells in the absence of known etiology has been called idiopathic CD4+ T&#xD;
      lymphocytopenia, and a case definition was established by the CDC as a CD4 count less than&#xD;
      300 cells/mL on 2 consecutive samples in a patient uninfected by HIV and with no other&#xD;
      disease or treatment that might provide a reasonable alternative explanation for CD4&#xD;
      lymphocytopenia. Early investigations centered on a search for a novel retrovirus, but we and&#xD;
      others have not found evidence of such a retrovirus. The patients that we have seen are&#xD;
      heterogeneous, and it appears likely that there will be multiple etiologies for this&#xD;
      syndrome. We are currently continuing to follow subjects long term and to see new subjects in&#xD;
      order to continue to characterize the clinical aspects of patients who meet the case&#xD;
      definition; to determine the natural history of ICL, and to provide samples to researchers&#xD;
      who are interested in investigations into the pathogenesis of ICL.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1992</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 2003</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>100</enrollment>
  <condition>CD4 Lymphocytopenia</condition>
  <condition>Idiopathic CD4 Positive T Lymphocytopenia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA&#xD;
&#xD;
        Adults greater than or equal to 18 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
        CD4 count less than 300 cells/mmL on 2 consecutive samples.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Uninfected by HIV as determined by ELISA with confirmatory Western Blot&#xD;
&#xD;
        Absence of disease or treatment that might provide a reasonable alternative explanation for&#xD;
        the CD4 cell count or might confound the evaluation. Examples of such diseases would be any&#xD;
        acute, severe medical illness that had not resolved when CD4 cell counts were obtained;&#xD;
        active tuberculosis; leukemia or lymphoma; or previously characterized immunodeficiency&#xD;
        disorder. Treatment that that might provide a reasonable alternative explanation includes&#xD;
        chemotherapy over a field that could affect bone marrow or supraphysiologic glucocorticoid&#xD;
        therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Capable of providing informed consent.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roger PM, Bernard-Pomier G, Counillon E, Breittmayer JP, Bernard A, Dellamonica P. Overexpression of Fas/CD95 and Fas-induced apoptosis in a patient with idiopathic CD4+ T lymphocytopenia. Clin Infect Dis. 1999 May;28(5):1012-6. doi: 10.1086/514739.</citation>
    <PMID>10452627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cunningham-Rundles C, Murray HW, Smith JP. Treatment of idiopathic CD4 T lymphocytopenia with IL-2. Clin Exp Immunol. 1999 May;116(2):322-5. doi: 10.1046/j.1365-2249.1999.00886.x.</citation>
    <PMID>10337025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aldrich J, Gross R, Adler M, King K, MacGregor RR, Gluckman SJ. The effect of acute severe illness on CD4+ lymphocyte counts in nonimmunocompromised patients. Arch Intern Med. 2000 Mar 13;160(5):715-6. doi: 10.1001/archinte.160.5.715. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>10724063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2003</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>HIV Negative</keyword>
  <keyword>CD4 Deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Retrovirus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>T-Lymphocytopenia, Idiopathic CD4-Positive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

