<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005334</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4189</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL044436</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005334</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Personality and Context on Recovery From Coronary Artery Bypass</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To study the personality and environmental factors that may determine the short-term and&#xD;
      long-term sequelae of coronary artery bypass surgery (CABS).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Coronary artery bypass surgery, or CABS, is one of the most common surgical procedures for&#xD;
      treating patients with coronary artery disease (CAD). A significant number of patients have&#xD;
      accelerated atherosclerosis in the postsurgical period and require second and third&#xD;
      operations. Moreover, relative to standard medical care, CABS does little to prolong life.&#xD;
      The major benefit of the procedure is improving life quality. Thus, to enhance this major&#xD;
      benefit of CABS, it is important to understand the factors, psychosocial as well as&#xD;
      biological, that might enhance quality of life after CABS. The few available studies on the&#xD;
      psychosocial aspects of recovery from CABS suggest that person variables evident prior to&#xD;
      surgery are related to postsurgery quality of life. Of special interest here are gender,&#xD;
      optimism, Type A, with its component behavior of hostility, and repressive style. The&#xD;
      significance of these attributes derives from their theoretical and empirical relationships&#xD;
      to the patient's illness representations and correspondent coping responses, and/or their&#xD;
      relationship to risk for coronary heart disease (CHD). In addition to person variables, a&#xD;
      number of environmental variables might also be expected to play a role in recovery.&#xD;
      Variables such as socioeconomic status (SES), major life events, and quantity and quality of&#xD;
      social support systems have all been shown to impact on health and illness. Moreover, from a&#xD;
      slightly different perspective, the patient's illness itself can serve as an environmental&#xD;
      variable impinging on the life of the person providing the primary support. Thus, it is also&#xD;
      important to understand how the patient's illness impacts on the provider of the primary&#xD;
      support.&#xD;
&#xD;
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:&#xD;
&#xD;
      A total of 305 patients between the ages of 25 and 70 scheduled for elective surgery at a&#xD;
      major local hospital were evaluated two weeks prior to surgery on the day prior to surgery,&#xD;
      and one week, six months, and two and a half years postsurgery. Primary support persons were&#xD;
      evaluated three times--at intake, six months postsurgery, and two and a half years&#xD;
      postsurgery. Medical information was obtained that permitted examination of the influences of&#xD;
      psychosocial variables on recovery. Major personality variables under investigation were&#xD;
      optimism, Type A, hostility, gender, repressive style, and to a lesser extent, anxiety, and&#xD;
      neuroticism. Major environmental variables included quality and quantity of social support&#xD;
      and availability of a primary support person. Main outcome variables for patients included&#xD;
      satisfaction with different life domains, depression, return to work, normalization of life&#xD;
      style, and new and recurrent morbidity. Main outcome variables for the support person&#xD;
      included perceptions of burden, depression, and life satisfaction.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in&#xD;
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1991</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1995</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scheier MF, Carver CS, Bridges MW. Distinguishing optimism from neuroticism (and trait anxiety, self-mastery, and self-esteem): a reevaluation of the Life Orientation Test. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1994 Dec;67(6):1063-78. doi: 10.1037//0022-3514.67.6.1063.</citation>
    <PMID>7815302</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carver CS, Scheier MF. Situational coping and coping dispositions in a stressful transaction. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1994 Jan;66(1):184-95. doi: 10.1037//0022-3514.66.1.184.</citation>
    <PMID>8126648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carver CS, Pozo C, Harris SD, Noriega V, Scheier MF, Robinson DS, Ketcham AS, Moffat FL Jr, Clark KC. How coping mediates the effect of optimism on distress: a study of women with early stage breast cancer. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1993 Aug;65(2):375-90. doi: 10.1037//0022-3514.65.2.375.</citation>
    <PMID>8366426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newsom JT, Schulz R. Social support as a mediator in the relation between functional status and quality of life in older adults. Psychol Aging. 1996 Mar;11(1):34-44. doi: 10.1037/0882-7974.11.1.34.</citation>
    <PMID>8726368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scheier MF, Bridges MW. Person variables and health: personality predispositions and acute psychological states as shared determinants for disease. Psychosom Med. 1995 May-Jun;57(3):255-68. doi: 10.1097/00006842-199505000-00007.</citation>
    <PMID>7652126</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scheier MF, Matthews KA, Owens JF, Schulz R, Bridges MW, Magovern GJ, Carver CS. Optimism and rehospitalization after coronary artery bypass graft surgery. Arch Intern Med. 1999 Apr 26;159(8):829-35. doi: 10.1001/archinte.159.8.829.</citation>
    <PMID>10219928</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nieboer AP, Schulz R, Matthews KA, Scheier MF, Ormel J, Lindenberg SM. Spousal caregivers' activity restriction and depression: a model for changes over time. Soc Sci Med. 1998 Nov;47(9):1361-71. doi: 10.1016/s0277-9536(98)00214-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9783879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2000</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 15, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 15, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 16, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

