<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00463112</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>511/8-1-04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00463112</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Diet Plus Sibutramine on Hormonal and Metabolic Features in Overweight and Obese Women With PCOS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Diet Plus Sibutramine on Hormonal and Metabolic Features in Overweight and Obese Women With PCOS: a Randomized, 24-Week Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hippocration General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hippocration General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Studies on the effect of sibutramine, an anti-obesity drug, on hormonal and metabolic&#xD;
      features of women with polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS) are lacking.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The objective of this study is to examine the effect of sibutramine plus hypocaloric diet on&#xD;
      body composition, hormonal and metabolic parameters and insulin resistance in obese patients&#xD;
      with PCOS.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Overweight and obese women with PCOS were placed in a hypocaloric diet plus sibutramine (10&#xD;
      mg/day) for the first month and then on a hypocaloric diet plus sibutramine (10 mg/day) or&#xD;
      hypocaloric diet only for the subsequent 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The main outcome measures are: Body composition, hormonal and metabolic features and insulin&#xD;
      sensitivity (OGTT) at baseline, at 3 and 6 months of treatment.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Polycystic Ovary Syndrome (PCOS) is one of the most common hormonal disorders in women of&#xD;
      reproductive age. As a syndrome it has multiple components, such as reproductive (chronic&#xD;
      anovulation and infertility), metabolic and cardiovascular. Although lean women present PCOS,&#xD;
      obesity is one of the main manifestations of the syndrome. Androgen excess and insulin&#xD;
      resistance underline much of the clinical and metabolic features of the syndrome.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Recent evidence suggests that PCOS patients have a substantial risk for the development of&#xD;
      metabolic and cardiovascular abnormalities similar to those presented in the metabolic&#xD;
      syndrome. Obesity, particularly of the abdominal type, is presented in approximately half of&#xD;
      the women with PCOS, although several studies have shown that percentage can vary from 30% to&#xD;
      75%. Several studies have demonstrated that obesity in women with PCOS enhances the clinical&#xD;
      and metabolic abnormalities of the syndrome, since obese women with PCOS have more profound&#xD;
      insulin resistance or type 2 DM,dyslipidemia and cardiovascular disease's risk, and greater&#xD;
      level of androgens due to low SHBG levels.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A modest weight loss (&lt;5% or even 5-10% of initial body weight) has been shown to improve&#xD;
      ovulation frequency and conception, to reduce miscarriage, hyperlipidemia, hypertension,&#xD;
      hyperglycemia and insulin resistance in women with PCOS. There are only a few studies on the&#xD;
      effect of anti-obesity drug administration in obese and overweight women with PCOS. To the&#xD;
      authors' best knowledge, the effect of sibutramine, a serotonin and noradrenaline reuptake&#xD;
      inhibitor (SNRI) approved as antiobesity drug, has been studied in only one study with obese&#xD;
      women with PCOS. Given this lack of information, the aim of the present study was to&#xD;
      investigate any additional effect of sibutramine combined with a hypocaloric diet on body&#xD;
      composition, hormonal and lipids parameters and insulin resistance in obese women with PCOS.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study's design The study was prospective, open label, randomized, comparative trial. The&#xD;
      study design included 3 periods; a screening period in order to confirm the diagnosis of&#xD;
      PCOS, a lead-in period (4 weeks duration) that all patients were prescribed 10mg/day&#xD;
      sibutramine plus a 600 kcal deficient diet, and a treatment period (for the subsequent 6&#xD;
      months) that subjects were randomized in a 2:1 ratio to the S group (10 mg/day of Sibutramine&#xD;
      plus hypocaloric diet) and the D group (hypocaloric diet only). Diet was based on the&#xD;
      individualized basal metabolic rate as defined by the Harris-Benedict's equation adjusted for&#xD;
      moderate physical activity. Before entering the lead-in period all subjects were prescribed&#xD;
      an energy-restricted diet containing 50% as carbohydrate, 30% as fat (10% saturated), and 20%&#xD;
      as protein. After randomization, subjects were advised not to modify their eating habits&#xD;
      throughout the study period.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The randomization was performed using sealed envelopes prepared in advance of the study by a&#xD;
      research associate not involved in the study. A randomisation table was created using blocks&#xD;
      of 3 numbers with all possible combinations. A random number generator has been used to&#xD;
      create balance between the treatment groups.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Clinical measures Body weight, waist circumference and fasting blood samples for total&#xD;
      testosterone (T), Sex Hormone Binding Globulin (SHBG), dehydroepiandrosterone sulfate&#xD;
      (DHEAS), androstenedione (Δ4Α), 17a-hydroxyprogesterone, follicle stimulating hormone (FSH),&#xD;
      luteinising hormone (LH), thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH), total cholesterol (TC),&#xD;
      triglycerides (TG), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C), high-density lipoprotein&#xD;
      cholesterol (HDL-C), glucose, and insulin were taken at baseline as well as at 3 and 6 months&#xD;
      of treatment. At the same period, an Oral Glucose Tolerance Test (OGGT) with 75-g glucose was&#xD;
      performed.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Blood samples were collected between 08:30 and 09:00 a.m., after an overnight fast, and&#xD;
      during the follicular phase of women's menstrual cycle. Monthly, subjects' body weight was&#xD;
      measured, adverse events, heart rate, blood pressure, and study drug compliance were&#xD;
      determined and a pregnancy urine test was performed. Body weight was always determined at&#xD;
      morning hours with subjects in light clothes.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>weight loss</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FAI, insulin resistance and other metabolic parameters</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>80</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sibutramine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  overweight and obese women with PCOS&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Nonclassical 21-hydroxylase deficiency, hyperprolactinemia, adrenal or ovarian tumor&#xD;
             and Cushing's disease, hypertension, thyroid dysfunction, overt diabetes mellitus and&#xD;
             concomitant treatment such as antihypertensive drugs, SSRI or other SNRI drug, oral&#xD;
             contraceptive pills or any other antiandrogen treatment (cyproterone acetate,&#xD;
             spirolactone, LHRH agonist) and insulin sensitizing agents (metformin, pioglitazone,&#xD;
             roziglitazone) that may interact with insulin sensitivity and lipid profile.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dimos Florakis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Divison of Endocrinology and Human Reproduction, Second Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Medical School, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hippocratio General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>54642</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2003</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 19, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 20, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 19, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 19, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 20, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>weight loss</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperadrogonemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Sibutramine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sibutramine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

