<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00460668</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL14089.075.06</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00460668</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Post-thoracotomy Pulmonary Rehabilitation on Quality of Life</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Single Centre Open Randomized Trial on the Effect of Post-thoracotomy Pulmonary Rehabilitation on Quality of Life</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Isala</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Isala</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effects of an integrated multidisciplinary&#xD;
      rehabilitation program on health related quality of life in the 12 months postoperative&#xD;
      period in patients with an elective thoracotomy and to evaluate the effects of the program on&#xD;
      general quality of life (SF-36), acute/chronic post-thoracotomy pain, impairment (changes in&#xD;
      pulmonary function), disability (exercise capacity) and start to complete recovery (ECOG&#xD;
      score of 0 or 1) 12 months postoperatively in patients with an elective thoracotomy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Morbidity in the post operative phase of thoracotomies is characterised by pain, dyspnea,&#xD;
      shoulder dysfunction and a loss of exercise tolerance may occur. There is literature about&#xD;
      post-thoracotomy painsyndromes and postoperative quality of life has been investigated.&#xD;
      However, data on post-thoracotomy rehabilitation and influence on morbidity and recovery are&#xD;
      not available.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Aim of the study:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Primary: To evaluate the effects of an integrated multidisciplinary rehabilitation program on&#xD;
      health related quality of life in the 12 months postoperative period in patients with an&#xD;
      elective thoracotomy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Secondary: To evaluate the effects of the program on general quality of life (SF-36),&#xD;
      acute/chronic post-thoracotomy pain, impairment (changes in pulmonary function), disability&#xD;
      (exercise capacity) and start to complete recovery (ECOG score of 0 or 1) 12 months&#xD;
      postoperatively in patients with an elective thoracotomy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study design: prospective single-centre, open randomised trial. Eighty-eight elective&#xD;
      thoracotomy patients with an age between the 18 and 80 years will be recruited during two&#xD;
      years. The follow up for each patient will be one year. The exclusion criteria are chronic&#xD;
      pain involvement, a previous thoracotomy, comorbidity limiting rehabilitation, psychiatric&#xD;
      illness and non- compliance.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients will be asked for participation before thoracotomy by informed consent and will be&#xD;
      randomised post-thoracotomy, before discharge into a rehabilitation or 'regular care' group.&#xD;
      Randomisation will take place for rehabilitation or regular care by a minimisation program&#xD;
      with special attendance to age (&lt; 70 or ≥ 70 years), gender, the result of the 6 minute walk&#xD;
      test (&lt; 100 m or ≥ 100 m), the FEV (FEV1&lt; 40% or ≥ FEV1 40 %) and type of surgery&#xD;
      (pneumectomy vs other). During screening a spirometry and a 6 minute walk test will be&#xD;
      performed. The first questionnaires (VAS, McGill pain questionnaire) will be given to the&#xD;
      patients after enrolment and before thoracotomy. The post-thoracotomy pain management&#xD;
      consists of the standard analgetic treatment; a thoracic epidural catheter which will be&#xD;
      slowly replaced by paracetamol, opioids and NSAID's. The consumption of analgetics will also&#xD;
      be documented in the follow up. Supplementary oxygen and lung inhalation is given when&#xD;
      necessary. This will be scored too. Regular physical therapy will be started directly after&#xD;
      thoracotomy as soon as possible.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The rehabilitation program will be initiated within a month after discharge. The degree of&#xD;
      the rehabilitation program will be separately detected for each patient by a cycle test&#xD;
      (heart rate) within 3 weeks post-thoracotomy. Patients in the pulmonary rehabilitation&#xD;
      program will be guided by a multidisciplinary team of pulmonologist, physical therapist and&#xD;
      social worker during 12 weeks. The program will last 3 x 2 hours weekly consisting of&#xD;
      exercise training and education.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All patients will be followed up after discharge at 1 month, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months&#xD;
      at the outpatient clinic of the pulmonology department and the pain clinic of the anaesthesia&#xD;
      department. Before discharge and at these intervals (except for the SGRQ at 1 month),&#xD;
      patients have to fill questionnaires about quality of life (SF-36 and SGRQ) and pain (McGill&#xD;
      pain questionnaire and VAS). Exercise capacity by means of the 6 minutes walk test and&#xD;
      spirometry will be measured after the accomplishment of the rehabilitation program at 3&#xD;
      months.&#xD;
&#xD;
      During follow up all the results between the experimental rehabilitation group and the&#xD;
      regular care group will be compared. In the interpretation of these results start to complete&#xD;
      recovery is defined as ECOG 0 and 1.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Randomisation, blinding and treatment allocation Randomisation will take place for&#xD;
      rehabilitation or regular care by a minimisation program with special attendance to age (&lt; 70&#xD;
      or ≥ 70 years), gender, the result of the 6 minute walk test (&lt; 100 m or ≥ 100 m), the FEV1&#xD;
      (FEV1&lt; 40% or ≥ FEV1 40 %), and type of surgery (pneumectomy vs other).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study population:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Eighty-eight patients with an elective thoracotomy between the age of 18 and 80 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Intervention:&#xD;
&#xD;
      An early pulmonary rehabilitation program during 12 weeks initiated after discharge from the&#xD;
      hospital.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Inclusion criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. elective, thoracotomy patients with a surgical intention to cure.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. age between 18 and 80 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. ECOG 0 - 2 post-thoracotomy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Exclusion criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. patients with chronic pain.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. a previous thoracotomy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. comorbidity limiting rehabilitation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. non-compliance.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Main study endpoints&#xD;
&#xD;
      1. health related quality of life (SGRQ score). Secondary study endpoints&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. general quality of life (SF-36).&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. acute / chronic post-thoracotomy pain (McGill and VAS).&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. impairment (changes in pulmonary function).&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. disability (exercise capacity; 6 Minute Walking Distance).&#xD;
&#xD;
        5. start to complete recovery (ECOG score of 0 or 1).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Statistical analysis: All analysis will be on an intention-to-treat basis. The primary&#xD;
      analysis will be on an intention-to-treat basis. The mean change in the primary endpoint&#xD;
      (SGRQ total score) after 6 months between the groups will be analysed using unpaired t-tests.&#xD;
      These tests will also be used to analyse differences after 12 months in secondary endpoints&#xD;
      (SF-36 scores, 6-minute walking difference, pain scores, and lung function values). Since&#xD;
      some study endpoints (quality of life and pain scores) will be measured more than two times&#xD;
      (repeatedly measured) the course of these scores in time will be tested using&#xD;
      MANOVA-analysis. To test for differences in proportions (proportion of patients with an&#xD;
      ECOG-score of 0 or 1 after rehabilitation) the Chi2 -test will be used.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Burden and risks associated with participation:&#xD;
&#xD;
      There are no adverse effects due to the rehabilitation program. Patients in the 'regular&#xD;
      care' group will not be guided by the multidisciplinary rehabilitation team. The&#xD;
      disadvantages are the following: Patients have to fill in quality of life questionnaires,&#xD;
      pain questionnaires and have to evaluate painscales (SGRQ, SF-36; McGill Pain questionnaire&#xD;
      and VAS) have to perform the 6 minutes walk-test and a spirometry twice. Finally, patients&#xD;
      have to visit the pulmonologist and the pain clinic more frequently. The expected benefits&#xD;
      are a better exercise tolerance, less pain and a better quality of life; a faster recovery.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SGRQ total score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF-36 scores</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>McGill pain questionnaire scores</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary function and 6MWD</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">57</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Thoracotomy</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Rehabilitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pulmonary rehabilitation post-thoracotomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pulmonary rehabilitation post-thoracotomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pulmonary rehabilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>2 or 3 times a week during 8 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pulmonary rehabilitation post-thoracotomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  elective, thoracotomy patients with a surgical intention to cure.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  age between 18 and 80 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ECOG 0 - 2 post-thoracotomy.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patients with chronic pain.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  a previous thoracotomy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  comorbidity limiting rehabilitation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  non-compliance&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>J.A. Stigt</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Isala</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Isala Klinieken</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zwolle</city>
        <zip>8011 JW</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 16, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 8, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Isala</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jan W.K. van den Berg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>elective thoracotomy</keyword>
  <keyword>pulmonary rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

