<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00491595</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-N01-CN-75035</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00491595</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I Clinical Study of Soy Isoflavones in Healthy, Post-Menopausal Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Multiple-Dose Clinical Study of Soy Isoflavones in Healthy, Post-Menopausal Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to examine the safety of specific soy components, known&#xD;
      as isoflavones, and to find out what effects (good and bad) these components have on tissues&#xD;
      that are sensitive to the hormone estrogen in healthy, post-menopausal women. Isoflavones are&#xD;
      compounds that occur naturally in soybeans and can be extracted to put in to capsule form or&#xD;
      add to foods. The capsule formulation being used in this study is considered an&#xD;
      investigational drug. This research is being done because many scientists believe that&#xD;
      isoflavones may play a role in the prevention of some kinds of cancer. While isoflavones have&#xD;
      been safely consumed in foods for centuries, we need to know if these soy components are safe&#xD;
      to take in higher doses when they are extracted from foods and provided in a supplement form.&#xD;
      We plan to test the safety and effects of the soy isoflavones known as genistein, daidzein&#xD;
      and glycitein.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a double blind, Phase I, multiple dose clinical trial of orally administered soy&#xD;
      isoflavones (PTI G-2535, 70% unconjugated isoflavones containing genistein, daidzein, and&#xD;
      glycitein). This preparation will be referred to as soy isoflavones in this and all study&#xD;
      related documents to more accurately reflect the study drug's content. The multiple dose&#xD;
      trial will last four months (112 days) and will include healthy, post-menopausal women as&#xD;
      determined by FSH levels and lack of spontaneous bleeding for at least one year. After&#xD;
      eligibility is determined, all potential subjects will ingest a soy shake to determine if&#xD;
      they are producers of the daidzein metabolite, equol. We expect to find approximately 30% of&#xD;
      our eligible subjects to be equol-producers as published in the literature. Equol producers&#xD;
      will be defined as individuals with plasma levels &gt;20ug/L; non-equol producers as those with&#xD;
      &lt;10ug/L 37. Individuals with intermediate equol values (&gt; 10 ug/L to &lt; 20 ug/L) will be&#xD;
      excluded from the study. Stratified randomization will assign the subjects to one of the two&#xD;
      groups, aiming for 30-40% equol producers in each group. Group 1 (20 subjects) will receive a&#xD;
      dietary supplement containing 600 mg of genistein in two doses of 300 mg (as part of a soy&#xD;
      isoflavones mixture) per day orally administered over an 84-day period. Group 2 (10 subjects)&#xD;
      will receive a placebo supplement (excipients from the active formulation), orally&#xD;
      administered over an 84-day period. These women will be recruited from the local population&#xD;
      within the Research Triangle area. The study will be conducted at the UNC Hospital General&#xD;
      Clinical Research Center (GCRC).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>Yes</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DNA damage, apoptosis, estrogenic effects and changes in gene expression</measure>
    <time_frame>112 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Drug Toxicity</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High Dose Soy isoflavones</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Performance status 0, 1, or 2 on ECOG scale&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acceptable hematopoietic, hepatic, and renal function (WBC≥3500 µL, platelet count ≥&#xD;
             100,000/ml, serum creatinine &lt; 2.0 mg/dl, serum bilirubin ≤ 2.0 mg/dl, transaminases &lt;&#xD;
             two times normal limits)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Post-menopausal status - FSH level &gt; 27 mIU/ml, no spontaneous bleeding &gt; 1 year&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Normal mammogram within the last 13 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Normal Papanicolaou Test within the last 13 months&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Serious intercurrent medical illnesses or history of seizure&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Significant cardiac disease (New York Heart Association Class III or IV)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Abnormalities on the physical examination screen including significant abnormality of&#xD;
             the heart, lungs, liver, spleen, or other abdominal organs, or neurologic abnormality&#xD;
             Abnormalities on the biochemical screen that could be metabolically significant&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Individuals with intermediate equol values (&gt; 10 ug/L to &lt; 20 ug/L) on soy challenge&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of antibiotics within the last 3 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of hormone/estrogen therapy or SERMs within the last 3 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Abnormal thyroid or endocrine function tests; or current use of thyroid medication&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  BMI at or above 35&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of complete hysterectomy or oophorectomy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  High risk of breast cancer (5-year risk of &gt;1.9%) based on NCI's Breast Cancer Risk&#xD;
             Assessment Tool&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A history of a malignancy active or initially diagnosed within 2 years other than&#xD;
             curatively treated non-melanoma carcinoma of the skin&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of substance abuse or addiction&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Alcohol intake of greater than 2 drinks/day or 14 drinks/week&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Tobacco use&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diets containing more than estimated intake of 20 mg genistein/day or 40mg&#xD;
             isoflavone/day AND unwilling/unable to reduce soy intake to below this level during&#xD;
             the study period&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of supplements containing phytoestrogens or that have estrogenic side effects&#xD;
             within 1 month of study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pre-menopausal or pregnant&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Inability to read and comprehend the Informed Consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Life expectancy &lt; 6 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of breast cancer&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Known soy intolerance&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  On chemotherapy within the last 2 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Inability to obtain an endometrial biopsy&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven H Zeisel, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC at Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>June 2007</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 26, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 26, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Soy isoflavones</keyword>
  <keyword>Genotoxicity</keyword>
  <keyword>Apoptosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Estrogenic effects</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Drug-Related Side Effects and Adverse Reactions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

