<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00494624</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VINKU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00494624</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Systemic Glucocorticoid in the Treatment of Wheezing in Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>VINKU</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Turku</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Academy of Finland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Turku</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We can not predict which wheezing child younger than 3 years of age benefits from systemic&#xD;
      glucocorticoid and which one does not. It is not known whether the differences in the&#xD;
      efficacy are related to the differences in viral etiology, atopy, immunogical maturity or age&#xD;
      of the patient. The study aims to answer the following questions: 1. What is the viral&#xD;
      etiology of acute childhood expiratory wheezing? 2. What is the efficacy of prednisolone in&#xD;
      relation to age, atopy and viral etiology in acute childhood wheezing? 3. Does prednisolone&#xD;
      treatment increase risk for secundary bacterial infection in acute childhood expiratory&#xD;
      wheezing? 4. What is the significance of inflammatory markers in predicting the efficacy of&#xD;
      systemic steroid or patient outcome in acute childhood expiratory wheezing? Study will follow&#xD;
      randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled parallel design. Study will start in Septemper&#xD;
      2000 and will be performed at the Department of Pediatrics, Turku University Hospital, Turku&#xD;
      Finland. The study population will be 300 hospitalized wheezing children aged 3 months - 15&#xD;
      years. Investigational drug will be prednisolone, first dose 2 mg/kg, then 2 mg/kg/d/3 (max.&#xD;
      60 mg/vrk) p.o. for 3 d and comparative drug will be placebo tablet similar to&#xD;
      investigational drug with the equal dosage. The primary outcome will be the time until ready&#xD;
      for discharge. The study will provide new and important information for the diagnostics,&#xD;
      treatment, disease outcome and prevention of acute childhood expiratory wheezing.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction&#xD;
&#xD;
      Extensive surveys have shown that 6-20 % of children have acute expiratory wheezing (1, 2).&#xD;
      The lifetime prevalence of wheezing among 12-14-year-old children in the Western countries is&#xD;
      8-19 % (3, 4). The clinical illness is called bronchiolitis when occuring for the first time&#xD;
      in infants younger than 12 months (5). When occuring later or recurring, beside bronchiolitis&#xD;
      a diagnosis of wheezy bronchitis has been used (6). In older children wheezy bronchitis&#xD;
      cannot be distinguished from virus-induced-asthma. In many countries the first expiratory&#xD;
      wheezing attack at the age of &gt; 3 years is diagnosed as asthma. To some extent,&#xD;
      bronchiolitis, wheezy bronchitis, and asthma are expressions of the same pathologic process&#xD;
      and at present there are no rigid criteria to separate these three illnessess.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Acute bronchiolitis is most commonly caused by respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) and wheezy&#xD;
      bronchitis by rhinovirus infections (6 - 8). Exacerbations of asthma are induced in 80-85% of&#xD;
      the cases by viral respiratory infections in children, mostly rhinovirus infections (7, 9).&#xD;
&#xD;
      It is well established that systemic glucocorticoids are the cornerstone in the management of&#xD;
      acute asthma (10). However, systemic glucocorticoids do not appear to be effective in&#xD;
      bronchiolitis in young children (11). Despite the lack of evidence for efficacy,&#xD;
      glucocorticoids are used up to 60 % of patients with RSV bronchiolitis (12).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The unfavourable effects of glucocorticoids during viral infections have received increasing&#xD;
      attention. For example, steroids have been found to increase the risk of acute otitis media&#xD;
      during rhinovirus infections in children (13). In adults glucocorticoids have increased the&#xD;
      titers of rhinovirus and the shedding of the virus from the pharynx (14, 15). It may be&#xD;
      possible that glucocorticoids increase the severity of some viral respiratory tract&#xD;
      infections.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Today, we can not predict which wheezing child younger than 3 years of age benefits from&#xD;
      systemic glucocorticoid and which one does not. It is not known whether the differences in&#xD;
      the efficacy are related to the differences in viral etiology, atopy, immunogical maturity or&#xD;
      age of the patient.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Main Questions&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. What is the viral etiology of acute childhood expiratory wheezing?&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. What is the efficacy of prednisolone in relation to age, atopy and viral etiology in&#xD;
           acute childhood expiratory wheezing?&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Does prednisolone treatment increase risk for secundary bacterial infection in acute&#xD;
           childhood expiratory wheezing?&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. What is the significance of inflammatory markers in predicting the efficacy of systemic&#xD;
           steroid or patient outcome in acute childhood expiratory wheezing?&#xD;
&#xD;
      Rationale&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study provides new and important information for the diagnostics, treatment, disease&#xD;
      outcome and prevention of acute childhood expiratory wheezing.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Design and setting&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study follows randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled parallel design. Study will start&#xD;
      in Septemper 2000 and continue until June 2002 (except June and July 2001). The study will be&#xD;
      performed at the department of pediatrics, Turku University Central Hospital, Turku Finland.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subjects&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study population will be 300 patients. To allow detection of a 18-h difference (half of&#xD;
      the average duration of stay in our hospital) in the time until ready for discharge between&#xD;
      the prednisolone-treated group and the placebo groups (with an estimated standard deviation&#xD;
      of 24 h) and to maintain an alpha error of 0.05 and a beta error of 0.20, the required size&#xD;
      of the sample is 27 children for each treatment group in RSV bronchiolitis (16). No estimate&#xD;
      is available for rhinovirus group. If patients are separated to different groups according to&#xD;
      e.g. age or viral infection, 108 patients are needed. On the other hand to get 31 patients&#xD;
      with a viral infection (viral infection in 80 % of patients with expiratory wheezing, and&#xD;
      sensitivity of methods 69 %), 49 children are needed in each treatment group (to assess&#xD;
      different subgroups, 196 children) (9, 17). To take account the variations of epidemics, a&#xD;
      total of 300 children will be recruited. The estimated time to get enough patients, which&#xD;
      need hospitalization for expiratory wheezing, will be 2 years at the department of&#xD;
      pediatrics, Turku University Central Hospital, Turku, Finland.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Inclusion criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  age 3 months to 16 years&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  hospitalization for expiratory wheezing&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  written informed consent from the parents&#xD;
&#xD;
      Exclusion criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Any chronic disease (other than allergy or asthma), e.g. heart disease, immune&#xD;
           deficiency, or diabetes&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  varicella and exposure to varicella if not previously have had it&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Systemic glucocorticoid 4 weeks prios to the study&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Severe disease that needs treatment in the intensive care unit or oxygen saturation&#xD;
           below 92% despite of additional oxygen and frequent salbutamol inhalations&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study drugs&#xD;
&#xD;
      Investigational drug&#xD;
&#xD;
      Prednisolone, first dose 2 mg/kg, then 2 mg/kg/d/3 (max. 60 mg/vrk) p.o. for 3 d (5 mg&#xD;
      tabletti, Prednisolon ®, Leiras, Finland).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Comparative drug&#xD;
&#xD;
      Placebo tablet similar to investigational drug (tablet, Leiras) will be given with the equal&#xD;
      dosage.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Addministration of the drug&#xD;
&#xD;
      Tablets will be cut in four pieces, which mixt into jelly ot yogurt. If the child vomits, the&#xD;
      drug will be given again after 30 min. If the child still vomits, he or she will be given&#xD;
      equal dose of methylprednisolone or physiologic saline i.v. or i.m. (62,5 mg/ml inject,&#xD;
      Solomet®, Orion, Finland).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Randomization&#xD;
&#xD;
      The randomization will be performed by an independent person not participating in the study.&#xD;
      According to the randomization, each volunteer will be allocated to one treatment. Individual&#xD;
      number 01 onwards will be assigned.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Protocol&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study physician will inform the subject and his or her guardian about the study and gives&#xD;
      the subject information (Appendix 1). Guardian's written informed concent (Appendix 2) will&#xD;
      be obtained after he or she has got acquainted with the test procedure. The subject can&#xD;
      withdraw the consent to the study at any time. Guardian will be asked to fill the modified&#xD;
      ISAAC questionaire (Appendix 3). New patients will enter the study at 8-10 a.m. and p.m.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study is outlined in the study flow sheet (Appendix 4). The study physician will examine&#xD;
      the patients twice daily at 8-10 a.m. and p.m. during the hospitalization (Appendix 5). The&#xD;
      patients will be hospitalized until he or she does not wheeze or have breathing difficulties.&#xD;
      After the hospitalization the patients will fill symptom diary for 2 weeks (Appendix 6).&#xD;
      Follow-up visit will be 2 weeks after the hospitalization and follow-up telephone contact&#xD;
      will be 2 months after the hospitalization. If the patient had a first wheezing episode, he&#xD;
      or she will be re-examined 12 months after the study and oscillometric examination will be&#xD;
      performed (if older than 24 months).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Nasal swap virological studies will also be performed to 60 healthy control children at&#xD;
      outpatient clinic or surgical department in the Turku University Central Hospital during the&#xD;
      study period.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Methods&#xD;
&#xD;
      Nasopharyngeal swap samples for virologic studies will be collected with 3 sterile cotton&#xD;
      swaps which are dipped through the nostrils against nasal mucosa. These samples will be&#xD;
      placed in a separate viral transport medium tubes for antigen, culture and PCR analysis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Virus culture (influenza A and B , adeno-, RS-, parainfluenza type 1, 2 and 3 virus) was done&#xD;
      by using the Ohio strain of HeLa cells and human foreskin fibroplasts according to routine&#xD;
      procedure. Viral antigens (influenza A and B , adeno-, RS-, parainfluenza type 1, 2 and 3&#xD;
      virus) were detected by time-resolved fluoroimmunoassay with monoclonal antibodies (17).&#xD;
      Reverse transcription-PCR assays were used for detection of corona-, rhino-, entero-, RS-,&#xD;
      influenza A and B as well as human metapneumovirus (hMPV). The details of methods have been&#xD;
      discribed earlier (18, 19). Virus-specific serum antibody titers (Influenza A and B virus,&#xD;
      adenovirus, parainfluenza type 1/3 and 2 virus, RSV, HHV-6 and enterovirus IgG as well as for&#xD;
      enterovirus also IgM) were determined by enzyme immunoassay (EIA) using antigen-coated solid&#xD;
      phase and horsedish peroxidase conjugated rabbit antihuman IgG (Dako, Glostrup, Denmark).&#xD;
      Three fold increase in IgG antibody titers was considered positive except four fold increase&#xD;
      in RSV IgG antibody titers. Enterovirus was also considered positive if virus specific IgM&#xD;
      was positive.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The influenssa A ja B , adeno , parainfluenssa type 1 , 2 and 3 as well as respiratory&#xD;
      synsytial virus (RSV) antigen and culture, and rhino-, entero- and coronavirus PCR will be&#xD;
      performed in the Department of Virology, Turku university, Finland. Human metapneumovirus PCR&#xD;
      will be performed in the Department of Virology, Erasmus Medical Center, Rotterdam, The&#xD;
      Netherlands. RSV A and B as well as Influenza virus A and B PCR will be performed in the&#xD;
      National Health Institute, Helsinki, Finland. Viral and bacteral (C. pneumoniae, M.&#xD;
      pneumoniae , S. pneumoniae, H. influenzae ja M. catarrhalis) will be performed in the&#xD;
      National Health Institute, Oulu, Finland (17).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Expiratory nitric oxide will collected bed side with a bag collection system (Siemens) and&#xD;
      analysed within 72 h at the Department of Clinical Physiology, Turku University Central&#xD;
      Hospital, Turku, Finland (20). Oscillometric studies will be performed at the Department of&#xD;
      Paediatric Turku University Central Hospital, Turku, Finland. Nasal cytokine (IL-8 and&#xD;
      RANTES) measurements will be performed in the Children's Hospital, University of Texas&#xD;
      Medical Branch, Galveston, Texas, USA. Other laboratory tests will be performed in the&#xD;
      Central Laboratory, Turku University Central Hospital, Turku, Finland.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Primary endpoint: Our primary endpoint will be the time until ready for discharge, which will&#xD;
      be defined as a duration of respiratory symptoms score &gt;3 during hospital stay. The&#xD;
      respiratory symptoms score, which will be assessed every 12 h during hospitalization, will&#xD;
      consist of the degree of dyspnea (0=none, 1=mild, 2=moderate, 3=severe), type of breathing&#xD;
      (0=normal, 1=use of stomach muscles, 2=use of intercostal muscles, 3=nasal flaring), severity&#xD;
      of auscultatory findings on wheezing (0=none, 1=expiratory, 2=inspiratory and expiratory,&#xD;
      3=audible without stethoscope), and assessment of expiratory:inspiratory time (0=1:2, 1=1:1,&#xD;
      2=2:1, 3=3:1). An estimation of 6 h will be used for the last 12 h period between hospital&#xD;
      assessments, i.e. the period during which the patient became ready for discharge.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Secondary endpoints: Oxygen saturation during hospital stay, wheeze and cough during two&#xD;
      weeks after discharge from the hospital (assessed each day as none, mild, moderate or&#xD;
      severe), readmission to the out-patient clinic or hospital for recurrent wheezing during a&#xD;
      two-month period after discharge and blood eosinophil counts at discharge and two weeks&#xD;
      later.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Adverse events&#xD;
&#xD;
      All adverse events encountered during the study period will be reported on the case record&#xD;
      forms. The subjects will be urged to report any adverse events immetiately after appearance.&#xD;
      All adverse events will be grated on a scale form 1 to 3, where 1 = mild, 2 = moderate and 3&#xD;
      = severe. The investigator will also be requested to judge the causality of each adverse&#xD;
      event to the treatment (1 = not related, 2 = possibly related and 3 = probably related). If&#xD;
      serious adverse effects occurs the sponsor shall be notified within 24 h by telephone and&#xD;
      subsequently in writing by the investigator. All serious adverse events must be reported to&#xD;
      national regulatory authorities within 24 hours of occurence.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Amendment of protocol&#xD;
&#xD;
      A new approval by the ethics committee has to be obtained before execution of any prospective&#xD;
      deviation from the signed protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subject recruitment and information&#xD;
&#xD;
      Before recruitement, the guardian will be informed about the aims, character and risks of the&#xD;
      study using the information text in the Subject Information (Appendix 1). After the subject&#xD;
      has had sufficient time to acquaint himself with the information text, the investigator seeks&#xD;
      for his written consent (Appendix 2). The original signed consent form will be retained by&#xD;
      investigator. The investigator is responsible for informing all study team members of&#xD;
      sufficient details of the study and the methods to be applied.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Ethical aspects&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study follows the recommendations for biomedical research involving human subjects&#xD;
      (current revision of the Declaration of Helsinki of the World Medical Assembly). Prior to&#xD;
      initiation of the study, the protocol, the subject information and the informed consent form&#xD;
      will be submitted to and approved by the ethics committee of Turku University Central&#xD;
      Hospital.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Data management and statistical analysis&#xD;
&#xD;
      The data will be collected in statistical software and the results will be analysed using&#xD;
      statistical tests appropriate for parallel design. All study correspondence, records and&#xD;
      documents related to the conduct of the study and the distribution of the investigational&#xD;
      drug (e.g. diskettes, case record forms, concent forms and other pertinent information) must&#xD;
      be retained by the investigator for a period of at least 15 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
      References&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Ruuskanen O, Ogra PL. Respiratory syncytial virus. Curr Probl Pediatr 1993;23:50-79.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Martinez FD, Wright AL, Taussig LM, Holmberg CJ, Halonen M, Morgan WJ. Asthma and&#xD;
           wheezing in the first six years of life. The Group Health Medical Associates. N Engl J&#xD;
           Med 1995;332:133-8.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Habbick BF, Pizzichini MM, Taylor B, Rennie D, Senthilselvan A, Sears MR. Prevalence of&#xD;
           asthma, rhinitis and eczema among children in 2 Canadian cities: the International Study&#xD;
           of Asthma and Allergies in Childhood. CMAJ 1999;160:1824-8.&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. Hesselmar B, Aberg B, Eriksson B, Aberg N. Asthma in children: prevalence, treatment,&#xD;
           and sensitization. Pediatr Allergy Immunol 2000;11:74-9.&#xD;
&#xD;
        5. McIntosh K. Bronchiolitis and asthma: possible common pathogenetic pathways. J Allergy&#xD;
           Clin Immunol 1976;57:595-604.&#xD;
&#xD;
        6. Mertsola J, Ziegler T, Ruuskanen O, Vanto T, Koivikko A, Halonen P. Recurrent wheezy&#xD;
           bronchitis and viral respiratory infections. Arch Dis Child 1991;66:124-9.&#xD;
&#xD;
        7. Rakes GP, Arruda E, Ingram JM, et al. Rhinovirus and respiratory syncytial virus in&#xD;
           wheezing children requiring emergency care. IgE and eosinophil analyses. Am J Respir&#xD;
           Crit Care Med 1999;159:785-90.&#xD;
&#xD;
        8. Glezen PW, Greenberg SB, Atmar RL, Piedra PA, Couch RB. Impact of respiratory virus&#xD;
           infections on persons with chronic underlying conditions. JAMA 2000;283:499-505.&#xD;
&#xD;
        9. Johnston SL, Pattemore PK, Sanderson G, et al. Community study of the role of viral&#xD;
           infections in exacerbations of asthma in 9-11 year old children. BMJ 1995;310:1225-9.&#xD;
&#xD;
       10. Storr J, Barrell E, Barry W, Lenney W, Hatcher G. Effect of a single oral dose of&#xD;
           prednisolonee in acute childhood asthma. Lancet 1987;1:879-82.&#xD;
&#xD;
       11. Roosevelt G, Sheehan K, Grupp Phelan J, Tanz RR, Listernick R. Dexamethasone in&#xD;
           bronchiolitis: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet 1996;348:292-5.&#xD;
&#xD;
       12. Wang EEL, Law BJ, Boucher FD, et al. Pediatric investigators collaborative network on&#xD;
           infections in Canada (PICNIC) study of admission and management variation in patients&#xD;
           hospitalized with respiratory syncytial viral lower respiratory tract infection. J&#xD;
           Pediatr 1996;129:390-5.&#xD;
&#xD;
       13. Ruohola A, Heikkinen T, Waris M, Puhakka T, Ruuskanen O. Intranasal fluticasone&#xD;
           propionate does not prevent acute otitis media during viral upper respiratory infection&#xD;
           in children. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2000;106:467-71.&#xD;
&#xD;
       14. Gustafson LM, Proud D, Hendley JO, Hayden FG, Gwaltney JM Jr. Oral prednisone therapy in&#xD;
           experimental rhinovirus infections. J Allergy Clin Immunol 1996;97:1009-14.&#xD;
&#xD;
       15. Puhakka T, Mäkelä MJ, Malmström K, et al. The common cold: effects of intranasal&#xD;
           fluticasone propionate treatment. J Allergy Clin Immunol 1998;101:726-31.&#xD;
&#xD;
       16. De Boeck K, Van der Aa N, Van Lierde S, Corbeel L, Eeckels R. Respiratory syncytial&#xD;
           virus bronchiolitis: a double-blind dexamethasone efficacy study. J Pediatr&#xD;
           1997;131:919-21.&#xD;
&#xD;
       17. Mäkelä MJ, Puhakka T, Ruuskanen O, Leinonen M, Saikku P, Kimpimäki M, et al. Viruses and&#xD;
           bacteria in the etiology of the common cold. J Clin Microbiol 1998; 36: 539 42.&#xD;
&#xD;
       18. Halonen P, Rocha E, Hierholzer J, Holloway B, Hyypiä T, Hurskainen P, Pallansch M.&#xD;
           Detection of enteroviruses and rhinoviruses in clinical specimens by PCR and&#xD;
           liquid-phase hybridization. J Clin Microbiology 1995;33:648-53.&#xD;
&#xD;
       19. van den Hoogen BG, de Jong JC, Groen J, Kuiken T, de Groot R, Fouchier RA, Osterhaus AD.&#xD;
           A newly discovered human pneumovirus isolated from young children with respiratory tract&#xD;
           disease. Nat Med 2001;7:719-24.&#xD;
&#xD;
       20. American Thoracic Society. Recommendations for standardized procedures for the online&#xD;
           and offline measurement of exhaled lower respiratory nitric oxide and nasal nitric oxide&#xD;
           in adults and children - 1999. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 1999; 160: 2104-17.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2008</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The time until ready for discharge</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygen saturation during hospital stay</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wheeze and cough during two weeks after discharge from the hospital</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readmission to the out-patient clinic or hospital for recurrent wheezing during a two-month period after discharge</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood eosinophil counts at discharge and two weeks later</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Wheezing</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>prednisolone</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  age 3 months to 16 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  hospitalization for expiratory wheezing&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  written informed consent from the parents&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any chronic disease (other than allergy or asthma), e.g. heart disease, immune&#xD;
             deficiency, or diabetes&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  varicella and exposure to varicella if not previously have had it&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Systemic glucocorticoid 4 weeks prios to the study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Severe disease that needs treatment in the intensive care unit or oxygen saturation&#xD;
             below 92% despite of additional oxygen and frequent salbutamol inhalations&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tuomas Jartti, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Turku University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Olli Ruuskanen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Turku University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tuomas Jartti, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+358 2 313 0000</phone>
    <email>tuomas.jartti@utu.fi</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Olli Ruuskanen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+358 2 313 0000</phone>
    <email>olli.ruuskanen@tyks.fi</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Turku University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Turku</city>
        <zip>20520</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tuomas Jartti, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+358 2 313 0000</phone>
      <email>tuomas.jartti@utu.fi</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Olli Ruuskanen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+358 2 313 0000</phone>
      <email>olli.ruuskanen@tyks.fi</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pasi Lehtinen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2007</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 2, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 2, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Wheezing</keyword>
  <keyword>virus</keyword>
  <keyword>child</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Sounds</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

