<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00498316</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2005-0781</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2011-02823</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>RP100469 02</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1P01CA148600-01A1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>5R01CA061508-20</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00498316</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cord Blood Expansion on Mesenchymal Stem Cells</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cord Blood Expansion on Mesenchymal Stem Cells</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ViaCell</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if combining cord blood units will be&#xD;
      safe and result in the cells &quot;taking&quot; faster in recipients. The cord blood units will have&#xD;
      their cell number increased in the lab using cells from a family member or they will be&#xD;
      collected from an unrelated healthy donor.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Umbilical cord blood is a source of blood-forming cells that can be used for transplantation.&#xD;
      The major problem with this type of transplant is the small number of blood-forming cells&#xD;
      available in each cord unit, which may delay the &quot;take&quot; of the graft in the recipient. A&#xD;
      strategy to overcome this problem is to give 2 cord blood units, increasing the number of&#xD;
      cord blood cells in one of them in the laboratory before they are transplanted. This is done&#xD;
      in order to increase their number. The expansion of 1, but not both, of the cord blood units&#xD;
      will allow the research team to decide more effectively whether the laboratory expansion is&#xD;
      responsible for the speed and content of the &quot;take.&quot; At this time, no proof exists that this&#xD;
      expansion technique will improve the performance of the cord blood specimens.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In order to collect a larger expansion of the numbers of cord blood cells, recent research&#xD;
      suggests that growing the cord blood cells on a layer of bone marrow stromal cells increases&#xD;
      the number of expanded cells which can be collected. In the body, these stromal cells form a&#xD;
      matrix or &quot;spider web&quot; in the bone marrow. Blood-forming bone marrow cells (looking like&#xD;
      dewdrops) grow on this stromal cell matrix (spider web) and are nurtured by the stromal&#xD;
      cells. In this research study, researchers will either collect marrow stromal cells from a&#xD;
      family member through a bone marrow aspiration, or they will use &quot;off-the-shelf&quot; marrow&#xD;
      stromal cells that have been collected from a healthy donor. These &quot;off-the-shelf&quot; marrow&#xD;
      stromal cells were grown and frozen by Mesoblast Systems. These stromal cells from either&#xD;
      your family member or &quot;off-the-shelf&quot; will hopefully improve the performance of the cord&#xD;
      blood cells after they are given to you.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Placement of central venous catheter for collection of &quot;back-up&quot; peripheral blood progenitor&#xD;
      cells (PBPC):&#xD;
&#xD;
      Before you have back-up PBPC collected or you receive chemotherapy, you will require&#xD;
      placement of a hollow plastic tube (catheter) into a large vein inside your body. This&#xD;
      catheter will be used to draw blood and to give medications and fluids. The catheter is&#xD;
      inserted through the skin in the upper chest and extends to a point above the right side of&#xD;
      your heart. Your doctor will explain this procedure to you in more detail, and you will be&#xD;
      required to sign a separate consent form for this procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Collection of back-up stem cells:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Because collecting additional cells from the donor of the cord blood is not possible if the&#xD;
      transplant with cord blood fails, a back-up PBPC or bone marrow sample to ensure recovery of&#xD;
      your marrow function will be collected from you and frozen before the high dose chemotherapy&#xD;
      begins. This specimen will only be used if doctors think it is necessary.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Peripheral blood progenitor cell collection (Leukapheresis):&#xD;
&#xD;
      Before collection of the PBPC, you will be treated with a drug called granulocyte colony&#xD;
      stimulating factor (G-CSF), which will cause the important stem cells in the marrow to move&#xD;
      the peripheral blood where they will be collected. This medication is given as a shot under&#xD;
      the skin once a day for 3-7 days, at which time your PBPC will be collected from your central&#xD;
      catheter during a 3-4 hour outpatient procedure. This procedure is standard, and is called&#xD;
      leukapheresis. You will be required to sign a separate consent form for this procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Bone Marrow Collection:&#xD;
&#xD;
      If the leukapheresis cannot be performed successfully, you will receive general anesthesia in&#xD;
      the operating room and will have multiple needle sticks of the hip bones in order to collect&#xD;
      bone marrow. Less than 5 percent of your bone marrow will be taken. This procedure, if done,&#xD;
      will also require you to sign a separate consent form.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Selection of alternate back-up donor:&#xD;
&#xD;
      If your own back-up bone marrow or back-up PBPC cannot be collected, a family member will be&#xD;
      asked to serve as a back-up donor or an identified third cord blood unit may be used should&#xD;
      both the cord blood units fail to function. A back-up donor or product will be required for&#xD;
      you to participate in this research&#xD;
&#xD;
      Selection of a stromal cell donor for cord cultures:&#xD;
&#xD;
      In this study, researchers will identify a donor for the stromal cells. This will either be a&#xD;
      family member or from an unrelated healthy donor whose marrow stromal cells were collected,&#xD;
      grown, and frozen by Mesoblast Systems (off-the-shelf). If your family member is used, they&#xD;
      will collect about 7 tablespoons of bone marrow from them.This family member's tissue type&#xD;
      (HLA antigens) does not exactly match yours. That bone marrow will be taken to the laboratory&#xD;
      where over 3-4 weeks, marrow stromal cells will be grown. These marrow stromal cells produce&#xD;
      vitamin-like growth factors that may help your cord blood cells expand to greater numbers. If&#xD;
      a family member is not appropriately HLA matched, does not meet eligibility, is not a&#xD;
      candidate due to health reasons, or if the participant's disease is getting worse so that&#xD;
      there is not enough time to grow the family member's marrow cells into marrow stromal cells,&#xD;
      then &quot;off-the-shelf&quot; marrow stromal cells that have been collected from a healthy donor will&#xD;
      be used for the procedure. These &quot;off-the-shelf&quot; marrow stromal cells were grown and frozen&#xD;
      by Mesoblast Systems. These cells have been safely given to patients with peripheral vascular&#xD;
      disease, but their use in this study is considered investigational.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Your bone marrow transplant doctors will assign you to one of 3 chemotherapy treatments,&#xD;
      which are discussed below.&#xD;
&#xD;
      High-dose chemotherapy treatment (Myeloablative):&#xD;
&#xD;
      If you are between 1 and 55 years of age and can receive high-dose chemotherapy, or you are&#xD;
      between 55 and 65 years old and your doctor agrees, you will receive fludarabine,&#xD;
      clofarabine, busulfan, antithymocyte globulin (ATG), and total body irradiation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      You will receive a test dose of busulfan by vein over 60 minutes as an outpatient usually&#xD;
      during the week before admission. If the test dose cannot be given as an outpatient, you will&#xD;
      be admitted to the hospital on Day -9 for IV fluids and the busulfan test dose. This&#xD;
      low-level &quot;test&quot; dose of busulfan is to check how the level of busulfan in your blood levels&#xD;
      changes over time. This information will be used to decide the next dose needed to reach the&#xD;
      target blood level that matches your body size.&#xD;
&#xD;
      About 11 samples of blood will be drawn for pharmacokinetic (PK) testing of busulfan. PK&#xD;
      testing measures the amount of study drug in the body at different time points. These blood&#xD;
      samples will be drawn at various timepoints starting before the Busulfan infusion and&#xD;
      continuing over approximately the next 11 hours. The blood samples will be repeated again&#xD;
      with the first day of high-dose busulfan treatment. Each sample will be about 1 teaspoon of&#xD;
      blood. A temporary heparin lock will be placed in your vein to lower the number of needle&#xD;
      sticks needed for these draws. If it is not possible for the PK tests to be performed for&#xD;
      technical or scheduling reasons, you will receive the standard fixed dose of busulfan.&#xD;
&#xD;
      If you received the test dose as an outpatient, you will be admitted to the hospital on Day&#xD;
      -8 and will receive fluids by vein. On Days -7 through -4, you will receive by vein&#xD;
      fludarabine over 1 hour, clofarabine by vein over 1 hour, and busulfan by vein over 3 hours.&#xD;
      You will receive ATG on Days -4 and -3. On Day -3, you will receive a single treatment of&#xD;
      low-dose total body irradiation. You will &quot;rest&quot; (not receive chemotherapy drugs) on Days -2&#xD;
      and -1. Day 0 is the day of transplantation, so the negative day numbers are used to label&#xD;
      the treatment days before transplant.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All chemotherapy drugs, fluids, and other medications that must be given by vein will be&#xD;
      infused through the catheter. Once the back-up cells are collected, all participants will be&#xD;
      admitted to the hospital as indicated by their assigned treatment plan schedule. Chemotherapy&#xD;
      may be stopped if intolerable side effects occur.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Lower-dose chemotherapy treatment (Non-myeloablative):&#xD;
&#xD;
      If you are older than 55 and 80 years of age or less, or are of any age with a pre-existing&#xD;
      medical condition that prevents you from receiving high dose chemotherapy, you will receive&#xD;
      fludarabine- cyclophosphamide-ATG-total body irradiation. You will receive cyclophosphamide&#xD;
      as a single dose on Day -6. Fludarabine will be given once a day for 4 days in a row (Days -6&#xD;
      through -3). You will receive ATG on Days -4 and -3. You will also receive a single treatment&#xD;
      of low-dose total body irradiation on Day -1. Day 0 is the day of transplantation. Rituximab&#xD;
      may be given on Day -9 if appropriate for your disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All chemotherapy drugs, fluids, and other medications that must be given by vein will be&#xD;
      infused through the catheter. Once the back-up cells are collected, all participants will be&#xD;
      admitted to the hospital as indicated by their assigned treatment plan schedule. Chemotherapy&#xD;
      may be stopped if intolerable side effects occur.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Reduced Intensity chemotherapy treatment:&#xD;
&#xD;
      If you are between the ages of 1 and 80 years old (and the study doctors think this would&#xD;
      keep you from receiving the full myeloablative therapy), if you cannot receive low-dose total&#xD;
      body irradiation, and if your doctor agrees, you will receive fludarabine-melphalan-ATG.&#xD;
      Starting on Day -5 you will receive fludarabine given once a day for 4 days in a row (Days -5&#xD;
      through -2). You will receive Melphalan as a single dose on Day -2. You will receive ATG on&#xD;
      Days -3 and -2. Day 0 is the day of transplantation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All chemotherapy drugs, fluids, and other medications that must be given by vein will be&#xD;
      infused through the catheter. Once the back-up cells are collected, all participants will be&#xD;
      admitted to the hospital as indicated by their assigned treatment plan schedule. Chemotherapy&#xD;
      may be stopped if intolerable side effects occur.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Expansion of cord blood:&#xD;
&#xD;
      On Day -14, one of your two cord blood units will be thawed in the MD Anderson Stem Cell&#xD;
      Laboratory and expanded over a layer of marrow stromal cells from your family member or from&#xD;
      &quot;off-the-shelf&quot; marrow stromal cells. The expansion will continue for about 2 weeks and when&#xD;
      complete, the cells will be given to you on Day 0 as described below. A small amount of cord&#xD;
      blood cells (less than 3%) will be used for laboratory procedures that measure the quality of&#xD;
      the product.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The CliniMACS System is a medical device that is used to separate types of blood cells from&#xD;
      blood that is removed from the body during leukapheresis. These separated cells are processed&#xD;
      for use in treatments such as stem cell transplants.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Transplantation of cord blood:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Two (2) days after completion of high or lower-dose therapy (Day 0), both units of cord blood&#xD;
      (the expanded and the unexpanded cord) will be infused into you (one at a time) through your&#xD;
      catheter. The unexpanded cord will be thawed and infused first, followed by the infusion of&#xD;
      the cells that were expanded in the lab. Each unit will take about 30 minutes to infuse. You&#xD;
      will then be hospitalized until your marrow function is restored enough. This usually takes&#xD;
      between 3-6 weeks. During this time, you will receive a variety of medications, transfusions,&#xD;
      and other standard procedures aimed at decreasing the risks of this procedure, such as graft&#xD;
      vs. host disease (GVHD).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Graft versus host disease (GVHD) preventive therapy:&#xD;
&#xD;
      GVHD results from a reaction of the transplanted cord blood cells against certain tissues in&#xD;
      your body. In an attempt to prevent or decrease the severity of GVHD, you will receive 2&#xD;
      drugs. Mycophenolate will be given through your catheter 2 times per day (morning and&#xD;
      evening) on Days -3 through Day 100. Tacrolimus will be given as a 24-hour continuous&#xD;
      infusion over 3-6 weeks. Around Day 30 or 40 (after engraftment), the tacrolimus will be&#xD;
      changed to pills given once a day for 180 days (6 months). If GVHD is present, tacrolimus may&#xD;
      then be continued longer. The number of tacrolimus pills may vary according to the blood&#xD;
      levels of the drug, but usually are between 1-5 pills. Your dose of tacrolimus can be&#xD;
      gradually lowered around Day 180 if no GVHD is present. This medicine is used for 6-9 months&#xD;
      (longer if chronic GVHD occurs).&#xD;
&#xD;
      You will remain on study as long as your disease does not return. If your disease returns,&#xD;
      you will be taken off study and you may be offered participation in another study or other&#xD;
      standard treatments.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Follow-up after transplant:&#xD;
&#xD;
      After you leave the hospital, you will be seen regularly in the Department of Blood and&#xD;
      Marrow Transplantation at MD Anderson. The frequency of the visits may vary, but may be as&#xD;
      often as daily. Routine blood (1-2 tablespoons) and urine tests will be performed. The&#xD;
      frequency of blood tests may also vary, but may be performed daily. You will have bone marrow&#xD;
      samples collected before transplant and then as needed during the first 100 days after&#xD;
      transplant, every 3 months during the first year after transplant, and then once a year while&#xD;
      you are on study. After that, bone marrow samples will be collected once a year,&#xD;
      indefinitely. These samples are being collected to look for tumor (as a staging test) and to&#xD;
      looFk for chimerism (the percent of tumor cells detectable that can predict graft failure&#xD;
      and/or relapse). To collect a bone marrow sample, an area of the hip or chest bone is numbed&#xD;
      with anesthetic and a small amount of bone marrow is withdrawn through a large needle.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants with lymphomas and Hodgkin's disease will need a computed tomography (CT) scan&#xD;
      of the chest, abdomen, and pelvis performed before transplant, then as needed during the&#xD;
      first 100 days after transplant, and then every 3 months for the first year after transplant.&#xD;
      After that, these scans will be done yearly. You will be on study for 1 year but then will be&#xD;
      followed yearly as is standard of care.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This is an investigational study. All treatment drugs given to you are FDA approved and&#xD;
      commercially available. The CliniMACS device is not FDA approved. At this time, it is being&#xD;
      used in research only. Up to 125 patients may take part in this study. All will be enrolled&#xD;
      at MD Anderson.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 3, 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Engraftment and Time to Engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days after transplant, then every 3 months thereafter</time_frame>
    <description>Engraftment defined as a sustained ANC &gt; 0.5 x 109/L for 3 consecutive days and evidence of donor chimerism or autologous reconstitution by D+42</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">98</enrollment>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cord blood transplantation performed on day 0. Busulfan 32 mg/m2 by vein as an outpatient before Day -14 or as an inpatient on Day -9, and AUC of 4,000 microMol.min-1 by vein on Days -7 to -4.&#xD;
Fludarabine 10 mg/m2 by vein on Days -7 to -4, 40 mg/m2 by vein on Days -6 to -3 or on Days -5 to -2.&#xD;
Rituximab 375 mg/m2 by vein on Day -9. ATG 1.25 mg/Kg by vein on Day -4 and 1.75 mg/Kg by vein on Day -3, 1.25 mg/kg by vein on Day -3 and 1.75 mg/kg by vein on Day -2.&#xD;
Cyclophosphamide 50 mg/kg by vein on Day -6. Clofarabine 30 mg/m2 by vein on Days -7 to -4. Total body irradiation (TBI) 200 cGy at 25 cGy/minute delivered on Day -3. Melphalan 140 mg/m2 by vein on Day -2. Tacrolimus 0.03 mg/kg by vein daily starting on D-2, to be changed to oral dosing when tolerated. Tacrolimus is to be tapered around Day +180, if no GVHD is present.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cord Blood Infusion</intervention_name>
    <description>Cord blood transplantation performed on day 0.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Busulfan</intervention_name>
    <description>32 mg/m2 by vein as an outpatient before Day -14 or as an inpatient on Day -9, and AUC of 4,000 microMol.min-1 by vein on Days -7 to -4 for patients with ALL, AML, NHL, CLL, CML, HD, and MM who are &gt;1 and &lt; 55 years old. Patients &gt;55 but &lt; 65 years who have a Performance Status of 0 or 1 and no comorbidities may receive the myeloablative regimen 4 at the discretion of the investigator(s).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Busulfex</other_name>
    <other_name>Myleran</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>10 mg/m2 by vein on Days -7 to -4 for patients with ALL, AML, NHL, CLL, CML, HD, and MM who are &gt;1 and &lt; 55 years old. Patients &gt;55 but &lt; 65 years who have a Performance Status of 0 or 1 and no comorbidities may receive the myeloablative regimen 4 at the discretion of the investigator(s).&#xD;
40 mg/m2 by vein on Days -6 to -3 for patients with AML, ALL, NHL, CLL,CML, HD and MM who are &gt; 55 and &lt; 80 years old or of any age with co-morbid condition that in the opinion of the investigators would preclude myeloablative therapy.&#xD;
40 mg/m2 by vein on Days -5 to -2 for patients with AML, ALL, NHL, CLL, CML, and HD who are &gt;1 and &lt; 80 years old that in the opinion of the investigator(s) would preclude myeloablative therapy and who cannot receive Total Body Irradiation (TBI) may receive the reduced intensity treatment regimen 3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fludarabine Phosphate</other_name>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>375 mg/m2 by vein on Day -9 for patients with AML, ALL, NHL, CLL,CML, HD and MM who are &gt; 55 and &lt; 80 years old or of any age with co-morbid condition that in the opinion of the investigators would preclude myeloablative therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rituxan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ATG</intervention_name>
    <description>1.25 mg/Kg by vein on Day -4 and 1.75 mg/Kg by vein on Day -3 for patients with AML, ALL, NHL, CLL,CML, HD and MM who are &gt; 55 and &lt; 80 years old or of any age with co-morbid condition that in the opinion of the investigators would preclude myeloablative therapy.&#xD;
1.25 mg/kg by vein on Day -3 and 1.75 mg/kg by vein on Day -2 for patients with AML, ALL, NHL, CLL, CML, and HD who are &gt;1 and &lt; 80 years old that in the opinion of the investigator(s) would preclude myeloablative therapy and who cannot receive Total Body Irradiation (TBI) may receive the reduced intensity treatment regimen 3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Antithymocyte Globulin</other_name>
    <other_name>Thymoglobulin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>50 mg/kg by vein on Day -6 for patients with AML, ALL, NHL, CLL,CML, HD and MM who are &gt; 55 and &lt; 80 years old or of any age with co-morbid condition that in the opinion of the investigators would preclude myeloablative therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cytoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Neosar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clofarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>30 mg/m2 by vein on Days -7 to -4 for patients with ALL, AML, NHL, CLL, CML, HD, and MM who are &gt;1 and &lt; 55 years old. Patients &gt;55 but &lt; 65 years who have a Performance Status of 0 or 1 and no comorbidities may receive the myeloablative regimen 4 at the discretion of the investigator(s).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Clofarex</other_name>
    <other_name>Clolar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Total Body Irradiation (TBI)</intervention_name>
    <description>200 cGy at 25 cGy/minute delivered on Day -3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TBI</other_name>
    <other_name>XRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Melphalan</intervention_name>
    <description>140 mg/m2 by vein on Day -2 for patients with AML, ALL, NHL, CLL, CML, and HD who are &gt;1 and &lt; 80 years old that in the opinion of the investigator(s) would preclude myeloablative therapy and who cannot receive Total Body Irradiation (TBI) may receive the reduced intensity treatment regimen 3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alkeran</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>0.03 mg/kg by vein daily starting on D-2, to be changed to oral dosing when tolerated. Tacrolimus is to be tapered around Day +180, if no GVHD is present.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Prograf</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mycophenolate Mofetil</intervention_name>
    <description>1 gram by vein twice a day Days -3 through Day 100.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MMF</other_name>
    <other_name>CellCept</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>G-CSF</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mcg/kg/day subcutaneously beginning on day 0, and continuing until the absolute neutrophil count (ANC) is &gt; 2.5 x 109/L.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cord Blood Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Filgrastim</other_name>
    <other_name>Neupogen</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Patients must have one of the following hematologic malignancies: Acute Myelogenous&#xD;
             Leukemia (AML), induction failure, high-risk for relapse first remission (with&#xD;
             intermediate-risk or high-risk cytogenetics, flt3 mutation positive and/or evidence of&#xD;
             minimal residual disease by flow cytometry), secondary leukemia from prior&#xD;
             chemotherapy and/or arising from MDS, Langerhan's cell histiocytosis, any disease&#xD;
             beyond first remission; or,&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS): Primary or therapy related; or,&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL): induction failure, primary refractory to treatment&#xD;
             (do not achieve complete remission after first course of therapy) or are beyond first&#xD;
             remission including second or greater remission or active disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. #3, continued: Patients in first remission are eligible if they are considered high&#xD;
             risk, defined as any of the following detected at any time: with translocations 9;22&#xD;
             or 4;11, hypodiploidy, complex karyotype, secondary leukemia developing after&#xD;
             cytotoxic drug exposure, and/or evidence of minimal residual disease, or acute&#xD;
             biphenotypic leukemia, or double hit non-Hodgkin's lymphoma; or,&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma (NHL) in second or third complete remission, or relapse&#xD;
             (including relapse post autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplant). Double hit&#xD;
             lymphomas in first remission or more advanced disease; or,&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma (SLL), or Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) with&#xD;
             progressive disease following standard therapy; or,&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. CML second chronic phase or accelerated phase; or,&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Hodgkin's Disease (HD): Induction failures, second or third complete remission, or&#xD;
             relapse (including relapse post autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplant); or,&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Multiple Myeloma: stage II or III, symptomatic, secretory Multiple Myeloma requiring&#xD;
             treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Age greater than or equal to 1 year but less than or equal to 55 years (Myeloablative&#xD;
             Regimen 4). Eligibility for pediatric patients will be determined in conjunction with&#xD;
             an MD Anderson Cancer Center (MDACC) pediatrician. Patients &gt;55 but &lt; 65 years who&#xD;
             have a Performance Status of 0 or 1 and no comorbidities may receive the myeloablative&#xD;
             regimen 4 at the discretion of the investigator(s).&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Age greater than 55 years and less than or equal to 80 years (Nonmyeloablative Regimen&#xD;
             2)&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. Age greater than or equal to 1 but less than or equal to 80 years old that in the&#xD;
             opinion of the investigator(s) would preclude myeloablative therapy and who cannot&#xD;
             receive Total Body Irradiation (TBI) may receive reduced intensity regimen 3.&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Performance score of at least 60% by Karnofsky or PS less than 3 (ECOG) (age greater&#xD;
             than or equal to 12 years), or Lansky Play-Performance Scale of at least 60% or&#xD;
             greater (age &lt;12 years)&#xD;
&#xD;
         14. Left ventricular ejection fraction of at least 40% (Myeloablative Regimen 4, Reduced&#xD;
             Intensity Regimen 3) or 30% (Nonmyeloablative Regimen 2)&#xD;
&#xD;
         15. Pulmonary function test demonstrating a diffusion capacity of least 50% predicted&#xD;
             (Myeloablative Regimen 4, Reduced Intensity Regimen 3) or at least 40% predicted&#xD;
             (Nonmyeloablative Regimen 2). For children &lt; 7 years of age who are unable to perform&#xD;
             pulmonary function test (PFT), oxygen saturation &gt; 92% on room air by pulse oximetry.&#xD;
&#xD;
         16. Creatinine &lt; 1.6 mg/dL (Myeloablative Regimen 4, Reduced Intensity Regimen 3) or &lt; 3.0&#xD;
             mg/dL (Nonmyeloablative Regimen 2).&#xD;
&#xD;
         17. Serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT)/bilirubin &lt; / = to 2.0 x normal&#xD;
             (Myeloablative Regimen 4, Reduced Intensity Regimen 3) or &lt; / = 4.0 x normal&#xD;
             (Nonmyeloablative Regimen 2)&#xD;
&#xD;
         18. Negative Beta HCG test in a woman with child bearing potential defined as not&#xD;
             post-menopausal for 12 months or no previous surgical sterilization and willing to use&#xD;
             an effective contraceptive measure while on study.&#xD;
&#xD;
         19. Unrelated Cord Blood will be used as a source of hematopoietic support if a 5 or 6/6&#xD;
             related or 6/6 unrelated bone marrow donor is not available, or if the tempo of a&#xD;
             patient's disease dictates it is not in the patient's best interest to wait for an&#xD;
             unrelated marrow donor to be procured.&#xD;
&#xD;
         20. Patients must have two Cord Blood units available which are matched with the patient&#xD;
             at 4, 5, or 6/6 HLA class I (serological) and II (molecular) antigens. Each cord must&#xD;
             contain at least 10 million total nucleated cells/Kg recipient body weight (pre-thaw)&#xD;
&#xD;
         21. Patients must have a family member who is matched at 2, 3, or 4 HLA antigens typed as&#xD;
             described above and willing to donate 80-100 ml or bone marrow for MSC generation or&#xD;
             the Angioblast Mesenchymal Precursor Cells will be used for the cord blood&#xD;
             co-cultures. Patients that are high risk for relapse are eligible to use the&#xD;
             Angioblast &quot;off-the-shelf&quot; Mesenchymal Precursor Cells.&#xD;
&#xD;
         22. Have identified a back-up cell source in case of engraftment failure. The source can&#xD;
             be autologous, related, or unrelated.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. HIV positive&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Positive beta HCG in female of child-bearing potential defined as not post-menopausal&#xD;
             for 12 months or no previous surgical sterilization or breast-feeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Uncontrolled serious medical condition such as persistent septicemia despite adequate&#xD;
             antibiotic therapy, decompensated congestive heart failure despite cardiac medications&#xD;
             or pulmonary insufficiency requiring intubation. (excluding primary disease for which&#xD;
             CB transplantation is proposed), or psychiatric condition that would limit informed&#xD;
             consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Active central nervous system (CNS) disease in patient with history of CNS malignancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Availability of appropriate, willing, HLA-matched related marrow donor.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Shpall, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 6, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 10, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Cord Blood Expansion</keyword>
  <keyword>Umbilical Cord Blood</keyword>
  <keyword>Mesenchymal Stem Cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Myelogenous Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>ALL</keyword>
  <keyword>AML</keyword>
  <keyword>MDS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melphalan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Busulfan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clofarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thymoglobulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antilymphocyte Serum</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

