<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00493519</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TASMC-07-NV-219-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00493519</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cephalic Phase in Anorexia Nervosa,Bulimia Nervosa and Obese Binge Eaters</brief_title>
  <acronym>Cephalic 1</acronym>
  <official_title>Cephalic Phase in Anorexia Nervosa,Bulimia Nervosa and Obese Binge Eaters</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this trial is to examine the cephalic phase insulin response (CPIR) and&#xD;
      pancreatic polypeptide (PP) release as indicators of the cephalic phase occurrence and&#xD;
      magnitude to palatable food stimulus in anorectic and bulimic subgroups as compared to&#xD;
      healthy controls&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Food stimulation of gastric and pancreatic secretion is classically divided into cephalic,&#xD;
      gastric and intestinal phases.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Cephalic phase refers to a simultaneous activation of gastrointestinal motility, gastric acid&#xD;
      and pancreatic enzyme secretion ,as well as, release of hormones from the endocrine pancreas&#xD;
      which occurs through activation of vagal -efferents as a result of food-related sensory&#xD;
      stimuli such as taste and smell prior to nutrient absorption and which coincides with a&#xD;
      thermogenic response.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Of the cephalic phase secretions, cephalic phase insulin release (CPIR) has received the most&#xD;
      attention, but pancreatic polypeptide (PP) and glucagon responses have also been studied.&#xD;
      While the magnitude of cephalic phase insulin release is relatively small (25% above&#xD;
      baseline), pancreatic polypeptide increases 100% above baseline. The large magnitude of the&#xD;
      PP response makes it a sensitive indicator of vagal activation to food stimuli.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In most experiments, subjects are either exposed to visual and olfactory stimulation by&#xD;
      seeing and smelling the food stimulus or are required to perform a modified sham-feed, i.e.&#xD;
      to taste, chew and then expectorate the food stimulus.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In general, cephalic phase are thought to be preparatory response before ingestion of food.&#xD;
      Because of their small magnitude, the physiological significance of the cephalic phase&#xD;
      hormonal responses has been largely discounted. However, there is evidence that experimental&#xD;
      prevention of CPIR lead to hyperinsulinemia and hyperglycemia. Therefore, CPIR may contribute&#xD;
      to glucose homeostasis /regulation. Moreover CPIR may be an indicator of hunger and could be&#xD;
      important for understanding eating disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In parallel with these hormonal secretion ,an increase in energy expenditure has also been&#xD;
      observed . This thermogenic response to food is even greater with sham feeding than with&#xD;
      normal feeding and is paralleled by changes in RQ showing enhanced carbohydrate oxidation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Studies conducted in obese humans demonstrate exaggerated absolute magnitude of CPIR .However&#xD;
      basal hyper-insulinemia which is typically observed in obese individuals may clouds this&#xD;
      observation. Moreover, it has been hypothesized that CPIR is attenuated in obese when is&#xD;
      expressed as a percentage of baseline and therefore they may not secrete enough insulin&#xD;
      during pre-absorptive period to regulate postprandial glucose levels.&#xD;
&#xD;
      There is also evidence that obese people with insulin resistance have a reduced thermogenic&#xD;
      response to feeding .&#xD;
&#xD;
      Only limited numbers of studies have been done on the cephalic phase in anorexia and bulimia.&#xD;
      There are findings of a significant CPIR in anorexics as compared to controls which tends to&#xD;
      rule out a deficient cephalic insulin response as a contributor to the self-starvation&#xD;
      observed in anorexia nervosa. As to bulimics who often show endocrine abnormalities, their&#xD;
      CPIR was only slightly differ or from controls.&#xD;
&#xD;
      These findings suggest more complex determinants of eating disorders than physiological state&#xD;
      alone.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2007</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>VAS, EDI, Blood test for glucose, insulin, PP, shame feed procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Anorexia Nervosa</condition>
  <condition>Bulimia Nervosa</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>chocolate cake</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        75 patients will be divided into the following 4 subgroups;&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. . 15 patients with anorexia nervosa.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. . 15 patients with bulimia nervosa (purging type).&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. . 15 patients with binge eating disorder and obesity.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. . 15 obese patients without eating disorder&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. . 15 Non-eating disordered normal weight patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Non diabetic and non-pregnant patients above 18 years of age without gastrointestinal&#xD;
        diseases and without medications which can affect gastrointestinal motility and appetite.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nachum Vaisman, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>TASMC Israel</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nachum Vaisman, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+972-524-266596</phone>
    <email>vaisman@tasmc.health.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>TASMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Aviv</city>
        <zip>64239</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nachum Vaisman, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+972-524-266596</phone>
      <email>vaisman@tasmc.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2007</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 4, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 4, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 6, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Cephalic phase</keyword>
  <keyword>Anorexia nervosa</keyword>
  <keyword>Bulimia nervosa</keyword>
  <keyword>obese binge eaters</keyword>
  <keyword>VAS</keyword>
  <keyword>EDI</keyword>
  <keyword>shame-feed procedure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anorexia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bulimia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anorexia Nervosa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bulimia Nervosa</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

