<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00495872</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2007-0170</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00495872</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Valproic Acid-Based 2-Agent Oral Regimens for Patients With Advanced Solid Tumor</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-Arm Complete Phase 1 Trial of Valproic Acid-Based 2-Agent Oral Regimens for Patients With Advanced Solid Tumor</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to find the highest tolerable dose of valproic&#xD;
      acid in combination with either dasatinib, erlotinib hydrochloride, lapatinib, lenalidomide,&#xD;
      sorafenib, or SU011248 (sunitinib malate) that can be given to patients with advanced cancer.&#xD;
      The safety of each combination of the study drugs will be studied as well.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Study Drugs:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Valproic acid is designed for use as an anti-seizure medication. It is thought to also have&#xD;
      anticancer activity by activating (&quot;turning on&quot;) tumor-fighting genes, which may cause cancer&#xD;
      cell death.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Dasatinib is designed to change the function of genes. By changing the function of these&#xD;
      genes, it may prevent cancer from growing and spreading.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Erlotinib hydrochloride is designed to block the activity of a protein found on the surface&#xD;
      of many tumor cells that may control tumor growth and survival. This may stop tumors from&#xD;
      growing.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Lapatinib is designed to block the activity of certain molecules. These molecules play a part&#xD;
      in the growth of cancer cells and are particularly important for the growth of inflammatory&#xD;
      breast cancer tumors.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Lenalidomide is designed to change the body's immune system. It may also interfere with the&#xD;
      development of tiny blood vessels that help support tumor growth. Therefore, in theory, it&#xD;
      may decrease or prevent the growth of cancer cells.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Sorafenib is designed to block the function of a cancer protein as well as tumor blood-vessel&#xD;
      forming proteins.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Sunitinib malate is designed to block pathways that control important events such as the&#xD;
      growth of blood vessels that are essential for the growth of cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study Administration:&#xD;
&#xD;
      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, the study doctor will decide&#xD;
      which drug you will receive with valproic acid, based upon your particular disease. You will&#xD;
      then begin taking valproic acid plus either dasatinib, erlotinib hydrochloride, lapatinib,&#xD;
      lenalidomide, sorafenib, or sunitinib malate. One (1) cycle is either 21 or 28 days long,&#xD;
      depending on which study drug combination you receive.&#xD;
&#xD;
      You will take valproic acid by mouth once or twice a day for 7 days in a row. You will then&#xD;
      have a 7-day &quot;rest&quot; period from taking this drug.&#xD;
&#xD;
      You will also take either sorafenib or sunitinib malate by mouth once or twice a day&#xD;
      continuously for 21 days, or dasatinib, erlotinib hydrochloride, lapatinib, or lenalidomide&#xD;
      by mouth once or twice a day continuously for 28 days.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Depending on what stage of the study you are in, you will take the study drugs either once or&#xD;
      twice a day.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study Visits:&#xD;
&#xD;
      You will have the below tests/procedures at designated study visits.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Before each cycle (within 7 days of after your last dose)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  You will be have a complete physical exam.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Your performance status will be recorded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  You will be asked about any side effects you may be experiencing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  If you are able to become pregnant, you will have a blood (about 1 teaspoon) or urine&#xD;
           pregnancy test. To take part in this study, you must not be pregnant.&#xD;
&#xD;
      After the end of Cycles 2, 4 and 6, you will have a chest x-ray and either a CT scan, MRI&#xD;
      scan, or PET scan to check the status of the cancer. You will then have a chest x-ray and&#xD;
      either a CT scan, MRI scan, or PET scan after the end of every 3 cycles (Cycle 9, 12, 15, and&#xD;
      so on) to check the status of the cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Length of Study:&#xD;
&#xD;
      You will continue to take your study drug combination on this study, as long as the disease&#xD;
      does not get worse and you do not experience any intolerable side effects.&#xD;
&#xD;
      End-of-Study Visit:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Once you have stopped taking your study drug combination, you will come back for an&#xD;
      end-of-study visit to have the following tests/procedures performed:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  You will have a complete physical exam.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Your performance status will be recorded.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Blood may be drawn (about 1 tablespoon) for routine tests&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  You may have a CT scan, an MRI scan, or PET to check the status of the cancer, depending&#xD;
           on what the study doctor thinks is necessary.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Follow-Up:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The status of the disease will be followed-up for as long as possible after you complete this&#xD;
      study. Once every 8 weeks, you will either be contacted by phone and asked how you are&#xD;
      feeling (which should take about 5-10 minutes), or you will be asked to come to the clinic&#xD;
      for a routine visit. You will have a CT or MRI scan once every 12 weeks (or until another&#xD;
      anticancer therapy has been started) to check the status of the cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This is an investigational study. Each of the study drugs is FDA approved and commercially&#xD;
      available. The combination of valproic acid plus one of the other study drugs is&#xD;
      investigational in this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Valproic acid is FDA approved for the treatment of simple and complex absence seizure,&#xD;
      complex partial epileptic seizure, acute mania, and migraine prophylaxis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Dasatinib is FDA approved for the treatment of acute lymphoid leukemia (ALL) and chronic&#xD;
      myeloid leukemia (CML).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Erlotinib hydrochloride is FDA approved for the treatment of carcinoma of the pancreas and&#xD;
      non-small-cell lung cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Lapatinib is FDA approved for the treatment of breast cancer (inflammatory, relapsed, or&#xD;
      refractory) and metastatic breast cancer (HER2 overexpression).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Lenalidomide is FDA approved for the treatment of multiple myeloma and myelodysplastic&#xD;
      syndrome.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Sorafenib is FDA approved for the treatment of renal cell carcinoma. Sunitinib malate is FDA&#xD;
      approved for the treatment of gastrointestinal stromal tumors and renal cell carcinoma.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Up to 327 patients will take part in this study. All will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2007</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) as Determined by the Number of Participants With Dose Limiting Toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 28 (1 Cycle)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">204</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VN</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Valproic Acid + Sorafenib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Valproic Acid + Sunitinib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Valproic Acid + Dasatinib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Valproic Acid + Erlotinib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Valproic Acid + Lapatinib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Valproic Acid + Lenalidomide</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dasatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>50 mg by mouth (PO) Twice Daily for 28 Days Every 28 Days</description>
    <arm_group_label>VD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sprycel®</other_name>
    <other_name>BMS-354825</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Erlotinib</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg PO Daily for 28 Days Every 28 Days</description>
    <arm_group_label>VT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Erlotinib Hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>OSI-774</other_name>
    <other_name>Tarceva</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lapatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>1000 mg PO Daily for 28 Days Every 28 Days</description>
    <arm_group_label>VL</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GW572016</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>15 mg PO Daily for 28 Days Every 28 Days</description>
    <arm_group_label>VR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CC-5013</other_name>
    <other_name>Revlimid™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sorafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>400 mg PO Daily for 21 Days Every 28 Days</description>
    <arm_group_label>VN</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BAY 43-9006</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sunitinib</intervention_name>
    <description>25 mg PO Daily for 21 Days Every 28 Days</description>
    <arm_group_label>VS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sunitinib Malate</other_name>
    <other_name>SU011248</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Valproic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>40 mg/kg PO Daily for 7 Days, then 7 Days Off</description>
    <arm_group_label>VD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VN</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Depakene</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Patients must have advanced solid tumor: they have either a disease where there is no&#xD;
             established standard of care therapy or have failed one or more prior therapy. (for&#xD;
             all treatment arms)&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Patients must have ECOG performance status &lt; or = 2 (0-2). Patients &lt;/=10 years&#xD;
             modified Lansky scale &gt;/= 60. Patients &gt;10 to 18 years Karnovsky scale &gt;/= 60.(for all&#xD;
             treatment arms)&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below: Platelets &gt;&#xD;
             50,000/uL; Creatinine clearance &gt; 20mL/min (for all treatment arms); Total bilirubin &lt;&#xD;
             5 mg/dL (except for Lapatinib arm); ALT &lt;/= 6X ULN for Lapatinib arm only;&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. (cont. from above) Liver function criteria and dosing based on each individual drug:&#xD;
             Valproic acid - if ALT &gt;/= 6X ULN or T. Bili &gt;/= 3, then dose should be decreased by&#xD;
             50%; Sorafenib - If Child Pugh class A or B, no dose adjustment; if Child Pugh class&#xD;
             C, decrease dose by 50% (400 mg po daily max); Sunitinib - If ALT &gt;/= 6X ULN or T.&#xD;
             Bili &gt;/= 3 , decrease dose by 25% (37.5 mg po daily max);&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. (cont. from above) Erlotinib - If ALT &gt; 6X ULN or T. Bili &gt;/= 3 , decrease dose by 25%&#xD;
             (100 mg po daily max); Lapatinib - If ALT &gt; 3X ULN or T. Bili &gt; 2X ULN, decrease dose&#xD;
             by 60% (500-750 mg po daily max); Dasatinib - No dose adjustment needed; Lenalidomide&#xD;
             - No dose adjustment needed.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Patients or legal representative must be able to understand and be willing to sign an&#xD;
             IRB-approved written informed consent document. (for all treatment arms)&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception&#xD;
             prior to study entry, for the duration of study participation, and for 30 days after&#xD;
             the last dose. (for all treatment arms)&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active&#xD;
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure (NYHA Class III or IV), unstable&#xD;
             angina pectoris, symptomatic cardiac arrhythmia, active bleeding, active thrombosis,&#xD;
             or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study&#xD;
             requirements.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. History of allergic reactions to the study drugs or their analogs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Failure to recover from any prior surgery within 4 weeks of study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Any treatment specific for tumor control within 3 weeks of study drugs; or within 2&#xD;
             weeks if cytotoxic agents were given weekly (within 6 weeks for nitrosoureas or&#xD;
             mitomycin C), or within 4 half-lives for target agents with half lives and&#xD;
             pharmacodynamic effects lasting less than 5 days (that include but are not limited to&#xD;
             erlotinib, sorafenib, sunitinib, bortezomib, and other similar agents); or failure to&#xD;
             recover from the toxic effect of any therapy prior to study entry.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Study agents cannot be obtained for any reason since this study does not provide free&#xD;
             agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Any prior history of hypertensive crisis or hypertensive encephalopathy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Significant vascular disease (e.g., aortic aneurysm, aortic dissection) and&#xD;
             symptomatic peripheral vascular disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Evidence of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Major surgical procedure, open biopsy, or significant traumatic injury within 28 days&#xD;
             prior to study enrollment or anticipation of need for major surgical procedure during&#xD;
             the course of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Minor surgical procedure, excluding placement of a vascular access device, within 7&#xD;
             days prior to study enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. History of abdominal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation, or intra-abdominal abscess&#xD;
             within 6 months prior to study enrollment; and serious, non-healing wound, ulcer, or&#xD;
             bone fracture.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aung Naing, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>MD Anderson Cancer Center website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2012</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 2, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 2, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 3, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 16, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 16, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 18, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Solid Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Dasatinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Erlotinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Lapatinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Lenalidomide</keyword>
  <keyword>Sorafenib</keyword>
  <keyword>Erlotinib Hydrochloride</keyword>
  <keyword>Sunitinib Malate</keyword>
  <keyword>Sunitinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Valproic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>SU011248</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sunitinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erlotinib Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dasatinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lapatinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Valproic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

