<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00491218</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>07-12030</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00491218</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Addition of Cardiac CT to Exercise Treadmill Testing in the Evaluation of Angina</brief_title>
  <acronym>CT-EXTRA</acronym>
  <official_title>The Addition of Cardiac Computed Tomography to Exercise Treadmill Testing in the Evaluation of Angina</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Walter Reed Army Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Walter Reed Army Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The current outpatient evaluation for angina in low and intermediate risk patients typically&#xD;
      starts with a functional assessment for coronary ischemia. Exercise treadmill testing is&#xD;
      often selected as the initial diagnostic modality for coronary artery function. However,&#xD;
      exercise treadmill testing is limited by its moderate sensitivity and specificity, often&#xD;
      resulting in further cardiac resource utilization for patient risk stratification and&#xD;
      reassurance. With the advent of coronary multislice computed tomography (MSCT) angiography,&#xD;
      coronary artery anatomy can now be evaluated noninvasively. Despite its impressive&#xD;
      performance characteristics, the role of coronary MSCT angiography in the outpatient&#xD;
      evaluation of angina remains undefined.&#xD;
&#xD;
      CT-EXTRA compares the impact on patient safety and downstream resource utilization of a novel&#xD;
      initial diagnostic strategy employing the addition of coronary MSCT angiography to exercise&#xD;
      treadmill testing with a standard diagnostic strategy of exercise treadmill testing for the&#xD;
      ambulatory evaluation of low-intermediate risk patients with possible angina. The study is a&#xD;
      single center, prospective, non-blinded, randomized clinical trial. Men and women, age 18-70,&#xD;
      with a low to intermediate pretest probability of coronary artery disease who are referred&#xD;
      for an exercise treadmill test for angina are eligible. Subjects are randomized either to an&#xD;
      initial diagnostic strategy of exercise treadmill testing or exercise treadmill testing with&#xD;
      coronary MSCT angiography. Subsequent diagnostic testing and treatment are the discretion of&#xD;
      the referring physician. Subjects will be clinically followed for 24 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The clinical impact on patient safety and downstream clinical resource utilization of this&#xD;
      novel diagnostic strategy in which both coronary artery anatomy and function are initially&#xD;
      evaluated will be determined. The primary outcome is a composite endpoint consisting of&#xD;
      freedom from adverse cardiac events, further cardiac diagnostic testing, and future cardiac&#xD;
      clinical encounters. Secondary outcomes include the impact on the indiscriminate use of&#xD;
      coronary angiography, subject anxiety, depression, motivation for healthy behavioral change,&#xD;
      and satisfaction with diagnostic evaluation and use of antiplatelet and antilipid therapy.&#xD;
      Lastly, the cost effectiveness of the routine addition of coronary MSCT angiography in the&#xD;
      outpatient evaluation of possible angina will be determined.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CT-EXTRA is a randomized clinical trial that will compare a novel diagnostic strategy&#xD;
      employing the addition of coronary MSCT angiography to exercise treadmill testing with a&#xD;
      standard diagnostic strategy of exercise treadmill testing for the outpatient evaluation of&#xD;
      low-intermediate risk patients with possible angina. This is the first randomized clinical&#xD;
      trial that evaluates a diagnostic strategy for outpatient chest pain that incorporates a&#xD;
      noninvasive assessment of both coronary artery function and anatomy. CT- EXTRA will determine&#xD;
      whether coronary MSCT angiography adds any incremental prognostic value over exercise&#xD;
      treadmill testing alone for predicting future adverse cardiac events and reduces downstream&#xD;
      clinical resource utilization. This study will also evaluate the impact of this strategy on&#xD;
      the avoidance of unnecessary invasive coronary angiography, statin and aspirin prescription,&#xD;
      patient anxiety, satisfaction with the diagnostic approach, and motivation for healthy&#xD;
      behavioral change. Finally, an economic analysis will be performed to assess the differences&#xD;
      in overall healthcare costs between the diagnostic approaches. In today's managed&#xD;
      care-dominated paradigm, it is paramount that a new diagnostic modality such as coronary MSCT&#xD;
      angiography is not only clinically effective but cost effective as well. CT EXTRA will&#xD;
      provide critical information to clinicians and health care administrators on the clinical and&#xD;
      cost effectiveness of an initial diagnostic strategy employing routine coronary MSCT&#xD;
      angiography in the evaluation of patients for possible angina.&#xD;
&#xD;
      300 male and female military health care beneficiaries between the ages of 18-70, who are low&#xD;
      to intermediate risk for symptomatic coronary artery disease and are referred to the Walter&#xD;
      Reed Cardiology Clinic for an exercise treadmill test for the evaluation of possible angina&#xD;
      (chest pain or angina-equivalent).&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study is a randomized, non-blinded, prospective trial to be conducted in the Cardiology&#xD;
      clinic at Walter Reed Army Medical Center. Patients, age 18-70 years, referred to the&#xD;
      Cardiology clinic for an exercise treadmill test for an outpatient evaluation of possible&#xD;
      angina and are low-intermediate risk for symptomatic coronary artery disease, will be&#xD;
      eligible. All patients who meet the aforementioned inclusion/exclusion criteria will be&#xD;
      consented by an investigator and randomized from sealed envelopes to either &quot;mandatory&#xD;
      coronary MSCT angiography&quot; or &quot;no coronary MSCT angiography&quot; before initiation of exercise&#xD;
      treadmill testing. The randomization sequence will be generated using a sequence of&#xD;
      computer-generated random numbers. All consented subjects will complete surveys assessing&#xD;
      baseline depression using the Beck Depression Inventory, anxiety using the State and Trait&#xD;
      Anxiety Inventory, and motivation healthy behavioral change using the ladder scale&#xD;
      questionnaire. Completion of these three questionnaires are for research purposes and will&#xD;
      take approximately 15 minutes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Exercise Treadmill Testing&#xD;
&#xD;
      All subjects will undergo exercise treadmill testing as initially ordered by the referring&#xD;
      physician. All exercise treadmill testing will be conducted at the Cardiology clinic at&#xD;
      Walter Reed Army Medical Center according to standard clinic protocol. Testing will be&#xD;
      conducted by a health care professional (staff physician, fellow, or nurse practitioner) not&#xD;
      associated with the protocol. A Cardiology staff physician not affiliated with the protocol&#xD;
      will officially interpret each exercise treadmill test. Subjects will perform a graded&#xD;
      exercise treadmill test according to a Full Bruce protocol aimed at reaching 85% of the&#xD;
      maximal predicted heart rate for age. According to standard clinical practice, an exercise&#xD;
      treadmill test is considered positive if 0.1 mV of new horizontal or downsloping ST segment&#xD;
      depression or ST segment elevation 0.80 ms beyond the J point occurs during exercise or&#xD;
      recovery in two or more contiguous lead. A nondiagnostic test is defined as the absence of&#xD;
      ischemic electrical changes in the setting of reproduction of chest pain symptoms or when&#xD;
      peak heart rate is ≤85 % of the age-predicted maximal heart rate. An exercise treadmill test&#xD;
      is considered negative when &gt; 85% of the age-predicted maximal heart rate is achieved and&#xD;
      reproduction of anginal symptoms and development of electrocardiographic ischemic changes are&#xD;
      absent. In accordance with standard clinical practice, exercise treadmill testing will be&#xD;
      prematurely terminated in the event of lightheadedness, severe ST depression (&gt;2mm) or&#xD;
      elevation (&gt;1mm), ventricular or supraventricular arrhythmias, exaggerated blood pressure&#xD;
      increase (&gt;250 mm Hg systolic or &gt;120mm Hg diastolic) and a &gt;10mm Hg decrease in diastolic&#xD;
      blood pressure. Upon completion of exercise treadmill testing, the subject will be provided a&#xD;
      copy of the results and official interpretation of the exercise treadmill test for inclusion&#xD;
      in their medical records. A copy of the exercise treadmill test results will be kept in the&#xD;
      subject's file for the investigational team. Completion of an exercise treadmill test&#xD;
      generally takes about 25 minutes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Immediately Following Exercise Treadmill Testing&#xD;
&#xD;
      All consented subjects following exercise treadmill testing will undergo initial laboratory&#xD;
      assessment to include fasting lipid panel (LDL-C, HDL-C, and triglycerides), C-reactive&#xD;
      protein, fasting blood glucose, creatinine, thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) and urine&#xD;
      pregnancy test (for females). Approximately 15 mL (3 teaspoons) of blood will be drawn by the&#xD;
      central laboratory, the clinical laboratory at Walter Reed Army Medical Center. Excess blood&#xD;
      will be discarded by the central laboratory according to their standard protocol. All&#xD;
      laboratory values will be processed through this central laboratory.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subjects assigned to the &quot;no coronary MSCT angiography&quot; arm will follow up with their&#xD;
      referring physician for further evaluation. Additional selection of testing, consultation,&#xD;
      and choice of therapy is at the discretion of the referring physician. Coronary CT&#xD;
      angiography will not be available to this group of subjects. Otherwise, the protocol will not&#xD;
      predetermine the clinical diagnostic or treatment course for the subject. This approach will&#xD;
      simulate the previous standard of care for the evaluation of possible angina (prior to the&#xD;
      availability of coronary CT angiography in clinical practice). By excluding the option of&#xD;
      coronary CT angiography in this group, any possible incremental value of the test can more&#xD;
      accurately be assessed.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the event of a &quot;high risk&quot; exercise treadmill test, subjects will be offered inpatient&#xD;
      admission. High risk tests will include any of the following: the occurrence of sustained&#xD;
      ventricular tachycardia, syncope, a high risk Duke treadmill score (&gt;-10), limiting angina in&#xD;
      stage 1 of the Full Bruce protocol, &gt; 2 mm ST depression in 3 or more leads in stage 1 of the&#xD;
      Full Bruce protocol. Subjects with such high risk tests who are assigned to the &quot;no coronary&#xD;
      MSCT angiography&quot; arm will be encouraged to undergo invasive coronary angiography. Subjects&#xD;
      assigned to the &quot;mandatory coronary MSCT angiography&quot; arm will undergo coronary MSCT&#xD;
      angiography in an expedited manner. This will be followed by invasive coronary angiography,&#xD;
      if warranted, 48 hours later. Because the protocol excludes subjects deemed as having a high&#xD;
      pretest probability of obstructive coronary artery disease, the potential for this occurrence&#xD;
      should be minimized.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients assigned to the &quot;mandatory coronary MSCT angiography&quot; arm will be scheduled for&#xD;
      coronary MSCT angiography on an outpatient basis. The procedure for coronary MSCT angiography&#xD;
      is described below. After completion of coronary MSCT angiography, the results will be&#xD;
      provided to the referring physician. Additional selection of testing, consultation, or&#xD;
      therapy is at the discretion of the referring physician. The protocol will not predetermine&#xD;
      the clinical course for the subject following coronary MSCT angiography.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Coronary MSCT angiography&#xD;
&#xD;
      Pre-procedural Medications: In order to obtain high quality computed tomographic images with&#xD;
      minimal motion artifacts, the goal heart rate is ≤ 65 beats per minute. This usually requires&#xD;
      administration of beta-blocker medications before image acquisition. In addition, subjects&#xD;
      with baseline low rates (&gt; 65bpm) generally need a reduced dose of beta-blockers to blunt&#xD;
      increases in rate during the MSCT scan due to anxiety and or reflex responses to contrast.&#xD;
      The dose of initial oral beta-blocker will be determined based on resting heart rate at the&#xD;
      time of exercise treadmill testing. For subjects with a baseline heart rate above 65bpm and&#xD;
      blood pressure above 100/50, 100-150mg of short acting metoprolol will be prescribed by the&#xD;
      investigator. Subjects will be instructed to ingest this medication approximately one hour&#xD;
      before the scheduled outpatient MSCT scan. For subjects with heart rates above 50bpm and less&#xD;
      than 65bpm and blood pressure above 100/50, 25-50 mg of oral short acting metoprolol will be&#xD;
      prescribed by the investigator. Subjects will be instructed to ingest this medication&#xD;
      approximately one hour before the scheduled outpatient MSCT scan. For subjects with a&#xD;
      baseline heart rate &lt; 50bpm, no metoprolol will be prescribed.&#xD;
&#xD;
      On the day of the MSCT scan and upon arrival to the Radiology Department, the subject will&#xD;
      receive a peripheral upper extremity intravenous catheter, placed by a certified nurse in the&#xD;
      Radiology Department. The subject's baseline blood pressure and heart rate will be recorded.&#xD;
      For subjects whose heart rate remains ≥ 65 beats per minute and blood pressure ≥ 100/50,&#xD;
      intravenous metoprolol (5 mg aliquots every 2-5 minutes under close observation and&#xD;
      continuous telemetric monitoring, up to 40 mg total) will be administered by a cardiology&#xD;
      staff or fellow. Once satisfactory heart rate and blood pressure stability are established,&#xD;
      subjects will undergo MSCT testing as listed below. However, if target heart rate is not&#xD;
      achievable by this protocol, this is not cause for exclusion from the study, since&#xD;
      feasibility and accuracy studies have shown that diagnostic scans can be obtained in many&#xD;
      patients with higher heart rates with advanced scanners. Nitroglycerin, a coronary&#xD;
      vasodilator, will be administered to all subjects (0.8 mg sublingually) approximately 1&#xD;
      minute before initiation of the MSCT scan to optimize image quality. Subjects will be queried&#xD;
      regarding the recent use (within the previous 72 hours) of medications for erectile&#xD;
      dysfunction (Cialis, Levitra and Viagra) on the day of the MCST scan since these drugs can&#xD;
      interact with nitroglycerin to cause a potential life-threatening hypotensive effect. On the&#xD;
      day of the scheduled MSCT scan, subjects who admit to have taken Cialis within the past 72&#xD;
      hours or Levitra / Viagra within the past 48 hours will not be allowed to undergo coronary&#xD;
      MSCT angiography and will be rescheduled. Subjects will be instructed to withhold these&#xD;
      medications for at least 3 days before the scheduled scan.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All female subjects who are randomized to the MSCT arm will be required to wear a&#xD;
      radioprotective bismuth shield during the actual MSCT scan. This radioprotective brassiere&#xD;
      (Cone Instruments Inc, Solen, Ohio) composed of neoprene and bismuth trioxide has been&#xD;
      studied in 16 slice CT scans and has been shown to reduce breast radiation exposure by&#xD;
      approximately 40%.25 The bra will be placed directly over both breasts of the female subjects&#xD;
      by either a female nurse or technician in the Radiology Department. The adhesive strips on&#xD;
      the undersurface of these radioprotective bras will prevent any slippage during the actual&#xD;
      scan. Depending on the bust size of the subject, either a medium or large bra will be&#xD;
      employed for best fit. Each bra is intended for single patient use only and will be discarded&#xD;
      after each study. The effect of these bismuth shields on image interpretation is unknown. If&#xD;
      images of the coronary arteries are deemed to be unevaluable, women 40 years and younger will&#xD;
      be excluded from participation in the study. In this event, only women greater than the age&#xD;
      of 40 years will be enrolled and radioprotective shields will not be used.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subject follow-up&#xD;
&#xD;
      After completion of initial testing (exercise treadmill test +/- MSCT angiography), subjects&#xD;
      will be returned to the referring physicians who will dictate further clinical management.&#xD;
      The results of the exercise treadmill testing and coronary MSCT angiography (if applicable)&#xD;
      will be provided to the referring physician. Additional selection of testing, consultation,&#xD;
      and choice of therapy is at the discretion of the referring physician. For subjects assigned&#xD;
      to the &quot;no coronary MSCT angiography&quot; arm, the referring provider will be instructed not to&#xD;
      make MSCT an available option for these subjects if further testing is deemed appropriate.&#xD;
      Otherwise, the protocol will not predetermine the clinical diagnostic or treatment course for&#xD;
      the subject. This approach should simulate actual clinical practice and the previous standard&#xD;
      of care (prior to availability of MSCT) and will allow assessment of downstream clinical&#xD;
      resource utilization in an unbiased fashion.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subjects will be followed for a total of two years. During that time, the following factors&#xD;
      will be evaluated:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Status of the presenting syndrome including final diagnosis&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Number of cardiac visits to an outpatient physician or emergency department (ED) because&#xD;
           of chest pain/anginal equivalent&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Cardiac hospitalizations for chest pain syndrome/angina equivalent&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Requirement for additional cardiac diagnostic testing, namely further stress testing&#xD;
           (nuclear, MRI, echocardiography) and/or cardiac catheterization&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Need for additional radiographic testing for incidental findings found on coronary MSCT&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Need for coronary revascularization procedures&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Unstable angina, myocardial infarction or cardiac death. Myocardial infarction is&#xD;
           defined as a cardiac event requiring admission to the hospital with the development of&#xD;
           cardiac enzyme level elevation. Unstable angina is defined by accelerating anginal&#xD;
           symptoms with or without ischemic electrocardiographic changes requiring hospital&#xD;
           admission and coronary revascularization. Death will be attributed to a cardiac origin&#xD;
           in the case of documented significant arrhythmia and/or cardiac arrest, congestive heart&#xD;
           failure, or myocardial infarction. Moreover, any unexplained death that occurs suddenly&#xD;
           out of the hospital will be ascribed a cardiac cause.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Prescription of antilipid and antiplatelet therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
      These factors will be determined by electronic medical record review (CHCS-II) and telephonic&#xD;
      interview with the subjects every 6 months for a total of 2 years. Any visit to an outpatient&#xD;
      clinic or ED and any inpatient admission will be categorized as &quot;cardiac&quot; if the presenting&#xD;
      complaint is chest pain or identical to the original complaint which prompted the initial&#xD;
      exercise treadmill test referral.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subjects will return to the clinic at 12 months to complete questionnaires to assess changes&#xD;
      in depression, anxiety and motivation for healthy behavioral change using the Beck Depression&#xD;
      Inventory(BDI), State and Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) and ladder scale respectively.&#xD;
      Subjects will also be surveyed about their current perception of chest pain as cardiac or&#xD;
      noncardiac and the utility of their index cardiovascular evaluation, to provide insight into&#xD;
      the etiology of their symptoms.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Endpoints Primary The primary outcome will be a composite endpoint consisting of adverse&#xD;
      cardiac events and cardiac resource utilization. Specifically, this will include the&#xD;
      occurrence of adverse cardiac events (cardiac death, myocardial infarction, unstable angina,&#xD;
      coronary revascularization), utilization of additional diagnostic testing for initial&#xD;
      complaint, and the occurrence of future clinical outpatient/inpatient/ED encounters for the&#xD;
      initial cardiac complaint.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Secondary&#xD;
&#xD;
      Secondary endpoints will include:&#xD;
&#xD;
      1. Occurrence of adverse cardiac events (cardiac death, myocardial infarction, unstable&#xD;
      angina, coronary revascularization)&#xD;
&#xD;
      . 2. Need for subsequent cardiac diagnostic testing for the initial complaint of&#xD;
      angina/angina equivalent 3. Occurrence of future clinical outpatient/inpatient/ED encounters&#xD;
      for the initial cardiac complaint 4. Avoidance of unnecessary cardiac catheterizations 5.&#xD;
      Change in motivation for healthy behavioral change, as assessed by the ladder motivational&#xD;
      scale 6. Change in subject anxiety, as assessed by the State and Trait Anxiety Inventory.&#xD;
&#xD;
      7. Change in subject depression, as assessed by the Beck Depression Inventory. 8.&#xD;
      Satisfaction with diagnostic evaluation for initial complaint&#xD;
&#xD;
      Predefined Analyses&#xD;
&#xD;
      In addition to the primary and secondary outcomes, there will be two predefined analyses&#xD;
      related to these outcomes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      1. Cost Efficiency Analysis, measured as total direct per-patient cost incurred for each&#xD;
      diagnostic strategy as related to the primary outcome. The direct per -patient cost in the&#xD;
      evaluation of outpatient angina will be calculated by adding the following components and&#xD;
      dividing by the number of patients tested:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. cost of all initial tests of each diagnostic arm (exercise treadmill testing +/-&#xD;
           coronary MSCT angiography&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. cost of any additional cardiac diagnostic tests deemed necessary by the referring&#xD;
           provider after the completion of the initial diagnostic strategy arms for evaluation of&#xD;
           the initial complaint&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. cost of any subsequent inpatient/outpatient/ED evaluations for the initial cardiac&#xD;
           complaint over the following 24 months&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. cost of any subsequent radiographic testing needed for incidental findings found on MSCT&#xD;
           over the following 24 months The cost of the different diagnostic tests utilized&#xD;
           (coronary MSCT angiography, exercise treadmill testing, myocardial perfusion testing,&#xD;
           exercise echocardiography, coronary angiography, and other radiographic tests) and&#xD;
           clinical encounters (inpatient admissions, ED evaluations, outpatient evaluations) will&#xD;
           be estimated from current Medicare reimbursement rates.&#xD;
&#xD;
      2. Statin and aspirin use, measured as the change in the prevalence of statin and aspirin use&#xD;
      among subjects in each diagnostic arm.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>June 2007</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Natural History</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Angina</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Chest pain or anginal equivalent symptoms possibly suggestive of symptomatic coronary&#xD;
             artery disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Low-intermediate risk (&lt;75% pretest probability) for symptomatic coronary artery&#xD;
             disease on basis of age, sex, and quality of reported symptom as classified by the&#xD;
             Diamond and Forrester scheme6&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Referred to Walter Reed Cardiology clinic for an exercise treadmill test as the&#xD;
             initial diagnostic test of choice&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Age equal to or greater than 18 years and less than 70 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Ability to provide informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Abnormal baseline electrographic changes that would preclude proper diagnosis of&#xD;
             ischemia including preexcitation (Wolff-Parkinson-White) syndrome, a paced ventricular&#xD;
             rhythm, more than 1 mm of ST depression at rest, complete left bundle branch block, or&#xD;
             criteria for left ventricular hypertrophy, even if they have less than 1 mm of&#xD;
             baseline ST depression&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Presence of known pre-existing coronary artery disease (known prior myocardial&#xD;
             infarction, EKG evidence of prior infarction, prior angiographic evidence of&#xD;
             significant coronary artery disease, history of prior coronary revascularization).&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Previous outpatient or inpatient evaluation for coronary artery disease to include&#xD;
             exercise treadmill testing, stress echocardiography or nuclear myocardial perfusion&#xD;
             studies within the last three years.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Presence of signs or symptoms that are clearly compatible with non-cardiac chest pain,&#xD;
             including musculoskeletal, gastrointestinal or neuropathic causes.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Renal insufficiency (creatinine &gt;1.5mg/dl) or renal failure requiring dialysis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Baseline heart rate &gt; 100bpm, atrial fibrillation or other markedly irregular rhythm&#xD;
             (frequent ectopy, multifocal atrial tachycardia) on baseline ECG.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Pregnancy or unknown pregnancy status.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Known allergy to iodinated contrast.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Inability to tolerate beta-blocking drugs, including patients with reactive airways&#xD;
             disease requiring maintenance inhaled bronchodilators or steroids, complete heart&#xD;
             block or second-degree atrioventricular block.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Patients with hyperthyroidism including Grave's disease and toxic multinodular goiter&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Computed tomography imaging, or iodinated contrast administration over 50 ml, within&#xD;
             the past 48 hours.&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. Unwillingness to withhold ingestion of metformin or commonly used erectile dysfunction&#xD;
             medications (Viagra, Cialis, Levitra) for 48 hours prior to MSCT scan.&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Previous history of radiation therapy to the thorax.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick J Devine, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>WRAMC Cardiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patrick J Devine, MD</last_name>
    <phone>2027829855</phone>
    <email>patrick.devine@na.amedd.army.mil</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Allen J Taylor, MD</last_name>
    <phone>2027822887</phone>
    <email>allen.taylor@na.amedd.army.mil</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Walter Reed Army Medical Center Cardiology Service</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20307</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patrick J Devine, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2007</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 22, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 26, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 26, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>impact of cardiac computed tomography on outpatient angina evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>downstream resource utilization</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Angina Pectoris</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

