<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00496795</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Ethics committee 079.06</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NSD 14918</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>14918</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00496795</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Predictors for Response to Dose-dense Docetaxel and Epirubicin Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>DDP</acronym>
  <official_title>Molecular Markers Predictive Response to Dose Dense Chemotherapy With Epirubicin and Docetaxel in Sequences for Locally Advanced Breast Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Bergen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Haukeland University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Bergen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Molecular markers predicting response to dose dense chemotherapy with epirubicin and&#xD;
      docetaxel in sequence for locally advanced breast cancer&#xD;
&#xD;
      Protocol summary.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Principal Investigator Hans P. Eikesdal, Professor, Dept. of Oncology, Haukeland University&#xD;
      Hospital &amp; Dept. of Clinical Science, University of Bergen&#xD;
&#xD;
      Project leader: Professor Per Eystein Lønning, Dept. of Oncology, Haukeland University&#xD;
      Hospital &amp; Dept. of Clinical Science, University of Bergen&#xD;
&#xD;
      Collaborators. Dept of Surgery - Responsible: Turid Aas, Consultant Surgeon&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants. Dept of Oncology Stephanie Geisler, Consultant Oncologist Jurgen Geisler,&#xD;
      Consultant Oncologist&#xD;
&#xD;
      Type of Study Phase II, Translational research&#xD;
&#xD;
      Scientific aims: Addressing factors predicting response to dose intensive epirubicin followed&#xD;
      by docetaxel sequential therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
      Treatment regimen: epirubicin 60 mg/m2 on a 2 weekly basis x 4 followed by docetaxel 100&#xD;
      mg/m2 2-weekly x 4.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients: Breast cancer patients below 65 years of age suffering from large (&gt;4 cm largest&#xD;
      diameter, non-inflammatory and / or N2-N3) primary breast cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
      .&#xD;
&#xD;
      Clinical aim: Assessing responsiveness to this dose intensive regimen.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Number of patients to be enrolled: 60 - 100&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim The scientific aim of this study is to explore mechanisms of resistance to chemotherapy&#xD;
      in breast cancer. To do so, we explore molecular parameters predicting response to&#xD;
      chemotherapy administered prior to local therapy in large, primary breast cancers.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Background Neoadjuvant (primary medical) therapy has got wide acceptance as primary therapy&#xD;
      in breast cancer. In addition, this treatment provides an optimal setting studying the&#xD;
      mechanisms of drug resistance in human cancers.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Considering chemotherapy for primary breast cancer treatment, contemporary trend has been to&#xD;
      treat these tumors more aggressively. High-dose therapy involving stem cell support is not&#xD;
      advocated, as this has not been shown to improve long-term survival in early breast cancer.&#xD;
      However, the attitude in general has been toward a more aggressive approach within the frame&#xD;
      of &quot;conventional&quot; therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Based on theoretical modeling, an alternative approach, &quot;dose-dense&quot; therapy, has been&#xD;
      advocated. Recently, that concept was brought to the test in two adjuvant trials. Thus,&#xD;
      Citron et al applying doxorubicin, paclitaxel and cyclofosfamide revealed an improved outcome&#xD;
      for dose-dense (2-weekly) administration compared to regular 3-weekly scheduling. In&#xD;
      contrast, the German GEPARDUO study reported doxorubicin plus cyclophosphamide and docetaxel,&#xD;
      given in sequence on a 3-weekly basis (8 cycles), to be superior to doxorubicin and docetaxel&#xD;
      given in concert on a 2-weekly basis for 4 cycles. However, the doses administered&#xD;
      (doxorubicin 50 versus 60 mg/m2; docetaxel 75 versus 100 mg/m2) was unequal, meaning total&#xD;
      drug dose exposure differed between the two treatment arms. While more data are warranted, a&#xD;
      reasonable interpretation of available data suggest sequential administration of different&#xD;
      compounds in a dose-density approach to be a suitable regimen provided adequate total doses&#xD;
      are given.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Rationale for regimen Considering anthracyclines, most regimens today combine either&#xD;
      epirubicin or doxorubicin in concert with 5-fluorouracil and cyclophosphamide. However, based&#xD;
      on the evidence in the literature, it is not clear what the contribution of 5-FU or&#xD;
      cyclophosphamide is to the effectiveness of such regimens, in particular not when a taxane is&#xD;
      administered in sequence or concert. Thus, the NSABP-group has abandoned use of 5-FU from&#xD;
      their adjuvant regimen. Considering cyclophosphamide, this compound seems to add to the&#xD;
      carcinogenetic effect of anthracyclines enhancing the risk of secondary leukemia, while the&#xD;
      contribution to the antitumor efficacy of the regimen remains uncertain. The taxanes are&#xD;
      known to have significant antitumor effects in breast cancer when administered as&#xD;
      monotherapy. Considering docetaxel, the dose generally advocated for monotherapy is 100&#xD;
      mg/m2, while a dose of 75mg/m2 is recommended for combined use. Thus, the potential exists&#xD;
      that the dose for combined use may be sub-optimal in some patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Justification for a sequential approach is further supported by studies in metastatic breast&#xD;
      cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Scientific aims While many mechanisms of resistance have been identified in experimental&#xD;
      systems, we have little knowledge what may be the cause of drug resistance in human cancers.&#xD;
      The factors so far identified that have been found associated with resistance to chemotherapy&#xD;
      in breast cancer are amplification of HER-2 / Topo-II and mutations affecting TP53.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Recently, several groups have explored responsiveness to chemotherapy using mRNA microarrays.&#xD;
      While these studies consistently identified different gene profiles correlating to&#xD;
      responsiveness to different regimens, the predictive value was too low for clinical&#xD;
      application. Moreover, the results did not add to our understanding of the biological&#xD;
      mechanisms causing drug resistance. In contrast, studies exploring different forms of cancer&#xD;
      have started to reveal specific gene alterations, in particular affecting pathways of DNA&#xD;
      damage repair or apoptosis in relation to drug resistance. Thus, our primary aim is to&#xD;
      explore potential gene disturbances based on functional hypotheses.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A major issue identifying mechanisms of drug resistance is to explore different compounds on&#xD;
      a monodrug basis. Clinically, the major reason for combining or administering sequentially an&#xD;
      anthracycline and a taxane is the efficacy of each compound combined with a significant lack&#xD;
      of cross-resistance. Administered as a combined schedule, this limits the possibility of&#xD;
      identifying the mechanisms of resistance / sensitivity to each compound individually.&#xD;
      Provided that a sequential regimen provides the same efficacy as a combined schedule, such an&#xD;
      approach is justified ethically. Thus, for a patient given 2 and 3 drugs in concert, the&#xD;
      potential may be they respond to one drug only, while having the toxicity of the other&#xD;
      compounds. In case of non-responsiveness to a single compound, this may be exchanged for an&#xD;
      alternative treatment option. This contrasts the possibilities provided in the adjuvant&#xD;
      setting. In adjuvant therapy, there is no way by which we may assess the response to&#xD;
      individual drugs; thus the different compounds have to administer in concert.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Based on what is said above, we consider sequential dose-dense treatment using epirubicin and&#xD;
      docetaxel sequentially to be a feasible treatment option.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Treatment regimen Each patient will receive 4 cycles of epirubicin 60 mg/m2 given at 2 weekly&#xD;
      intervals together with G-CSF. Thereafter, docetaxel 100 mg/ m2 will be given at 2 weekly&#xD;
      intervals for 4 cycles. Patients revealing positivity for HER2 status will have trastuzumab&#xD;
      (Herceptin) implemented together with docetaxel but not during anthracycline treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Staging at baseline&#xD;
&#xD;
      After given informed consent, patients will be staged as follows:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  MRI of both breasts&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Chest X-ray&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Liver ultrasound (in case metastases are suspected or verified; to be followed by CT and&#xD;
           / or MRI confirmation)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Skeletal scintigram. Any positive findings to be confirmed by subsequent X-ray / CT and&#xD;
           / or MRI&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  ECG&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  LVEF (Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction)&#xD;
&#xD;
      Response evaluation Response will be evaluated based on clinical examination and MRI, each&#xD;
      assessment to be done separately.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Clinical examination will be performed prior to commencing therapy (before surgical biopsy)&#xD;
      and subsequently at 4, 6 and 8 weeks on therapy. Response will be classified according to the&#xD;
      common &quot;RECIST&quot; criteria. An important exception is to be made. As argued in a previous&#xD;
      protocol, we consider the RECIST definition of &quot;progressive disease&quot; as a 20% increase in the&#xD;
      sum of the largest tumor diameters to be too liberal with respect to large primary tumors.&#xD;
      Based on experience in our clinic, we believe the definition of progressive disease as an&#xD;
      increase of &gt; 25% in the product of the largest tumor diameter and its perpendicular (the&#xD;
      previous common UICC criteria) to be a more suitable definition, protecting patients from&#xD;
      undergoing deterioration of their clinical condition. This is in accordance to our previous&#xD;
      experience.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In case of &quot;progressive disease&quot; at any stage during epirubicin treatment, the patient will&#xD;
      terminate epirubicin immediately and go ahead with docetaxel treatment. In case of&#xD;
      progressive disease on docetaxel treatment, further therapy is left to the physician's&#xD;
      discretion.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Considering MRI assessment, this should be performed prior to commencing therapy, in the&#xD;
      interval following the 4th cycle of epirubicin (prior to commencing docetaxel) and after the&#xD;
      4th cycle of docetaxel, prior to surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Tissue sampling&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Each patient will undergo a surgical biopsy prior to commencing treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. A Tru-cut biopsy should be obtained 24 hours after administration of the first&#xD;
           epirubicin cycle to assess &quot;immediate&quot; alterations in response to cytotoxic damage.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Immediately prior to commencing treatment with docetaxel, a third sample (this time a&#xD;
           Tru-Cut biopsy) is obtained for snap-freezing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. A Tru-cut biopsy should be obtained 24 hours after administration of the first docetaxel&#xD;
           cycle to assess &quot;immediate&quot; alterations in response to cytotoxic damage.&#xD;
&#xD;
        5. Finally, tumor tissue is collected and snap-frozen at surgery following docetaxel&#xD;
           therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Bone marrow aspiration A single unilateral bone marrow aspiration is performed prior to&#xD;
      commencing chemotherapy treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study Endpoint&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Primary endpoint is to correlate molecular parameters to objective response to each of&#xD;
           the 2 regimens applied.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Secondary endpoint are&#xD;
&#xD;
           : - to correlate molecular parameters to relapse-free and overall survival&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  to identify and explore characteristics of epithelial and mesenchymal stem cells&#xD;
           isolated in tumor tissue and bone marrow&#xD;
&#xD;
      Surgery While many centers practice breast conservative surgery for tumors successfully&#xD;
      downstaged by primary medical treatment, in general we have applied a conservative approach,&#xD;
      advocating mastectomy. However, downstaging for limited surgery is not a primary or secondary&#xD;
      endpoint of this study. In general, we will advocate mastectomy also for patients with a&#xD;
      clinical complete response. However, this practice may change based on contemporary results&#xD;
      from other centers, and the protocol allow limited surgery at the physicians discretion in&#xD;
      individual patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Laboratory Investigations The area of molecular biology is rapidly developing with respect to&#xD;
      biological knowledge as well as technical analytical methods. Thus, it is not possible to&#xD;
      predict upfront which genes may be of particular interest in 5 years from know; neither is it&#xD;
      possible to foresee completely which laboratory methods will be available. Our aim is to&#xD;
      explore potential genetic alterations explaining the mechanisms of drug resistance. While it&#xD;
      is not possible to predict in detail, the aim of the study and all analysis to be conducted&#xD;
      should aim at this major goal.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Number of patients to be enrolled The study is an exploratory translational study. Thus, we&#xD;
      do not know the number of patients expected to achieve a clinical or pathological complete&#xD;
      response. Currently, on average 20 patients are referred to our Department for a diagnosis of&#xD;
      locally advanced breast cancer on an annual basis; including patients with tumors measuring&#xD;
      between 4 and 5 cm in diameter, we estimate the total number may be somewhere between 30 and&#xD;
      40 patients per year. From this cohort, we estimate an average number of 20 patients to be&#xD;
      enrolled in the study on an annual basis. Our aim is to recruit 100 patients with a minimum&#xD;
      of 60.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Publication Our aim is to publish the results from this study in peer-reviewed international&#xD;
      journals with contributors from the clinic and laboratory as authors.&#xD;
&#xD;
      References; from the Trial Administrator upon request.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Sequential epirubicin and docetaxel</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To correlate molecular parameters to objective response to each of the 2 regimens applied.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>To correlate molecular parameters to objective response to sequential dose-dense therapy with epirubicin followed by docetaxel in primary locally advanced breast cancer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To correlate molecular parameters to relapse-free and overall survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To identify and explore characteristics of epithelial and mesenchymal stem cells isolated in tumor tissue and bone marrow</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Stage III Breast Cancer AJCC V7</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>epirubicin/docetaxel sequential</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Epirubicin/docetaxel sequential, i.e. one arm study with Epirubicin 4 cycles 60 mg/m2 q2w, followed by docetaxel 4 cycles, 100 mg/m2 q2w. Each course with pegfilgrastim.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>epirubicin/docetaxel sequential</intervention_name>
    <description>Epirubicin 60 mg/m2, q2w 4 cycles. Followed by docetaxel 100 mg/m2 q2w 4 cycles</description>
    <arm_group_label>epirubicin/docetaxel sequential</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Farmorubicin (Pfizer)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Primary breast cancer &gt;4cm in diameter and / or lymph node status N2-3.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age 65 years or younger&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  &quot;Limited&quot; distant metastases allowed, but patients with massive distant metastases&#xD;
             should be excluded&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willing to participate in the study&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Known allergy toward any of the cytotoxic compounds to be administered (epirubicin and&#xD;
             doxorubicin)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Liver enzymes &gt; 2 times upper normal limit or bilirubin &gt; 3 times upper normal limit&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other medical conditions making them unfit for dose-dense therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cardiac insufficiency; for patients not to receive trastuzumab, decision whether to&#xD;
             exclude such patients will be at the physicians discretion. Considering patients with&#xD;
             HER-2 positive tumors who should have trastuzumab, exclusion criteria will be&#xD;
             according to the NBCG (Norwegian Breast Cancer Group) general guidelines&#xD;
             (www.NBCG.net).&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Per E Lonning, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Section of Oncology, Institute of Medicine, University of Bergen, Haukeland University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dept of Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bergen</city>
        <zip>N-5021</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 3, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 24, 2022</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 24, 2022</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2022</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Bergen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hans Petter Eikesdal</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast cancer, chemoresistance, predictive markers.</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epirubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>March 16, 2006</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/95/NCT00496795/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>August 23, 2006</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/95/NCT00496795/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

