<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00494728</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2006-0351</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02097</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01MH076776-01A1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01MH087692</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00494728</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Smoking Cessation for Depressed Smokers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Smoking Cessation Intervention for Depressed Smokers: Treatment Development</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objectives:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Primary Aim:&#xD;
&#xD;
      To conduct a preliminary randomized trial in smokers with current recurrent major depressive&#xD;
      disorder (MDD), current MDD with a single episode of 2 years or more, and current dysthymia&#xD;
      comparing combined cognitive behavioral analysis system of psychotherapy (CBASP) and standard&#xD;
      smoking cessation treatment (ST) (CBASP/ST) to combined Health Education and ST treatment&#xD;
      (HE/ST) to:&#xD;
&#xD;
      1. Examine the effects of CBASP/ST on both short and long-term point prevalence abstinence&#xD;
&#xD;
      Secondary Aims:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. To test the hypothesis that depressed smokers in the CBASP/ST treatment will experience&#xD;
           greater decreases in depressive symptoms from baseline to each of our follow-up&#xD;
           assessment points, compared to depressed smokers in the HE/ST treatment, and;&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. That depressed smokers in the CBASP/ST treatment will experience greater improvements in&#xD;
           psychosocial functioning from baseline to follow-up assessment points, compared to&#xD;
           depressed smokers in the ST treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. To evaluate between subject neurophysiological predictors of abstinence at 3 and 6&#xD;
           months, and:&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. To evaluate within-subject changes in neurophysiological responses to emotional and&#xD;
           smoking-related stimuli across treatment sessions, and the relation of these changes to&#xD;
           abstinence and depressive symptoms at end of treatment, and 3- and 6-months.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During the session today, you will be asked to complete 8-9 questionnaires about smoking&#xD;
      history, health status, current medications you are taking, your confidence in quitting&#xD;
      smoking, symptoms of nicotine dependence and withdrawal, symptoms of depression, negative&#xD;
      experiences during childhood, and your thoughts and feelings about work and the quality of&#xD;
      your relationships with others. In total, the questionnaires should take about 30-45 minutes&#xD;
      to complete. You will also blow into a machine that measures the amount of carbon monoxide in&#xD;
      your blood (a breath test). This visit may last 1 ½ to 2 hours.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Following the session today, you will be provided with information on the results of the&#xD;
      screening tests you completed at BCM to see whether you have a current depressive disorder or&#xD;
      any other psychiatric disorders. You will be provided with an opportunity to discuss this&#xD;
      information with the investigators.&#xD;
&#xD;
      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be randomly assigned (as&#xD;
      in the toss of a coin) to one of 2 groups. If you are assigned to Group 1, you will receive&#xD;
      counseling to help develop behavioral coping skills that will help with situations where you&#xD;
      are tempted to smoke more (which are considered high-risk situations), combined with mood&#xD;
      management counseling to help you develop interpersonal (communication) coping skills to help&#xD;
      with depression and negative moods that may affect your ability to quit smoking. If you are&#xD;
      assigned to Group 2, you will receive counseling to help develop behavioral coping skills&#xD;
      that will help with situations where you are tempted to smoke more (which are considered&#xD;
      high-risk situations), combined with education on the health-related effects of smoking.&#xD;
      Participants in both groups will receive nicotine patches.&#xD;
&#xD;
      During the 5 weeks after the visit, you will have six (6) 70-minute counseling sessions.&#xD;
&#xD;
      If you are in Group 1, you will receive information on how cigarette smoking is a learned&#xD;
      habit and a physical addiction and how the habit can be unlearned. You will receive&#xD;
      counseling to help you identify situations that are high risk for smoking and to help you&#xD;
      develop behavioral coping plans to decrease the chances of smoking in those situations. You&#xD;
      will be encouraged to use these skills between sessions. You will also receive counseling to&#xD;
      help you identify situations where you interact with others that may cause negative moods.&#xD;
      You will be taught interpersonal coping skills to help decrease depression and negative moods&#xD;
      and to increase your ability to quit smoking and not start again. You will be given homework&#xD;
      assignments that will help you practice these skills between sessions.&#xD;
&#xD;
      If you are in Group 2, you will receive information on how cigarette smoking is a learned&#xD;
      habit and a physical addiction and how the habit can be unlearned. You will also receive&#xD;
      counseling to help you identify situations that are high risk for smoking and to help you&#xD;
      develop behavioral coping plans to decrease the chances of smoking in those situations. You&#xD;
      will be encouraged to use these skills between sessions. You will also receive information&#xD;
      about health issues related to smoking and you will have the opportunity to discuss this&#xD;
      information with your counselor.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Before or after each of the counseling sessions, you will fill out 2-3 questionnaires on mood&#xD;
      and smoking behavior and have a breath test. You will be asked to fill out 5-6 questionnaires&#xD;
      on withdrawal symptoms, confidence in quitting smoking, your thoughts and feelings about&#xD;
      work, and the quality of your relationships with others. In total, it will should about 30-45&#xD;
      minutes to fill out the questionnaires at each visit. Each of these visits will take a total&#xD;
      of about 1 hour and 40 minutes to 1 hour and 55 minutes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The date to quit smoking will be scheduled for about 5 weeks after your first visit. As part&#xD;
      of your counseling sessions, you will be provided with counseling to help you develop a plan&#xD;
      to quit and to set a quit date. You will be given the nicotine patches starting on the quit&#xD;
      date. You will be asked to wear the nicotine patches on the upper area of your body for 24&#xD;
      hours each day.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Following the quit date, you will attend six (6) more 70-minute counseling sessions. You will&#xD;
      also attend 2 additional visits at 3 months and 6 months from your quit date. At each of&#xD;
      these visits, you will be asked to fill out 2-3 questionnaires on mood and smoking behavior&#xD;
      and to provide a breath test to measure the amount of carbon monoxide in your blood. You will&#xD;
      be asked questions about symptoms you may be having and the medications you are taking. You&#xD;
      will be asked to fill out 5-6 questionnaires on withdrawal symptoms, confidence in quitting&#xD;
      smoking, and the quality of your relationships with others at some of these visits. If you&#xD;
      are unable to attend your end-of-treatment, 3-month or 6-month visits, you may be asked to&#xD;
      provide a saliva sample to measure the amount of cotinine in your blood, a chemical produced&#xD;
      by the breakdown of nicotine during smoking. This sample will be taken using a dental roll&#xD;
      (cotton swab) placed in the mouth for several minutes to absorb saliva. At the 3-month and&#xD;
      6-month follow-up visits, you will be also asked questions about any current problems with&#xD;
      depression.&#xD;
&#xD;
      At the last treatment visit (Visit 12) and at the 3-month and 6-month follow-up visits, if&#xD;
      you are still smoking, you will be provided with information on where you can receive&#xD;
      additional help to quit smoking. If you continue to have a current depressive disorder, you&#xD;
      will be provided with additional information about this disorder, and you will be provided&#xD;
      with information on where you can receive treatment for your depressive disorder. The&#xD;
      investigators will provide a referral for treatment if you wish to receive treatment for your&#xD;
      depressive disorder at that time.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Each of the counseling visits will be videotaped. In addition, the first visit and the visits&#xD;
      at 3 and 6 months may also be videotaped. The videotapes will be erased within 1 year after&#xD;
      you complete this study. The videotapes will be used to help the investigators make sure that&#xD;
      the counselors are following the correct therapy procedures and may be used in future studies&#xD;
      to help the investigators better understand the mood management and health education&#xD;
      treatments. No one but the study investigators, study staff, and consultants (those who&#xD;
      review and rate how well the study therapists follow therapy procedures) will be allowed to&#xD;
      view the tapes. Your identity will be kept strictly confidential.&#xD;
&#xD;
      So that the study researchers can keep in contact with you throughout the study and over the&#xD;
      long period of time between your end of treatment visit and the 3- and 6- month follow-up&#xD;
      visits, you will be asked at the baseline visit to provide the name and address of 2 contacts&#xD;
      (family members/friends) that you feel confident would have updated contact information on&#xD;
      you.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Your participation in this study will end after the 6-month follow-up visit.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This is an investigational study. The nicotine patches are FDA approved for use in adults age&#xD;
      18 and older and commercially available. Up to 202 people will take part in this study. All&#xD;
      will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Abstinence Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately each 12 weeks following end of treatment (about 6 weeks)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">202</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CBASP + ST</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cognitive Behavioral Analysis System of Psychotherapy (CBASP) + Smoking Cessation Treatment (ST)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ST</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Smoking Cessation Treatment (ST)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smoking Cessation Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>12 60-minute individual sessions of standard smoking cessation treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBASP + ST</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ST</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nicotine Replacement Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>21 mg patch for 4 weeks; 14 mg patch for 2 weeks; 7 mg patch for 2 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBASP + ST</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ST</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CBASP</intervention_name>
    <description>Individual counseling sessions where taught/develop interpersonal and behavioral coping skills to help decrease depression and negative moods, and to increase ability to quit smoking.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBASP + ST</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cognitive Behavioral Analysis System of Psychotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Currently meeting DSM-IV criteria for major depressive disorder, recurrent; or major&#xD;
             depressive disorder, recurrent, in partial remission; or major depressive disorder,&#xD;
             single episode with a duration of 2 years or more; or; dysthymic disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Score greater than or equal to 8 on the PHQ at baseline&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Age greater than or equal to 16&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Smoking greater than or equal to 5 cigarettes per day&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Willing to set a quit date within 6 weeks of baseline&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. English speaking and have a telephone&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Willing to attend all sessions&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Willing to provide informed consent and agree to all assessments and study procedures&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. History of psychotic or bipolar disorder&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Current psychotherapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Current use of antidepressant&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Current principal DSM-IV Axis I disorder other than unipolar depression or nicotine&#xD;
             dependence&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Involvement in any smoking cessation activities&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Current use of nicotine replacement therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Known health or other complications that would adversely affect attendance&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Severe levels of depressive symptoms, vegetative symptoms, and/or symptoms related to&#xD;
             secondary psychiatric disorders that place participant at risk for harm or require&#xD;
             immediate treatment&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Currently at severe or extreme risk of suicide or moderate risk with resolved plans&#xD;
             and preparation&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Medical contraindications for use of nicotine patch, including uncontrolled heart&#xD;
             disease, history of severe hypersensitivity to nicotine replacement products, or&#xD;
             currently pregnant or lactating&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. 11) History of current medical condition, or any other factor that, in the judgment of&#xD;
             the principal investigator, would likely preclude completion of study requirements.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jan Blalock, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 2, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 6, 2022</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 6, 2022</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 8, 2022</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Behavioral Analysis System of Psychotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking Cessation Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine Replacement Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine Patch</keyword>
  <keyword>CBASP</keyword>
  <keyword>MDD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nicotine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

