<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00499356</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DK55909</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00499356</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Shear and Pressure Reducing Insoles for the Diabetic Foot</brief_title>
  <acronym>GlideSoft</acronym>
  <official_title>Shear and Pressure Reducing Insoles for the Diabetic Foot</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Diabetica Solutions Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Diabetica Solutions Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We evaluated the feasibility of the GlideSoft™ novel insole to reduce pressure and shear&#xD;
      forces on the foot. No commercially available insoles are designed to reduce shear. Although&#xD;
      insurance providers spend millions on diabetics' therapeutic insoles, there is no scientific&#xD;
      data about shear or pressure reduction. We will evaluate the optimal bonded materials from&#xD;
      Phase I compared to the Glidesoft™ design using the same combination of viscoelastic&#xD;
      materials. We evaluate 2 patient groups of 150 patients per arm (300 total) in an 18 month&#xD;
      trial. The control group patient arm wore a traditional bonded insole whereas another the&#xD;
      second arm receive the GlideSoft™. At baseline, and at the end of the 18 month trial, in-shoe&#xD;
      gait lab and in vitro biomechanical parameters measured pressure, shear, and material&#xD;
      properties as these changed with wear. This Phase II eighteen (18) month clinical trial&#xD;
      evaluated the effectiveness of ShearSole™ reducing the incidence of diabetic ulcers. The&#xD;
      overall study hypothesis was that GlideSoft™ provides significant shear reduction as compared&#xD;
      to traditional insoles without sacrificing pressure reduction characteristics or durability.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. To evaluate the efficacy of a shear reducing shoe insole (GlideSoft) in reducing the&#xD;
           incidence of diabetic foot pathology among high-risk patients. We studied the&#xD;
           effectiveness of a shear reducing shoe insole to prevent foot ulcers in high-risk&#xD;
           diabetics with sensory neuropathy, a history of a foot ulcer or a history of a partial&#xD;
           foot amputation. The study comprised two treatment arms. The first group received&#xD;
           standard therapy involving standard therapeutic shoes and insoles, patient education and&#xD;
           regular foot evaluations by a physician. The second group received the same standard&#xD;
           therapy, but instead of the standard insoles patients used the GlideSoft - a novel shear&#xD;
           reducing insole. As determined in the Phase I study, the GlideSoft dramatically reduced&#xD;
           shear forces compared to standard insoles, while performing equally well in reducing&#xD;
           compressive forces. Patients were followed for 18 months. The primary study outcome was&#xD;
           for incident foot ulcers. Our hypothesis was that patients who use the GlideSoft will&#xD;
           have fewer ulcers and that these ulcers will be less severe compared to patients&#xD;
           evaluated in the Standard Insole Group.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. To evaluate changes in pressure and shear reducing capabilities of the two. To evaluate&#xD;
           changes in pressure and shear reducing capabilities of the GlideSoft and standard&#xD;
           insoles over the duration of use.&#xD;
&#xD;
           We measured in-shoe pressures and in-vitro shear forces at the foot-insole interface at&#xD;
           the beginning of the study and after patients wore the insole for four months or one&#xD;
           &quot;standard cycle of wear&quot;. We used the Novel Electronics, Inc. Pedar in-shoe pressure&#xD;
           system to measure the interface between the foot and insole and the Shear Force Tester&#xD;
           (see Phase I report) to evaluate shear forces. We expected that the GlideSoft would&#xD;
           significantly reduce shear forces and provide equivalent reduction in vertical forces at&#xD;
           both the day 0 evaluation and day 120 evaluations.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. To evaluate patient perceived benefits, satisfaction, and compliance with the 2. To&#xD;
           evaluate changes in pressure and shear reducing capabilities of the GlideSoft and&#xD;
           standard insoles over the duration of use.&#xD;
&#xD;
      We measured in-shoe pressures and in-vitro shear forces at the foot-insole interface at the&#xD;
      beginning of the study and after patients wore the insole for four months or one &quot;standard&#xD;
      cycle of wear&quot;. We used the Novel Electronics, Inc. Pedar in-shoe pressure system to measure&#xD;
      the interface between the foot and insole and the Shear Force Tester (see Phase I report) to&#xD;
      evaluate shear forces. We expected that the GlideSoft would significantly reduce shear forces&#xD;
      and provide equivalent reduction in vertical forces at both the day 0 evaluation and day 120&#xD;
      evaluations.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incident foot ulcers</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">299</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Ulceration</condition>
  <condition>Amputation</condition>
  <condition>Foot Deformity</condition>
  <condition>Neuropathy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pressure reducing insole</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GlideSoft®</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diagnosis of diabetes by WHO criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ability to provide informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  18-80 years of age&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with open ulcers or open amputation sites&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active Charcot arthropathy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Severe peripheral vascular disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active foot infection&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Dementia&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Impaired cognitive function&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of drug or alcohol abuse within one year of the study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other conditions based on the PI's clinical judgment&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin R Higgins, DPM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kevin R. Higgins, DPM</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78217</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lavery LA, Higgins KR, Lanctot DR, Constantinides GP, Zamorano RG, Athanasiou KA, Armstrong DG, Agrawal CM. Preventing diabetic foot ulcer recurrence in high-risk patients: use of temperature monitoring as a self-assessment tool. Diabetes Care. 2007 Jan;30(1):14-20. doi: 10.2337/dc06-1600.</citation>
    <PMID>17192326</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2007</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 10, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 10, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 10, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>friction</keyword>
  <keyword>pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>insole</keyword>
  <keyword>ulcer</keyword>
  <keyword>prevention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Foot Deformities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Deformities, Congenital</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Foot</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

