<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00497666</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>346147Rosi</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00497666</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Association Between Rosiglitazone Use and Clinical Course of Diabetic Nephropathy: Population-Based Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Retrospective Study Evaluating the Association Between Rosiglitazone Use and Clinical Course of Diabetic Nephropathy: Population-Based Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assaf-Harofeh Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assaf-Harofeh Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recent data show that Rosiglitazone treatment can reduce proteinuria in diabetic patients.&#xD;
      However, currently there are no trials that examine the effects of Rosiglitazone on kidney&#xD;
      disease progression, that is, doubling of serum creatinine or time to onset of end-stage&#xD;
      renal disease, in patients with diabetic nephropathy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      We decided to study retrospectively the possible association between rosiglitazone use and&#xD;
      clinical course of diabetic nephropathy, including rate of deterioration of renal function,&#xD;
      appearance and progression of microalbuminuria/proteinuria, survival and acceptance to renal&#xD;
      replacement therapy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background Type 2 diabetes mellitus is a public health concern, and projections of its future&#xD;
      effect are alarming. According to the World Health Organization, diabetes affects more than&#xD;
      170 million people worldwide, and this number will rise to 370 million by 2030 [1]. About one&#xD;
      third of those affected will eventually have progressive deterioration of renal function [2,&#xD;
      3]. The first clinical sign of renal dysfunction in patients with diabetes is generally&#xD;
      microalbuminuria (a sign of endothelial dysfunction that is not necessarily confined to the&#xD;
      kidney)[4], which develops in 2 to 5 percent of patients per year [5,6]. In type 2 diabetes,&#xD;
      unlike type 1 diabetes [7], microalbuminuria is seldom reversible [8], but, instead,&#xD;
      progresses to overt proteinuria in 20 to 40 percent of patients.[9,10]. In 10 to 50 percent&#xD;
      of patients with proteinuria, chronic kidney disease develops that ultimately requires&#xD;
      dialysis or transplantation [11,12,13]. Forty to 50 percent of patients with type 2 diabetes&#xD;
      who have microalbuminuria eventually die of cardiovascular disease [14,15]; this is three&#xD;
      times as high a rate of death from cardiac causes as among patients who have diabetes but&#xD;
      have no evidence of renal disease [6].&#xD;
&#xD;
      In patients with diabetes and renal disease, lowering blood pressure and the levels of&#xD;
      urinary albumin is effective in reducing the risk of end-stage renal disease as well as that&#xD;
      of myocardial infarction, heart failure, and stroke [16]. Angiotensin-converting-enzyme (ACE)&#xD;
      inhibitors or angiotensin II antagonists appear to be the most effective renoprotective and&#xD;
      antihypertensive agents [11, 12, 17-21] . Treatment with the ACE inhibitor enalapril over a&#xD;
      period of six years decreased the incidence of microalbuminuria in patients with type 2&#xD;
      diabetes who were normotensive and not obese [22].&#xD;
&#xD;
      Preventing (or delaying) the development of microalbuminuria is a key treatment goal for&#xD;
      renoprotection [23] and, possibly, for cardioprotection [4]. Recent clinical trials suggested&#xD;
      that inhibition of the renin-angiotensin system may actually prevent nephropathy. The post&#xD;
      hoc analyses of the reduction in hypertension in the Heart Outcomes Prevention Evaluation&#xD;
      study [18] and in the Losartan Intervention for Endpoint study [24] found a lower incidence&#xD;
      of overt nephropathy in subjects with type 2 diabetes who received therapy that inhibited the&#xD;
      renin-angiotensin system than in controls.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Recent BENEDICT study indicates that treatment with trandolapril with or without verapamil&#xD;
      significantly reduces the incidence of microalbuminuria in patients with type 2 diabetes and&#xD;
      normal urinary albumin excretion, as compared with placebo [25]. Trandolapril alone also&#xD;
      appeared to decrease the incidence of microalbuminuria, whereas verapamil had no effect.&#xD;
      Thiseffect of trandolapril plus verapamil and trandolapril alone in preventing&#xD;
      microalbuminuria exceeded expectations based on changes in blood pressure alone.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Unfortunately, even with the appropriate use of available therapy, diabetic nephropathy still&#xD;
      remains the leading cause of ESRD [2]. More effective strategies are needed in order to&#xD;
      retard the progression of diabetic nephropathy and to reduce cardiovascular mortality in&#xD;
      diabetic population.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Thiazolidinediones (TZDs) represent a class of compounds currently used for the treatment of&#xD;
      type 2 DM that exert their hypoglycemic properties through reduction of IR [26]. These agents&#xD;
      act by stimulating a certain type of nuclear receptor, called peroxisome&#xD;
      proliferator-activated receptor gamma (PPAR ). Such receptors are abundant in adipose tissue&#xD;
      cells, but they are also present in various other cell types, such as vascular smooth muscle&#xD;
      cells, macrophages, vascular endothelial cells, colon epithelial cells, as well as renal&#xD;
      glomerular and tubular cells. Through transcriptional regulation of various genes, PPAR&#xD;
      receptors play an important role in adipocyte differentiation and lipid and carbohydrate&#xD;
      metabolism [26]. Apart from improving glycemic control in patients with type 2 DM, several&#xD;
      lines of evidence support the notion that TZDs have beneficial effects on other components of&#xD;
      the metabolic syndrome, such as blood pressure (BP) lowering, triglyceride reduction,&#xD;
      high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol elevation, redistribution of body fat away from the&#xD;
      central compartment, decrease of C-reactive protein and plasminogen activator inhibitor -1&#xD;
      (PAI-1) levels, and others [26].&#xD;
&#xD;
      Additionally, several animal studies demonstrate that TZDs also reduce urine albumin or&#xD;
      protein excretion and protect against injury to the kidney [27]. Moreover, experimental&#xD;
      studies exposed numerous actions of TZDs in the kidney that could explain a possible&#xD;
      renoprotective effect [27-30]. Our recent study on diabetic rats showed that rosiglitazone&#xD;
      exerts its anti-inflammatory renoprotective effect by inhibition of mesangial cells&#xD;
      proliferation, downregulation of apoptosis and blunting responsiveness to angiotensin-2 [31].&#xD;
&#xD;
      Human study also report significant reductions in UAE among patients with type 2 diabetes by&#xD;
      rosiglitazone [32].&#xD;
&#xD;
      Another human study was part of a cardiac safety study where rosiglitazone 4 mg b.i.d. was&#xD;
      compared to glyburide in 121 patients for 52 weeks [32]. After 28 weeks of treatment, both&#xD;
      groups had significant reductions in ACR of about 30%, but after 52 weeks only rosiglitazone&#xD;
      group continued to demonstrate a significant ACR reduction. This finding suggests that&#xD;
      duration of follow-up is an important variable in assessing the effect of TZDs [32].&#xD;
&#xD;
      Overall, the above data clearly show that TZD treatment can reduce UAE. However, it should be&#xD;
      emphasized that currently there are no trials that examine the effects of TZDs on kidney&#xD;
      disease progression, that is, doubling of serum creatinine or time to onset of end-stage&#xD;
      renal disease, in patients with diabetic nephropathy [33]. Such studies are needed in order&#xD;
      to provide the best evidence for a renoprotective effect of TZDs.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Based on this data, we decided to study the possible association between rosiglitazone use&#xD;
      and clinical course of diabetic nephropathy, including rate of deterioration of renal&#xD;
      function, appearance and progression of microalbuminuria/proteinuria, survival and acceptance&#xD;
      to renal replacement therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Methods. Study population. The study is planned as retrospective cohort study using automated&#xD;
      clinical data of Central Region Clalit Health Survices from 1999 until 2007.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Inclusion criteria: 1. Diagnosis of Diabetes Mellitus Type II; 2. Treatment With Oral&#xD;
      hypoglycemics; 3. Availability of Baseline and follow up clinical data Exclusion criteria: 1.&#xD;
      Insulin Therapy at baseline; 2. Malignancy Patients will be divided into 2 groups:&#xD;
      rosiglitazone-treated group and non-treated with rosiglitazone ( control) group.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Baseline Data ( separately for two groups). Number of patients. Gender Race/etnicity Age&#xD;
      Weight, BMI Duration of DM Diabetic microangiopathy: retinopathy, neuropathy, nephropathy&#xD;
      Medications for DM Creatinine Microalbumin Proteinuria HbA1c% Hb Ca, P, PTH Albumin&#xD;
      Hypertension: BP Cholesterol, LDL, TG Smoking: current, previous Alcohol consumption&#xD;
      Comorbidites: HTN, CAD, CHF, PVD, Hypercholesterolemia, CVA/TIA Drugs: ACEi, ARBs, CCB,&#xD;
      beta-blockers, statines, antiplatlate Use of nephrotoxic medications: NSAIDs&#xD;
&#xD;
      Follow up data Duration of rosiglitasone therapy/follow up Use of contrast media during study&#xD;
&#xD;
      Every year data:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Creatinine eGFR Microalbumin Proteinuria HbA1C% Start of insulin therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
      Events:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Hospitalisation (cause) Death (cause) ESRD/Dialysis Reported CHF MI CVA Angiography PVD&#xD;
      Amputation References&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. World Health Organization. The Diabetes Program 2004. (at&#xD;
           http://www.who.int/diabetes/en/.)&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Remuzzi G, Schieppati A, Ruggenenti P. Nephropathy in patients with type 2 diabetes. N&#xD;
           Engl J Med 2002;346:1145-1151.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Ruggenenti P, Remuzzi G. The diagnosis of renal involvement in non-insulin-dependent&#xD;
           diabetes mellitus. Curr Opin Nephrol Hypertens 1997;6:141-145.&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. Ritz E. Albuminuria and vascular damage -- the vicious twins. N Engl J Med&#xD;
           2003;348:2349-2352.&#xD;
&#xD;
        5. Gall MA, Hougaard P, Borch-Johnsen K, Parving HH. Risk factors for development of&#xD;
           incipient and overt diabetic nephropathy in patients with non-insulin dependent diabetes&#xD;
           mellitus: prospective, observational study. BMJ 1997;314:783-788.&#xD;
&#xD;
        6. Adler AI, Stevens RJ, Manley SE, Bilous RW, Cull CA, Holman RR. Development and&#xD;
           progression of nephropathy in type 2 diabetes: the United Kingdom Prospective Diabetes&#xD;
           Study (UKPDS 64). Kidney Int 2003;63:225-232.&#xD;
&#xD;
        7. Perkins BA, Ficociello LH, Silva KH, Finkelstein DM, Warram JH, Krolewski AS. Regression&#xD;
           of microalbuminuria in type 1 diabetes. N Engl J Med 2003;348:2285-2293&#xD;
&#xD;
        8. Parving HH, Lehnert H, Brochner-Mortensen J, Gomis R, Andersen S, Arner P. The effect of&#xD;
           irbesartan on the development of diabetic nephropathy in patients with type 2 diabetes.&#xD;
           N Engl J Med 2001;345:870-878&#xD;
&#xD;
        9. Mogensen CE. Microalbuminuria predicts clinical proteinuria and early mortality in&#xD;
           maturity-onset diabetes. N Engl J Med 1984;310:356-360&#xD;
&#xD;
       10. Nelson RG, Knowler WC, Pettitt DJ, Saad MF, Charles MA, Bennett PH. Assessing risk of&#xD;
           overt nephropathy in diabetic patients from albumin excretion in untimed urine&#xD;
           specimens. Arch Intern Med 1991;151:1761-1765.&#xD;
&#xD;
       11. Brenner BM, Cooper ME, de Zeeuw D, et al. Effects of losartan on renal and&#xD;
           cardiovascular outcomes in patients with type 2 diabetes and nephropathy. N Engl J Med&#xD;
           2001;345:861-869.&#xD;
&#xD;
       12. Lewis EJ, Hunsicker LG, Clarke WR, et al. Renoprotective effect of the angiotensin&#xD;
           receptor antagonist irbesartan in patients with nephropathy due to type 2 diabetes. N&#xD;
           Engl J Med 2001;345:851-860.&#xD;
&#xD;
       13. Nelson RG, Newman JM, Knowler WC, et al. Incidence of end-stage renal disease in type 2&#xD;
           (non-insulin-dependent) diabetes mellitus in Pima Indians. Diabetologia 1988;31:730-736&#xD;
&#xD;
       14. Eurich DT, Majumdar SR, Tsuyuki RT, Johnson JA. Reduced mortality associated with the&#xD;
           use of ACE inhibitors in patients with type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care 2004;27:1330-1334.&#xD;
&#xD;
       15. Parving HH, Mauer M, Ritz E. Diabetic nephropathy. In: Brenner BM, ed. Brenner &amp;&#xD;
           Rector's The kidney. 7th ed. Vol. 2. Philadelphia: Saunders, 2004:1777-818.&#xD;
&#xD;
       16. Dinneen SF, Gerstein HC. The association of microalbuminuria and mortality in&#xD;
           non-insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus: a systematic overview of the literature. Arch&#xD;
           Intern Med 1997;157:1413-1418&#xD;
&#xD;
       17. Parving HH, Jacobsen P, Rossing K, Smidt UM, Hommel E, Rossing P. Benefits of long-term&#xD;
           antihypertensive treatment on prognosis in diabetic nephropathy. Kidney Int&#xD;
           1996;49:1778-1782&#xD;
&#xD;
       18. Heart Outcomes Prevention Evaluation (HOPE) Study Investigators. Effects of ramipril on&#xD;
           cardiovascular and microvascular outcomes in people with diabetes melllitus: results of&#xD;
           the HOPE study and MICRO-HOPE substudy. Lancet 2000;355:253-259. [Erratum, Lancet&#xD;
           2000;356:860.]&#xD;
&#xD;
       19. Viberti G, Mogensen CE, Groop LC, Pauls JF. Effect of captopril on progression to&#xD;
           clinical proteinuria in patients with insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus and&#xD;
           microalbuminuria. JAMA 1994;271:275-279.&#xD;
&#xD;
       20. Ravid M, Lang R, Rachmani R, Lishner M. Long-term renoprotective effect of&#xD;
           angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibition in non-insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus: a&#xD;
           7-year follow-up study. Arch Intern Med 1996;156:286-289&#xD;
&#xD;
       21. Lewis EJ, Hunsicker LG, Bain RF, Rohde RD. The effect of angiotensin-converting-enzyme&#xD;
           inhibition on diabetic nephropathy. N Engl J Med 1993;329:1456-1462. [Erratum, N Engl J&#xD;
           Med 1993;330:152.&#xD;
&#xD;
       22. Ravid M, Brosh D, Levi Z, Bar-Dayan Y, Ravid D, Rachmani R. Use of enalapril to&#xD;
           attenuate decline in renal function in normotensive, normoalbuminuric patients with type&#xD;
           2 diabetes mellitus: a randomized, controlled trial. Ann Intern Med 1998;128:982-988&#xD;
&#xD;
       23. UK Prospective Diabetes Study (UKPDS) Group. Intensive blood-glucose control with&#xD;
           sulphonylureas or insulin compared with conventional treatment and risk of complications&#xD;
           in patients with type 2 diabetes (UKPDS 33). Lancet 1998;352:837-853. [Erratum, Lancet&#xD;
           1999;354:602.]&#xD;
&#xD;
       24. Lindholm LH, Ibsen H, Dahlof B, et al. Cardiovascular morbidity and mortality in&#xD;
           patients with diabetes in the Losartan Intervention For Endpoint reduction in&#xD;
           hypertension study (LIFE): a randomized trial against atenolol. Lancet&#xD;
           2002;359:1004-1010.&#xD;
&#xD;
       25. Ruggenenti P, Fassi A, Ilieva A, et al. Preventing Microalbuminuria in Type 2 Diabetes.&#xD;
           N Engl J Med 2004; 351: 1941-51.&#xD;
&#xD;
       26. Lebovitz HE, Banerji MA. Insulin resistance and its treatment by thiazolidinediones.&#xD;
           Recent Prog Horm Res 2001; 56: 265-294.&#xD;
&#xD;
       27. Haneda M, Koya D, Kikkawa R. Cellular mechanisms in the development and progression of&#xD;
           diabetic nephropathy: activation of the DAG-PKC-ERK pathway. Am J Kidney Dis 2001; 38:&#xD;
           S178-S181&#xD;
&#xD;
       28. Asano T, Wakisaka M, Yoshinari M et al. Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor&#xD;
           gamma1 (PPARgamma1) expresses in rat mesangial cells and PPARgamma agonists modulate its&#xD;
           differentiation. Biochim Biophys Acta 2000; 1497: 148-154&#xD;
&#xD;
       29. Xiong Z, Huang H, Li J et al. Anti-inflammatory effect of PPARgamma in cultured human&#xD;
           mesangial cells. Renal Failure 2004; 26: 497-505.&#xD;
&#xD;
       30. Gumieniczek A. Effect of the new thiazolidinedione-pioglitazone on the development of&#xD;
           oxidative stress in liver and kidney of diabetic rabbits. Life Sci 2003; 74: 553-562&#xD;
&#xD;
       31. Weissgarten J, Berman S, Efrati S, et al. Apoptosis and proliferation of cultured&#xD;
           mesangial cell isolated from kidneys of rosiglitasone-treated pregnant diabetic rats.&#xD;
           Nephrol Dial Transplant 2006; 21: 1198-204&#xD;
&#xD;
       32. Bakris G, Viberti G, Weston WM et al. Rosiglitazone reduces urinary albumin excretion in&#xD;
           type 2 diabetes. J Hum Hypertens 2003; 17: 7-12.&#xD;
&#xD;
       33. Sarafidis P, Bakris G. Protection of the kidney by thiazolidinediones: An assessment&#xD;
           from bench to bedside. Kidney Int 2006; 70: 1223-1233.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2007</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Diabetic Nephropathy</condition>
  <condition>Renal Protection</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rosiglitasone (retrospective observation)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Diagnosis of Diabetes Mellitus Type II&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Treatment With Oral hypoglycemics&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Availability of Baseline and follow up clinical data&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Insulin Therapy at baseline&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Malignancy&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leonid S Feldman</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nephrology Division, Assaf Harofeh Medical Center, Zerifin,</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leonid S Feldman</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assaf-Harofeh Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leonid S Feldman</last_name>
    <phone>+972-8-9779383</phone>
    <phone_ext>9383</phone_ext>
    <email>leonidf@asaf.health.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clalit Health Cervices, Central District</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zerifin,</city>
        <zip>70300</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leonid S Feldman</last_name>
      <phone>+972-8-9779383</phone>
      <phone_ext>9383</phone_ext>
      <email>leonidf@asaf.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shlomo Vinker, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2007</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 6, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 6, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 9, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 6, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 6, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 9, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetic nephropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>renal protection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Nephropathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

