<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00494819</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>9461700916</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NSC 94-2815-C-002-177-H</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00494819</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validity of ADHD Subtypes Using Neuropsychological Measure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Discriminate Validity of ADHD Subtypes Using Neuropsychological Test</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Taiwan University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD), characterized by inattention,&#xD;
      hyperactivity, and impulsivity, is among the most common neuropsychiatric disorders worldwide&#xD;
      (5-10% at school age) and in Taiwan (7.5%). The DSM-IV ADHD consists of three subtypes:&#xD;
      predominantly Inattentive (ADHD-I), predominantly Hyperactivity/Impulsivity (ADHD-H), and&#xD;
      Combined subtypes (ADHD-C). Although the DSM-IV field trials indicate that the current&#xD;
      subtypes differ significantly on variables such as age of onset, gender ratio, and level of&#xD;
      social and academic impairment, little has been addressed whether the DSM-IV subtypes differ&#xD;
      neuropsychologically. Numerous researches have proved that stimulants (methylphenidate is the&#xD;
      only stimulant in Taiwan) are the most effective medication in treating ADHD. Although the&#xD;
      efficacy of methylphenidate on behavioral measures has been established in Taiwan, there is&#xD;
      no information about neuropsychological measures.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Specific Aims:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. to validate ADHD subtype by neuropsychological measures; and&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. to investigate the efficacy of methylphenidate on the improvement of executive&#xD;
           functioning among children with ADHD.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subjects and Methods: Participants will consist of 20 children with ADHD-C, 20 with ADHD-I,&#xD;
      10 with ADHD-H and 50 controls without ADHD in the age range of 7 to 10. The measures include&#xD;
      the psychiatric interviews (Chinese K-SADS-E), neuropsychological tests (WISC-III,&#xD;
      Cancellation Test, Digit Span, Trail Making Test, CPT, Circle Tracing Test),&#xD;
      self-administered rating scale (SNAP-IV), and investigator administered assessment (CGI and&#xD;
      Behavior Observation Ratings).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Anticipated Results: We anticipated that children in the ADHD and non-ADHD group will perform&#xD;
      differently on the neuropsychological tests with more deficits in neuropsychological&#xD;
      functions in the ADHD group. Also, we expected that methylphenidate will improve the&#xD;
      performance on the neuropsychological tests and reduce the behavioral symptoms of ADHD&#xD;
      children. Subtypes difference in the neuropsychological functions is also expected.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND AND SIGNIFICANCE Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) is among the most&#xD;
      common impairing neuropsychiatric disorder worldwide among children and adolescents with the&#xD;
      prevalence of DSM-IV ADHD in the range of 5-10% in Western countries (Faraone et al., 2003)&#xD;
      and 7.5% in Taiwan (Gau et al., 2005) with the ratio of boys to girls as 3-8:1. The&#xD;
      significance of ADHD in clinical practice and research is not only in its high prevalence but&#xD;
      also in the impairments it brings about in neurocognitive function, academic performance, and&#xD;
      social adjustment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The DSM-IV ADHD is comprised with three subtypes, predominantly Inattentive (ADHD-I),&#xD;
      predominantly Hyperactivity/Impulsivity (ADHD-H), and Combined subtype (ADHD-C). The DSM-IV&#xD;
      field trials indicate that the current subtypes differ significantly on variables such as age&#xD;
      of onset, gender ratio, and level of social and academic impairment (Lahey et al., 1994).&#xD;
      Although previous researches have suggested that neuropsychological deficits in ADHD are&#xD;
      associated with frontal-subcortical regions (Castellanos, 1997), few studies have addressed&#xD;
      whether the DSM-IV subtypes differ neuropsychologically with inconsistent results (Nigg et&#xD;
      al, 2002).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Many studies have demonstrated the efficacy of stimulants in treating ADHD. Among them,&#xD;
      methylphenidate (MPH) was the widely used and has been rigorously studied (eg. Spencer et&#xD;
      al., 2005; Stein et al., 2005; Wilens et al., 2005). MPH is also the only stimulant&#xD;
      medication for the treatment of ADHD in Taiwan; it has been proved to reduce significantly&#xD;
      the symptoms of ADHD, and to increase self regulation, learning motivation, academic&#xD;
      performance, and interpersonal ability. Meanwhile, its efficacy was also observed in the&#xD;
      significant improvement of neuropsychological functioning (e.g., Konrad et al., 2004).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Given that there is no conclusive finding in the neuropsychological function among ADHD&#xD;
      subtypes and little is known about the neuropsychological deficits in three ADHD subtypes in&#xD;
      the Chinese population, the present study aims to validate ADHD diagnosis and ADHD subtypes&#xD;
      by executive functioning measures. Although the efficacy of methylphenidate on behavioral&#xD;
      measures has been established in Taiwan, there is no information about neuropsychological&#xD;
      measures.&#xD;
&#xD;
      SPECIFIC AIMS:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. to validate ADHD subtype by neuropsychological measures; and&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. to investigate the efficacy of methylphenidate on the improvement of executive&#xD;
           functioning among children with ADHD.&#xD;
&#xD;
      HYPOTHESIS:&#xD;
&#xD;
      We hypothesize that ADHD and ADHD subtype can be validated by the measures of executive&#xD;
      function and the methylphenidate not only decrease ADHD core symptoms but also improve&#xD;
      executive functions among children with ADHD.&#xD;
&#xD;
      METHOD Participants The sample will consist of 50 child psychiatric patients with ADHD (20&#xD;
      ADHD-I, 20 ADHD-C and 10 ADHD-H) and 50 normal controls, aged 7-10. The inclusion criteria&#xD;
      are patients who have clinically diagnosis of DSM-IV ADHD confirmed by the K-SADS-E, are aged&#xD;
      7-10, and have IQ &gt; 80; and who and whose parents consent to this study. Participants will be&#xD;
      excluded if they have a history of brain injury or epilepsy, visual/auditory deficit or were&#xD;
      diagnosed as having motor disorder, obsessive-compulsive disorder, mental retardation, and&#xD;
      depression. In order to recruit a population of pure ADHD (without other psychiatric&#xD;
      comorbidities), children who are comorbid with oppositional defiant disorder (ODD) or conduct&#xD;
      disorder (CD) were excluded, though the concurrence of ODD/CD and ADHD were high. Normal&#xD;
      controls will be recruited from the local elementary school in the same geographical area.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Measurements Considering the age group selected and symptoms of ADHD, we selected&#xD;
      measurements carefully to ensure that all participants will be able to complete every task&#xD;
      without getting fatigued or being distractive in the task.&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Chinese version of the Kiddie-Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia-&#xD;
           epidemiology version (K-SADS-E) Development of the Chinese K-SADS-E was carried out by&#xD;
           the Child Psychiatry Research Group in Taiwan, which included a two-stage translation&#xD;
           and modification of several items with psycholinguistic equivalents relevant to the&#xD;
           Taiwanese culture. The K-SADS-E has been widely used in a variety of studies on the&#xD;
           mental illness of children and adolescents in Taiwan (Gau et al., 2005). Mother will be&#xD;
           interviewed independently by two separate interviewers to make child's psychiatric&#xD;
           diagnoses.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children Short Form (WISC-III short form) WISC-III&#xD;
           (Wechsler, 1991) is a well established scale designed to assess the Full-Scale IQ (FSIQ)&#xD;
           of children under age of 16. It includes 13 subtests to test children's cognitive&#xD;
           ability of different dimensions. Test result is represented by Verbal IQ, Performance&#xD;
           IQ, and Full-Scale IQ. The present research conducted a quad combination of WISC short&#xD;
           form including subtests of Symbol Search, Arithmetic, Block Design, and Verbal. Previous&#xD;
           research suggested the mentioned combination have good reliability (rxx = .91) and&#xD;
           validity (rxx = .90) (Silverstein, 1982), and is preferred while conducting research to&#xD;
           estimate FSIQ.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Neuropsychological measures Five neuropsychological measures which consist of 19 task&#xD;
           variables will be used.&#xD;
&#xD;
           Cancellation Test (Rudel et al., 1978) Cancellation Test is a two-part paper-and-pencil&#xD;
           measure of visual scanning. Number Cancellation requires subject to strike out a&#xD;
           three-digit target (257) intermittently placed in a large array of numbers; Shape&#xD;
           Cancellation required subject to strike out a target shape (star) intermittently place&#xD;
           in a filed of other shapes. The total number of commission error, correct hits, and&#xD;
           completed time on the two separate tests will be recorded. Completion time divided by&#xD;
           the number is calculated as one of the indices.&#xD;
&#xD;
           Digit Span The assessor first requires subjects to repeat orally presented digit strings&#xD;
           (Digit Forward) and then recall digits in backwards sequence (Digit Backward). This task&#xD;
           represents the indices of sensory selection and capacity/focus components, in the&#xD;
           present research.&#xD;
&#xD;
           Trail Making Test (TMT; Reitan &amp; Wolfson, 1986) A brief paper-and-pencil test involving&#xD;
           numeric sequencing (Trail A) followed by alpha-numeric sequencing (Trail B) in original&#xD;
           form. The Trail B was modified by using Chinese phonic symbols to substitute for English&#xD;
           alphabet when applying to Chinese participants. Completed time and off-target errors on&#xD;
           the tasks are oriented to the attentional components of sensory selection, response&#xD;
           selection, and capacity/focus.&#xD;
&#xD;
           Continuous Performance Test (CPT; Conners, 1995) The CPT requires tabbing on the space&#xD;
           key when any character other than X shown on the screen. There were six sets in total,&#xD;
           with 20 characters within each set. The Inter-Stimulus Intervals (ISIs) are 1, 2, and 4&#xD;
           seconds, and different ISIs varied between sets. Each character maintains on the screen&#xD;
           for 250 ms. Correct hits, omission errors, commission errors, and reaction times will be&#xD;
           collected as indices of response selection and capacity/focus. The d' value known as a&#xD;
           discriminate factor is one of the indices for sustained attention.&#xD;
&#xD;
           Circle Tracing Test (CTT, Bachorowski &amp; Newman, 1985) This task requires subjects to&#xD;
           trace a large printed circle (20 inches in diameter) with their index finger to measure&#xD;
           inhibition of an ongoing response (eg. Geurts et al, 2004; Scheres et al., 2003). The&#xD;
           word START (in green ink) was printed on the right side of the line and the word STOP&#xD;
           (in red ink) was printed on the left side. The task was administered under two&#xD;
           conditions: first with neutral instruction ('trace the circle') followed by inhibition&#xD;
           instruction ('trace the circle again, but as slow as you can this time') within 12&#xD;
           minutes without subject's knowledge. The dependent variable on this task included time 1&#xD;
           under neutral instruction, time 2 under inhibition instruction, time discrepancy&#xD;
           referred to time 2 minus time 1, and a three-point (0-2) degree of deviation score&#xD;
           assessed by the trained observer. The larger the time discrepancy, the better a&#xD;
           participant is able to inhibit (slow down) the continuous tracing response.&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. Measures of behavior symptoms Subjects' parent will complete the SNAP-IV and a trained&#xD;
           rater will observe the subjects' behaviors and rate on two behavioral scales during the&#xD;
           tasks.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Swanson, Nolan, and Pelham IV scale (SNAP-IV, Swanson et al., 2001) The SNAP-IV is a 26-item&#xD;
      rating scale consisting of the DSM-IV symptoms for the Inattention (Item 1-9) and the&#xD;
      Hyperactivity/Impulsivity domains (Item 10-18) of the criteria for ADHD, and the oppositional&#xD;
      symptoms (Item 19-26) of the criteria for ODD. Several studies have used different versions&#xD;
      of the SNAP, either parent or teacher form, as an outcome measure to assess the efficacy of&#xD;
      treatment for ADHD (e.g., Steele et al., 2006). Regarding psychometric properties of the SNAP&#xD;
      rating scale, the Chinese version of SNAP-IV showed satisfactory test-retest reliability&#xD;
      (intraclass correlation= 0.59~0.72), internal consistency (alpha=0.88~0.90), concurrent&#xD;
      validity (Pearson correlations = 0.56~0.72), and discriminant validity (Liu et al., 2006).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Clinical Global Impression (CGI, NIMH, 1976) CGI, a three-item scale including Severity of&#xD;
      Illness, Global Improvement, and Efficacy Index, is used to assess treatment response in&#xD;
      psychiatric patients. The Severity of Illness with 7-point scale (1 = normal to 7 = extremely&#xD;
      ill) will be used in this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Behavior Observation Ratings This is a four-point (0 = not at all to 3 = extremely much)&#xD;
      rating scales with three items assessing children's behaviors during the task. The three&#xD;
      target behaviors to be observed are &quot;unsteady while remaining seated,&quot; &quot;murmuring during&#xD;
      task,&quot; and &quot;given up easily&quot; before and after one dose of methylphenidate.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Procedure We will obtain written informed consent of all subjects from both children and&#xD;
      their parents. The day prior to the date of receiving neuropsychological tasks, children will&#xD;
      be asked to halt medication in order to obtain their test results as baseline data to make&#xD;
      comparison with their performance after treatment with MPH.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The testing procedure is as follows: (1) All children (ADHD group and normal controls) will&#xD;
      be assessed IQ and a series of neuropsychological assessments. Their parents will complete&#xD;
      the SNAP-IV scale at the same time. (2) After that, children with ADHD will take IR MPH (at&#xD;
      the same dose as their prescription) and rest for approximately 45 minutes. Meanwhile,&#xD;
      parents of children with ADHD will be interviewed with K-SADS-E by trained interviewer. (3)&#xD;
      Children with ADHD will then be re-assessed CPT. CGI and Behavior observation will be&#xD;
      assessed.&#xD;
&#xD;
      ANTICIPATED RESULT We anticipated that children in the ADHD and non-ADHD group will perform&#xD;
      differently on the neuropsychological tests with more deficits in neuropsychological&#xD;
      functions in the ADHD group. Also, we expected that methylphenidate will improve the&#xD;
      performance on the neuropsychological tests and reduce the behavioral symptoms of ADHD&#xD;
      children. Subtypes difference in the neuropsychological functions is also expected.&#xD;
&#xD;
      CONCLUSION The present research aims to inspect the effect of methylphenidate on behavioral&#xD;
      measures and neuropsychological function among children with ADHD in Taiwan. Understanding&#xD;
      the treatment effect among neuropsychological function and different behavior may help us&#xD;
      clear out the psychopathology of ADHD. Learning the possible difference among subtypes&#xD;
      regarding the relationship of treatment and self-report outcome will benefit in that matter&#xD;
      as well.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2006</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">122</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention-deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        children with ADHD&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patients who have clinically diagnosis of DSM-IV ADHD confirmed by the K-SADS-E, are&#xD;
             aged 7-10, and have IQ &gt; 80; and who and whose parents consent to this study&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  if they have a history of brain injury or epilepsy, visual/auditory deficit or were&#xD;
             diagnosed as having motor disorder, obsessive-compulsive disorder, mental retardation,&#xD;
             mood disorders, pervasive developmental disorder, or schizophrenia&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan Shur-Fen Gau, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Taiwan University Hospital &amp; College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Taiwan Univeristy Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>10002</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2008</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 2, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 12, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 12, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 14, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ADHD, subtype, methylphenidate, neuropsychological measures</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

