<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00490425</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JHGU-195/02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00490425</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Asthma and Allergy by Probiotic Lactobacillus GG</brief_title>
  <acronym>FRALAC</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Lactbacillus GG on Wheeze and Allergic Sensitization in Infants at Risk</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johann Wolfgang Goethe University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johann Wolfgang Goethe University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Given that asthma results from a complex interaction between genetic susceptibility and&#xD;
      environmental factors and rates of childhood asthma are increasing, primary prevention has to&#xD;
      focus on modifiable aspects such as nutrition. There a implications from epidemiology that&#xD;
      food supplementation with probiotics given to atopic mothers in pregnancy and during&#xD;
      lactation can prevent the development allergies in the offspring. Children with atopic&#xD;
      dermatitis are at increased risk (up to 80%) of developing persistent respiratory tract&#xD;
      disease. Our trial examined whether probiotics are able to prevent allergic sensitization and&#xD;
      allergic asthma when given to 6-24 month old infants at an increased risk of allergies.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In our investigator-initiated prospective study, a total of 170 children with at least two&#xD;
      episodes of wheezing and a first degree family history of atopic disease were recruited from&#xD;
      our walk-in clinic between October 2002 and October 2004. We chose this relatively long&#xD;
      period of time to exclude a seasonal selection bias (e.g., upper airway infections or&#xD;
      airborne allergens). 131 eligible children (6 to 24 month old) were randomly assigned to a&#xD;
      double-blind dietary supplementation with Lactobacillus rhamnosus strain GG ATCC 53103 (LGG)&#xD;
      twice daily or placebo over six months. A computerized randomization schedule was prepared by&#xD;
      a biostatistician with allocation and dispensing of capsules by the distributor of LGG. The&#xD;
      capsules were matched for size, shape, and volume of content, which was reconstituted with 5&#xD;
      ml water and then given by spoon. Compliance was monitored by use of a capsule chart&#xD;
      (completed by parents) and capsule counts. The parents were asked to keep a diary provided by&#xD;
      the study group. Clinical monitoring was done for one year: before the intervention (visit&#xD;
      1), after 3, 6, 9, and 12 months (visit 2 to 5). It encompassed episodes of asthmatic&#xD;
      exacerbations defined as cough and wheeze, numbers and days of associated hospitalizations,&#xD;
      symptom free days, days without use of rescue medication (steroid suppositoria, a frequently&#xD;
      used device in Western Europe), and associated inhalative steroid and beta-agonist use.&#xD;
      Children underwent a physical examination including determination of the severity scoring of&#xD;
      atopic dermatitis (SCORAD) index to assess eczema severity examination on each study visit to&#xD;
      our walk-in clinic. To ensure consistency, the same investigator performed all SCORAD&#xD;
      assessments. Atopic eczema was confirmed by characteristical cutaneous findings, pruritus,&#xD;
      and chronic relapsing course. This last criterion was fulfilled if the child presented eczema&#xD;
      for at least one month on at least one visit. Asthma diagnosis was based on an algorithm from&#xD;
      an international paediatric asthma consensus group. Asthma was diagnosed if the child had&#xD;
      chronic or recurrent cough, wheeze or shortness of breath, or both, and if other diagnosis&#xD;
      were excluded and trial antiasthmatic treatment was effective. Blood samples were taken on&#xD;
      visit 1, 3, and 5. Sensitization to common dietary and respiratory allergen was measured by&#xD;
      total and antigen specific IgE assays against hen's egg, cat epithelia, house dust mite&#xD;
      (D1+2), birch pollen, milk protein, lactalbumin, timothy pollen, horse epithelia and&#xD;
      alternaria by chemiluminescence-immunoassay. This highly-sensitive assay is suitable&#xD;
      especially for the determination of low value of specific IgE. Additionally, eosinophilic&#xD;
      cationic protein and eosinophils were determined.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Primary outcome measures were the asthma-related clinical events. Secondary measures were the&#xD;
      serum concentrations of IgE, specific IgE, ECP, Eos, IL-2 soluble receptor alpha (IL-2Rα, to&#xD;
      reflect T-cell related inflammatory state) and transforming growth factor beta (TGFβ, a&#xD;
      profibrotic factor whose expression is increased in asthmatics, indicating airway remodeling.&#xD;
      All parents supplied written informed consent prior to the study. Human experimentation&#xD;
      guidelines of Good Clinical Practice, the German Drug Act and the declaration of Helsinki /&#xD;
      Hong Kong were followed in the conduct of clinical research.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>episodes of wheezing, drug use (inhalative steroids and betamimetics), hospital treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>October 2002 - October 2004</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>allergic sensitization, levels of IgE, inflammatory mediators, SCORAD indices</measure>
    <time_frame>October 2002-October 2004</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">131</enrollment>
  <condition>Allergic Asthma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lactobacillus rhamnosus strain GG ATCC 53103 (LGG, 1010 cfu)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of at least 3 episodes of wheezing bronchitis,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  First degree relative with history of allergic disease&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Congenital malformations,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Immunologic or oncologic systemic disorders,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current antibiotic therapy,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Prior exposure to probiotics; and&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Known intolerances towards ingredients of the probiotics (LGG, microcristalline&#xD;
             cellulose, gelatine, magnesiumstearate, titandioxide).&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stefan Zielen, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Goethe University, Childrens' Hospital, Dpt Allergy/Pulmonology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Childrens' Hospital, Goethe University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt</city>
        <state>Hessen</state>
        <zip>60590</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalliomaki M, Salminen S, Poussa T, Arvilommi H, Isolauri E. Probiotics and prevention of atopic disease: 4-year follow-up of a randomised placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2003 May 31;361(9372):1869-71. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(03)13490-3.</citation>
    <PMID>12788576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2007</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 21, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 21, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>probiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>LGG</keyword>
  <keyword>praevention</keyword>
  <keyword>allergic asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

