<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00490087</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC 23/98</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00490087</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Resectoscopic Treatment of Atypical Endometrial Polyps in Fertile Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Operational Hysteroscopy Versus Traditional Surgery: Costs and Health Benefits</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>IRCCS Burlo Garofolo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>IRCCS Burlo Garofolo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aims to evaluate the long-term efficacy and prognosis of hysteroscopic resection&#xD;
      and coagulation of the base of endometrial polyps with focal atypia in fertile women.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The introduction of hysteroscopy in clinical practice changed significantly our knowledge of&#xD;
      uterine cavity, but did not stimulate the start of big studies with aim to evaluate the&#xD;
      feasibility of conservative treatments for better defined diseases as endometrial polyp. The&#xD;
      use of curettage(D&amp;C) has led the gynecologists to consider diffuse atypical endometrial&#xD;
      hyperplasia and atypical polyp as the same disease. The treatment of these precancerous&#xD;
      lesions recommended by scientific societies is aggressive (hysterectomy). Surprisingly,&#xD;
      regarding hysterectomy we did not observe management modifications after the introduction of&#xD;
      endoscopic techniques, as happened in other surgical disciplines.&#xD;
&#xD;
      To evaluate costs and health benefits of operational hysteroscopy we started in our Institute&#xD;
      a study protocol in 1998. In a first trial we studied a conservative treatment of&#xD;
      postmenopausal woman with high anesthesiologic risk who had endometrial polyps with atypia&#xD;
      and no involvement of the base (Scrimin F. Am J Obstet Gynecol 2006;195:1328-30).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The good initial results and the request of conservative treatments by some women, desiring&#xD;
      pregnancies, encouraged us to start this preliminary trial to evaluate the long-term efficacy&#xD;
      and prognosis of hysteroscopic resection and coagulation of the base of endometrial polyps&#xD;
      with focal atypia in a little sample of fertile women. Other studies suggest progestin&#xD;
      treatment of well differentiated carcinoma in young women who desired to preserve their&#xD;
      fertility. There is no evidence of a correlation between the tendency to develop endometrial&#xD;
      polyps and the risk of endometrial carcinoma. The risk of malignant degeneration of&#xD;
      endometrial polyps is not well known, but seems to range between 0.5% and 6%. On this&#xD;
      background, we decided to study in the same population of fertile women and with a&#xD;
      quasi-randomised design the possible additional effect of levonorgestrel-releasing&#xD;
      intrauterine device (LNG-IUD).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Comparison: women assigned to odd numbers underwent polyp resection and endometrial&#xD;
      surveillance with insertion of levonorgestrel intrauterine system (IUD group), women assigned&#xD;
      to even numbers underwent polyp resection and endometrial surveillance without insertion of&#xD;
      levonorgestrel intrauterine system (no IUD or control group).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy and prognosis of hysteroscopic resection of atypical polyps in terms of appearance of endometrial cancer or recurrence of atypical endometrial lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence rate of polyp in the two groups</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Atypical Endometrial Polyps</condition>
  <condition>Atypical Endometrial Hyperplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hysteroscopic resection plus IUD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hysteroscopic resection without IUD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levonorgestrel intrauterine device (IUD)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Hysteroscopic resection plus IUD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  women in fertile age desiring to preserve their uterus&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  atypical polyps, without atypia in the base. The hysteroscopic and histologic criteria&#xD;
             for inclusion in the study were: proliferative, secretive, dysfunctional endometrium&#xD;
             or simple hyperplasia in 4 random biopsies.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  women with adenomatous or atypical hyperplasia in the random biopsies&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Federica Scrimin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Child Health IRCCS Burlo Garofolo, Trieste, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Child Health, IRCCS Burlo Garofolo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Trieste</city>
        <state>Friuli Venezia Giulia</state>
        <zip>34137</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Scrimin F, Wiesenfeld U, Candiotto A, Inglese S, Ronfani L, Guaschino S. Resectoscopic treatment of atypical endometrial polyps in fertile women. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2008 Oct;199(4):365.e1-3. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2008.03.041.</citation>
    <PMID>18928975</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2007</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 20, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 1, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 1, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 2, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Atypical endometrial polyps</keyword>
  <keyword>Atypical Endometrial Hyperplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hysteroscopic resection</keyword>
  <keyword>Conservative treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Fertile women</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polyps</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Levonorgestrel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

