<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 03, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00495066</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CA184-045</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00495066</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Compassionate Use Trial for Unresectable Melanoma With Ipilimumab</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter Treatment Protocol for Expanded Access Use of Ipilimumab (BMS-734016) Monotherapy in Subjects With Unresectable Stage III or Stage IV Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bristol-Myers Squibb</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study is to provide treatment with Ipilimumab to subjects who&#xD;
      have serious or immediately life-threatening unresectable Stage III or Stage IV melanoma, who&#xD;
      have no alternative treatment options, and whose physicians believe, based upon available&#xD;
      data on benefit and risk, that it is appropriate to administer Ipilimumab at a dose of 3&#xD;
      mg/kg induction (with re-induction, if eligible), or for eligible subjects previously&#xD;
      enrolled in Ipilimumab studies CA184-042, CA184-078, CA184-087, MDX010-16, or MDX010-20.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>No longer available</overall_status>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous Solution, Intravenous, Ipilimumab 3 mg/kg, Ipilimumab - one dose every 3 wks for a total of 4 doses. Subjects who are eligible may receive another 4 doses given every 3 wks; Until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or withdrawal of consent</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Signed Written Informed Consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Histologically confirmed Stage III (unresectable) or Stage IV melanoma&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Must have failed at least one systemic therapy for malignant melanoma or be intolerant&#xD;
             to at least one prior systemic treatment. Note: Enrollees must not be eligible for a&#xD;
             clinical study with Ipilimumab&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects with asymptomatic brain metastases are eligible&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Primary ocular and mucosal melanomas are allowed&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Must be at least 28 days since treatment with chemotherapy, biochemotherapy, or&#xD;
             immunotherapy, and recovered from any clinically significant toxicity experienced&#xD;
             during treatment. Must have recovered from prior surgery or radiation. Systemic&#xD;
             corticosteroids should be eliminated or weaned to the minimum dose before starting&#xD;
             Ipilimumab treatment. Consult with the Medical Monitor for individual subjects&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) 0- 2&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Life expectancy ≥ 16 weeks&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects must have the complete set of baseline (screening/baseline) radiographic&#xD;
             images, including but not limited to brain, chest, abdomen, and pelvis. Bone scans&#xD;
             should be completed if clinically indicated. The images can be accepted if obtained 6&#xD;
             weeks before initiation of Ipilimumab&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Required values for initial laboratory tests:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. White Blood Cells (WBC): ≥ 2000/uL (≥ 2 x 10*9*/L)&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Antigen Neutrophil Count (ANC): ≥ 1000/uL (≥ 1 x 10*9*/L)&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Platelets: ≥ 75 x 103/uL (≥ 75 x 10*9*/L)&#xD;
&#xD;
               4. Hemoglobin: ≥ 9 g/dL (≥ 80 g/L; may be transfused)&#xD;
&#xD;
               5. Creatinine: ≤ 2.0 x ULN&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Aspartate Aminotransferase (AST)/Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT):≤ 2.5 x Upper Limit of&#xD;
             Normal (ULN) for subjects without liver metastasis ≤ 5 times for liver metastases&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Bilirubin: ≤ 2.0 x ULN (except for subjects with Gilbert's Syndrome, who must have a&#xD;
             total bilirubin of less than 3.0 mg/dL)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Men and women, at least 16 years of age&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Prior treatment with an anti-Cytotoxic T-lymphocyte Associated Protein 4 (CTLA-4) drug&#xD;
             is allowed provided therapy was not discontinued to to drug-related toxicity&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) and their partners must use highly effective&#xD;
             methods of birth control (double barrier, e.g, condom or diaphragm or cervical cap&#xD;
             associated with spermicide or intrauterine device combined with another form of birth&#xD;
             control) for up to 12 weeks after the last dose of study drug to minimize the risk of&#xD;
             pregnancy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  WOCBP must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test (minimum sensitivity 25 IU/L&#xD;
             or equivalent units of HCG) at Screening and within 24 hours prior to the start of&#xD;
             investigational product&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Women who are not of childbearing potential (i.e., who are postmenopausal or&#xD;
             surgically sterile&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Men of fathering potential must be using an adequate method of contraception to avoid&#xD;
             conception throughout the study and for up to 12 weeks after the last dose of&#xD;
             investigational product in such a manner that the risk of pregnancy is minimized&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Women of Child-Bearing Potential (WOCBP) who are unwilling or unable to use an&#xD;
             acceptable method to avoid pregnancy for the entire study and for up to 12 weeks after&#xD;
             the last dose of investigational product&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  WOCBP using a prohibited contraceptive method&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Women with a positive pregnancy test on enrollment or before investigational product&#xD;
             administration&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects on any other systemic therapy for cancer, including any other experimental&#xD;
             treatment&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Prior treatment with an anti CTLA 4 antibody if treatment failure was due to&#xD;
             Immune-Related Adverse Events (irAEs) or discontinuation was due to an Adverse Event&#xD;
             (AE)/Serious Adverse Event (SAE)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any subject enrolled in a registrational study (ie, CA184024) that has a survival&#xD;
             endpoint should not be enrolled in CA184-045. Also, if a subject is eligible for a&#xD;
             treatment study, he or she is not eligible for this study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Presence of active autoimmune disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Presence of known hepatitis B or hepatitis C (active) infection, regardless of control&#xD;
             on antiviral therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any subject who has a life threatening condition that requires high-dose&#xD;
             immunosuppressants&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects with melanoma who have another active, concurrent, malignant disease, with&#xD;
             the exception of adequately treated basal or squamous cell skin cancer, superficial&#xD;
             bladder cancer, or carcinoma in situ of the cervix&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any non-oncology vaccine therapy used for prevention of infectious diseases for up to&#xD;
             4 weeks before or after any dose of Ipilimumab, with the exceptions of Amantadine and&#xD;
             Flumadine&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any subject enrolled in a registrational study (ie, CA184-024) that has a survival as&#xD;
             a primary endpoint should not be enrolled in CA184-045. Also, if a subject is eligible&#xD;
             for a treatment study, he or she is not eligible for this study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects from studies CA184-042, CA184-078 or CA184-087, who are being followed for&#xD;
             survival only or for scans only are not eligible for this study&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bristol-Myers Squibb</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bristol-Myers Squibb</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto ÉTICA - AMO - Assistência Multidisciplinar em Oncologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salvador</city>
        <state>Bahia</state>
        <zip>41950-610</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto do Cancer do Ceara</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fortaleza</city>
        <state>Ceara</state>
        <zip>60930-230</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Sao Lucas das PUCRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <state>Rio Grande do Sul (RS)</state>
        <zip>90610-000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Mae de Deus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <state>Rio Grande do Sul (RS)</state>
        <zip>90840440</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Amaral Carvalho hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jau</city>
        <state>Sao Paulo</state>
        <zip>17210-120</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fundacao Pio XI - Hospital De Cancer De Barretos</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barretos</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>14784-400</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital A. C. Camargo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>01509-900</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Sao Jose - Beneficencia Portuguesa - Oncology Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>CEP 01321-001</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto Nacional de Cancer - INCA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rio de Janeiro</city>
        <zip>20231-050</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Argentina</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Puerto Rico</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bms.com/clinical_trials/Pages/home.aspx</url>
    <description>BMS Clinical Trials Disclosure</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch/SafetyInformation/default.htm</url>
    <description>FDA Safety Alerts and Recalls</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 2, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 30, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 30, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 3, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ipilimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

